<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17183632</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1762354</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">06-PONE-RA-00017R1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0000010</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Infectious Diseases</subject><subject>Pediatrics and Child Health</subject><subject>Public Health and Epidemiology</subject><subject>Microbiology/Medical Microbiology</subject><subject>Infectious Diseases/Bacterial Infections</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Differences between Belgian and Brazilian Group A Streptococcus Epidemiologic Landscape</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">GAS Epidemiology Differences</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Smeesters</surname><given-names>Pierre Robert</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="n101">
<sup>&#x0002a;</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vergison</surname><given-names>Anne</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>Diocl&#x000e9;cio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Aguiar</surname><given-names>Eurico</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Deyi</surname><given-names>Veronique Yvette Miendje</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Van Melderen</surname><given-names>Laurence</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<institution>Infectious Diseases Department, H&#x000f4;pital Universitaire des Enfants Reine Fabiola, Universit&#x000e9; Libre de Bruxelles</institution>
<addr-line>Brussels, Belgium</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<institution>Laboratoire de G&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;tique des Procaryotes, Institut de Biologie et de M&#x000e9;decine Mol&#x000e9;culaires, Universit&#x000e9; Libre de Bruxelles</institution>
<addr-line>Brussels, Belgium</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<institution>Pediatric Department, Hospital Universit&#x000e1;rio de Bras&#x000ed;lia, Universidade de Bras&#x000ed;lia</institution>
<addr-line>Bras&#x000ed;lia, Brazil</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<institution>Epidemiology and Infection Control Unit, H&#x000f4;pital Universitaire des Enfants Reine Fabiola, Universit&#x000e9; Libre de Bruxelles</institution>
<addr-line>Brussels, Belgium</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff5">
<label>5</label>
<institution>Microbiology Department, Hospital Regional da Asa Sul</institution>
<addr-line>Bras&#x000ed;lia, Brazil</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff6">
<label>6</label>
<institution>Microbiology Department, Centre Hospitalier Universitaire Brugmann, Universit&#x000e9; Libre de Bruxelles</institution>
<addr-line>Brussels, Belgium</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>del Poeta</surname><given-names>Maurizio</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Medical University of South Carolina, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="n101">&#x0002a; To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email>psmeeste@ulb.ac.be</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: LV PS AV DC. Performed the experiments: PS. Analyzed the data: LV PS AV DC. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: LV PS AV EdA VM. Wrote the paper: LV PS AV. Other: Supervised lab work: LV. Enrolled patients: PS AV EdA VM. Approved final version of the manuscript: LV AV DC EdA VM.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2006</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e10</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>8</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>9</month><year>2006</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Smeesters et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2006</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Group A Streptococcus (GAS) clinical and molecular epidemiology varies with location and time. These differences are not or are poorly understood.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods and Findings</title><p>We prospectively studied the epidemiology of GAS infections among children in outpatient hospital clinics in Brussels (Belgium) and Bras&#x000ed;lia (Brazil). Clinical questionnaires were filled out and microbiological sampling was performed. GAS isolates were <italic>emm</italic>-typed according to the Center for Disease Control protocol. <italic>emm</italic> pattern was predicted for each isolate. 334 GAS isolates were recovered from 706 children. Skin infections were frequent in Bras&#x000ed;lia (48&#x00025; of the GAS infections), whereas pharyngitis were predominant (88&#x00025;) in Brussels. The mean age of children with GAS pharyngitis in Brussels was lower than in Bras&#x000ed;lia (65/92 months, p&#x0003c;0.001). <italic>emm</italic>-typing revealed striking differences between Brazilian and Belgian GAS isolates. While 20 distinct <italic>emm</italic>-types were identified among 200 Belgian isolates, 48 were found among 128 Brazilian isolates. Belgian isolates belong mainly to <italic>emm</italic> pattern A&#x02013;C (55&#x00025;) and E (42.5&#x00025;) while <italic>emm</italic> pattern E (51.5&#x00025;) and D (36&#x00025;) were predominant in Bras&#x000ed;lia. In Bras&#x000ed;lia, <italic>emm</italic> pattern D isolates were recovered from 18.5&#x00025; of the pharyngitis, although this <italic>emm</italic> pattern is supposed to have a skin tropism. By contrast, A&#x02013;C pattern isolates were unfrequently recovered in a region where rheumatic fever is still highly prevalent.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Epidemiologic features of GAS from a pediatric population were very different in an industrialised country and a low incomes region, not only in term of clinical presentation, but also in terms of genetic diversity and distribution of <italic>emm</italic> patterns. These differences should be taken into account for designing treatment guidelines and vaccine strategies.</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="5"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The incidence of Group A Streptococcus (GAS) diseases vary with location and time. Rheumatic fever is still a major cause of cardiovascular morbidity and mortality in developing countries <xref rid="pone.0000010-Carapetis1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0000010-Stollerman1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, while it has become uncommon in the industrialized world. Pharyngitis occurs predominantly during the cold season in temperate climates and is less frequent in tropical regions <xref rid="pone.0000010-Carapetis2" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. By contrast, skin infections are described at a much higher rate in developing countries than in rich western nations <xref rid="pone.0000010-Carapetis2" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0000010-Kaplan1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. These epidemiological differences are not or poorly understood.</p><p>Molecular GAS typing (<italic>emm</italic> typing) is based on the 5&#x02032; end sequence of the <italic>emm</italic> gene that encodes the hyper variable amino-terminal part of the M protein. This surface protein is a major virulence factor and acts as a protective antigen <xref rid="pone.0000010-Bisno1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Currently, more than 170 recognized <italic>emm</italic>-types, constituting more than 750 sub-types, have been described (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/ncidod/biotech/strep/emmtypes.htm">http://www.cdc.gov/ncidod/biotech/strep/emmtypes.htm</ext-link>). Molecular epidemiological data are available for Western countries where a limited number of specific <italic>emm</italic>-types are predominant. Although few comprehensive and prospective studies have been performed in developing countries <xref rid="pone.0000010-Carapetis1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, a high diversity of <italic>emm</italic>-types has been described in certain locations <xref rid="pone.0000010-Dey1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0000010-Sakota1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>.</p><p>The <italic>emm</italic> pattern serves as a genotypic marker to classify GAS strains according to their tissue tropism (skin or throat). It is based on the organization of <italic>emm</italic> and <italic>emm</italic>-like genes located in the <italic>mga</italic> locus <xref rid="pone.0000010-McGregor1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0000010-Bessen1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. The <italic>emm</italic> pattern A&#x02013;C strains are usually recovered from the throat isolates, whereas strains presenting an <italic>emm</italic> pattern D are most often isolated from the skin. &#x0201c;Generalist&#x0201d; <italic>emm</italic> pattern E strains are associated with both tissue sites. Rheumatic fever has been historically associated with strains belonging to <italic>emm</italic> pattern A&#x02013;C <xref rid="pone.0000010-Cunningham1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. However, the correlation between <italic>emm</italic> pattern and site of isolation has not always been confirmed in developing countries, where rheumatic fever is still endemic <xref rid="pone.0000010-Sakota1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0000010-Bessen1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. In Nepal, for instance, A&#x02013;C strains were preferentially recovered from skin infections <xref rid="pone.0000010-Sakota1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. These data indicate no definitive association between GAS <italic>emm</italic> pattern groups and the site of infection and/or the ability to cause a specific disease.</p><p>These epidemiological differences prompted us to conduct a comparative study between an industrialized country (Belgium) and a developing country (Brazil).</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>1) Clinical Epidemiology</title><p>706 children (360 in Brussels, 346 in Bras&#x000ed;lia) with various streptococcal manifestations were included in the study. No significant difference in the mean number of children under the same roof was observed between Bras&#x000ed;lia (2.2 children) and Brussels (2 children). 334 GAS isolates (204 in Brussels, 161 of which were reported from the laboratory and clinical data completed retrospectively; and 130 in Bras&#x000ed;lia) were recovered from the 706 children. In Brussels, 94&#x00025; of the GAS isolates were recovered from the throat or external ear (pharyngitis, scarlet fever and otitis) while cutaneous infections were rare (3&#x00025;). We observed two GAS invasive infections. In Bras&#x000ed;lia, GAS were isolated equally from cutaneous infections and pharyngitis. There were 5 GAS invasive infections and 1 sequela (post-streptococcal glomerulonephritis).</p><sec id="s2a1"><title>Risk factors for pharyngitis and impetigo</title><p>The percentage of clinically diagnosed pharyngitis associated with GAS positive culture was higher in Bras&#x000ed;lia (26&#x00025;) than in Brussels (20&#x00025;) (p&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0,13). In Bras&#x000ed;lia, the percentage of positive culture varied with the age of children: 32&#x00025;, 18&#x00025; and 0&#x00025; of the children older than 59 months, from 36 to 59 month old and under 36 month old presented a GAS pharyngitis respectively (p&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.003) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000010-g001">Figure 1</xref>). In Brussels, the prevalence of GAS pharyngitis was unchanged from 15 month old to 13 year old. The mean age of children with GAS pharyngitis was 7.6 year old (ranging from 38 to 153 months) in Bras&#x000ed;lia and 5.4 year old (ranging from 15 to 150 months) in Brussels (<italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.001). Nutrition indices, crowding, sex or previous antibiotherapy did not constitute a risk for GAS pharyngitis in both Brussels and Bras&#x000ed;lia.</p><fig id="pone-0000010-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0000010.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Distribution of GAS pharyngitis according to age in Brussels and Bras&#x000ed;lia.</title><p>Percentage of positive GAS throat culture for different age categories of children with pharyngitis. p&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0,003 for the comparison between the three age groups in Bras&#x000ed;lia.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0000010.g001"/></fig><p>61&#x00025; of impetigo were associated with a GAS positive culture in Bras&#x000ed;lia. These streptococcal skin infections were not related to age, sex, crowding, nutrition indices and previous antibiotic treatment during the last six months. The small number of impetigo in Brussels did not allow any statistical analyses.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>2) Molecular Epidemiology</title><sec id="s2b1"><title>
<italic>emm</italic>-types and <italic>emm</italic>-patterns distribution</title><p>The <italic>emm</italic>-type was successfully determined for 200 of the 204 Belgian isolates and 128 of the 130 Brazilian ones. Among the 200 isolates recovered in Brussels, 20 different <italic>emm</italic>-types were identified (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000010-g002">figure 2</xref> and table S1). A predominance of 6 <italic>emm</italic>-types, which accounted for 75&#x00025; of the isolates, was observed in Brussels (<italic>emm</italic> 6 (20&#x00025;), <italic>emm</italic> 1 (14&#x00025;), <italic>emm</italic> 12 (12&#x00025;), <italic>emm</italic> 89 (11&#x00025;), <italic>emm</italic> 4 (11&#x00025;) and <italic>emm</italic> 3 (8&#x00025;)). 55&#x00025; and 42.5&#x00025; of the GAS isolates were classified into <italic>emm</italic> patterns A&#x02013;C and E respectively, whereas only 0.5&#x00025; presented an <italic>emm</italic> pattern D.</p><fig id="pone-0000010-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0000010.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>
<italic>emm</italic>-types distribution in Brussels and Bras&#x000ed;lia.</title><p>The distribution of the <italic>emm</italic>-types is oligoclonal in Brussels (20 <italic>emm</italic>-types among 200 isolates) and polyclonal in Bras&#x000ed;lia (48 <italic>emm</italic>-types among 128 isolates). Moreover, the <italic>emm</italic>-types involved were different.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0000010.g002"/></fig><p>Among the 128 isolates recovered in Bras&#x000ed;lia which were typed, 48 different <italic>emm</italic>-types were identified (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000010-g002">figure 2</xref> and table S2). None of these <italic>emm</italic>-type was predominant. The most frequent <italic>emm</italic>-type (<italic>emm</italic> 53) represented only 8.5&#x00025; of the Brazilian isolates. The 6 most prevalent <italic>emm</italic>-types (<italic>emm</italic> 53, <italic>emm</italic> 22, <italic>emm</italic> 49, <italic>emm</italic> 58, <italic>emm</italic> 83, <italic>emm</italic> 8) among the Brazilian GAS isolates accounted for only 36&#x00025; of the total number of GAS isolates and nearly half of the <italic>emm</italic>-types (22/48) were represented by a single isolate. <italic>emm</italic> patterns E, D and A-C accounted for 51.5&#x00025;, 36&#x00025; and 9.5&#x00025; of the Brazilian isolates respectively.</p><p>15 <italic>emm</italic>-types (<italic>emm</italic> 1, <italic>emm</italic> 2, <italic>emm</italic> 3, <italic>emm</italic> 4, <italic>emm</italic> 6, <italic>emm</italic> 11, <italic>emm</italic> 12, <italic>emm</italic> 28, <italic>emm</italic> 44/61, <italic>emm</italic> 58, <italic>emm</italic> 64, <italic>emm</italic> 75, <italic>emm</italic> 87, <italic>emm</italic> 94 and <italic>emm</italic> st1815) were recovered from children in both Brussels (15/20 <italic>emm</italic>-types, 84&#x00025; of the isolates) and Bras&#x000ed;lia (15/48, 27&#x00025; of the isolates).</p></sec><sec id="s2b2"><title>New <italic>emm</italic> sub-types</title><p>8 new <italic>emm</italic> sub-types were identified. The 6 Brazilian new <italic>emm</italic> sub-types represented 7&#x00025; of the isolates. They differed from the reference strains by a single nucleotide change. In Brussels, we found 2 new sub-types. One differed by a single substitution and the other by a 7 nucleotides change from the reference strains.</p></sec><sec id="s2b3"><title>
<italic>emm</italic>-types, <italic>emm</italic>-pattern, clinical presentation and site preference</title><p>
<italic>emm</italic> pattern A&#x02013;C strains are commonly found in the throat, whereas <italic>emm</italic> pattern D strains are most often isolated from skin lesions. <italic>emm</italic> pattern E is considered as &#x0201c;generalist&#x0201d;: It is readily found at both tissue sites. Among the Brazilian isolates, the relative risk for <italic>emm</italic> pattern A&#x02013;C to be a throat isolate rather than a skin isolate was 1.68 (95&#x00025; CI, 1.04&#x02013;2.20). <italic>emm</italic> pattern D isolates had a relative risk to be recovered from skin rather than from throat of 2.16 (95&#x00025; CI, 1.53&#x02013;3.08). However, more <italic>emm</italic> pattern D than A&#x02013;C were isolated from the throat of Brazilian children. A comparison of the <italic>emm</italic> pattern displayed by pharyngeal isolates recovered in both capitals is showed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000010-g003">Figure 3</xref>. The distribution of <italic>emm</italic>-pattern among Brazilian skin isolates showed a classical predominance of <italic>emm</italic> pattern D (55&#x00025;) and E (42&#x00025;) with few A&#x02013;C (3&#x00025;). In order to compare the <italic>emm</italic> pattern from the most relevant isolates from the two cities, the <italic>emm</italic>-types that were represented by a minimum of 3 isolates were selected (18/48 Brazilian <italic>emm</italic>-types and 16/20 Belgian ones). The proportion of these <italic>emm</italic>-types that was recovered from both cutaneous and pharyngeal sites was 66&#x00025; (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;12) in Bras&#x000ed;lia and 31&#x00025; (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;5) in Brussels. These <italic>emm</italic>-types were constituted mainly by <italic>emm</italic> pattern E (Bras&#x000ed;lia and Brussels, n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;7 and 3 respectively), but also <italic>emm</italic> pattern D (only in Bras&#x000ed;lia, n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;4) and A&#x02013;C (in Bras&#x000ed;lia and Brussels, n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;1 and 2 respectively ).</p><fig id="pone-0000010-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0000010.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>
<italic>emm</italic> pattern of pharyngeal GAS in Brussels and Bras&#x000ed;lia.</title><p>
<italic>emm</italic> pattern A&#x02013;C strains are throat specific, whereas <italic>emm</italic> pattern D strains have a skin tropism.</p><p>
<italic>emm</italic> pattern E strains are found at both sites. In Brussels, strains with <italic>emm</italic> patterns A&#x02013;C (56&#x00025;) and E (41.5&#x00025;) were predominant among strains isolated from naso-pharynx (pharyngitis and scarlet fever included).</p><p>In Bras&#x000ed;lia, the A&#x02013;C pattern was rare (14&#x00025;) amongst pharyngeal strains while E pattern (61.5&#x00025;) and D pattern (18.5&#x00025;) were predominant.</p><p>REA: rearranged <italic>emm</italic> region.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0000010.g003"/></fig><p>The 2 cases of invasive infections in Brussels were caused by <italic>emm</italic> 1 and 3 strains belonging to the <italic>emm</italic> pattern A&#x02013;C. By contrast, invasive infections in Bras&#x000ed;lia were associated with different <italic>emm</italic>-types (1, 49, 80, 87, st213 and st 6735), belonging to the three different <italic>emm</italic> pattern (E (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;4), D (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;1) and A&#x02013;C (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;1)).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>This comparative study illustrates how GAS epidemiology features vary greatly in clinical and molecular aspects between two cities with different history, climate and socio-economical situation, although both performed in underprivileged populations attending public hospitals.</p><p>No GAS was isolated in children under 3 year-old in Bras&#x000ed;lia, while in Brussels, the GAS prevalence was similar in the 1 to 3 year-old group and in older children <xref rid="pone.0000010-Smeesters1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. This contrasts with previous studies showing that the incidence of GAS pharyngitis was lower in children younger than 5 year-old than in older children <xref rid="pone.0000010-Bisno2" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. Moreover, Belgian children with GAS pharyngitis were younger than Brazilian ones. Differences in day care attendance, administrated vaccines and antibiotics consumption in the first years of life might contributed to the variations we observed, as these factors can modify the naso-pharyngeal flora.</p><p>In the Belgian children, GAS infections were mostly attributable to <italic>emm</italic> pattern A&#x02013;C and E strains. In Bras&#x000ed;lia, the <italic>emm</italic> pattern A&#x02013;C was rarer than in Brussels while <italic>emm</italic> pattern D was much more frequent. The predominance of <italic>emm</italic> pattern D strains in tropical epidemiology has already been described <xref rid="pone.0000010-McDonald1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. However, the Brazilian <italic>emm</italic> pattern D strains, which classically have a skin tropism, presented interesting characteristics: (i) <italic>emm</italic> pattern D strains were recovered in one fifth (18.5&#x00025;) of the isolates collected from the throat of Brazilian children. (ii) one third of the &#x0201c;non unique&#x0201d; Brazilian <italic>emm</italic>-types (which were represented by a minimum of 3 isolates) recovered from both throat and skin sites belonged to <italic>emm</italic> pattern D. (iii) <italic>emm</italic> pattern D strains (<italic>emm</italic> 53.0) were simultaneously isolated from the skin and the throat of two children presenting a sore throat associated with a skin infection. Some <italic>emm</italic> pattern D could therefore be considered as &#x0201c;generalist&#x0201d; with variable skin tropism. Similar findings were found in Ethiopia <xref rid="pone.0000010-Tewodros1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> and Nepal <xref rid="pone.0000010-Sakota1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, where the <italic>emm</italic> pattern D strains were equally isolated from the skin and the throat. Previous studies showed that <italic>emm</italic> pattern D strains presented (with <italic>emm</italic> pattern E) the higher level of <italic>emm</italic>-type and multilocus sequence type (ST) diversity among the different <italic>emm</italic> pattern <xref rid="pone.0000010-McGregor1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. Recombination events appeared to be the most frequent in <italic>emm</italic> pattern D strains and included replacement of the <italic>emm</italic>-type locus <xref rid="pone.0000010-McGregor1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. Similarly, multilocus sequence typing identified substantial genetic recombination between the so-called skin and throat strains as well as various new combinations of <italic>emm</italic> and housekeeping genes in a small community with high rates of rheumatic fever and GAS impetigo <xref rid="pone.0000010-McGregor2" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. Some <italic>emm</italic> pattern D strains might have evolved to acquire the capacity to colonize and/or infect both cutaneous and pharyngeal environment and therefore cause rheumatic fever. In Bras&#x000ed;lia, where rheumatic fever is endemic (Rheumatic fever was responsible of one third of the Brazilian heart surgeries in 2004; data from the Brazilian ministry of Health, Sistema &#x000da;nico de Sa&#x000fa;de (SUS) - <italic>Minist&#x000e9;rio da Sa&#x000fa;de</italic>), GAS skin infections were frequent and <italic>emm</italic> pattern D strains were more &#x0201c;generalist&#x0201d; than previously thought. Moreover, the A&#x02013;C strains (classically associated with rheumatic fever) were rarely isolated. These findings are in agreement with the possible link between cutaneous strains and rheumatic fever in some epidemiological contexts. Indeed, if in temperate regions, rheumatic fever appears to be associated exclusively with throat infections, recent data suggested that GAS impetigo strains are probably involved directly or indirectly in acute rheumatic fever in particular communities <xref rid="pone.0000010-Bessen1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0000010-McDonald1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0000010-McGregor2" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. In Ethiopia, <italic>emm</italic> pattern D strains were over represented (57&#x00025;; 4/7) in the isolates associated with rheumatic fever <xref rid="pone.0000010-Tewodros1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. Skin infections might constitute the GAS reservoir which triggers auto-immune reaction with or without secondary throat colonisation.</p><p>The high rate of rheumatic fever in Bras&#x000ed;lia could also be associated with the impressive <italic>emm</italic>-types diversity we observed (48 <italic>emm</italic>-types over 128 isolates). This wide variety of <italic>emm</italic>-type circulating in Bras&#x000ed;lia is probably responsible for a great diversity of anti-M proteine antibodies, hence increasing the risk for autoimmune response. Reports of GAS epidemiology outside Western nations are scarce but contradictory. Some of them (Korea, Mexico and aboriginal Australian) show the presence of a few predominant <italic>emm</italic>-types <xref rid="pone.0000010-Bessen1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0000010-Kim1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0000010-Espinosa1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. In other countries (India, Ethiopia and Nepal), a high diversity of <italic>emm</italic>-types was reported <xref rid="pone.0000010-Dey1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0000010-Sakota1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, although they were different from one location to the other. The studies showing a highly polyclonal distribution were performed in locations where massive and recent human migrations occurred. The city of Bras&#x000ed;lia was built in a poor deserted region 45 years ago. The population of Bras&#x000ed;lia, which has become one of the most developed city of the country, is now about 2 millions and immigrated from the whole country. The resulting diversity of hosts might contribute to the diversity of <italic>emm</italic>-types. By contrast with the Brazilian data, the <italic>emm</italic>-type distribution in Brussels was oligoclonal as typically seen in western countries <xref rid="pone.0000010-Shulman1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>.</p><p>This comparative study suggests that differences in the selective pressure between industrialised and low incomes regions of the world could favour the genetic evolution of GAS <italic>emm</italic>-types and therefore their emergence and/or persistence. Further studies are needed to clarify these differences and their impact for the prevention of GAS infections and sequelae. The theoretical coverage of the 26 valent GAS vaccine <xref rid="pone.0000010-McNeil1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref> would be 76&#x00025; in Brussels whereas in Bras&#x000ed;lia, it would be as low as 32&#x00025;. This low theoretical coverage is similar to that reported in the studies from India, Ethiopia and Nepal. This is of particular relevance as these countries are those who could most benefit from a GAS vaccine.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Materials &#x00026; Methods</title><p>We prospectively studied the epidemiology of GAS infections from February 1 to October 31, 2004 in children from Brussels and Bras&#x000ed;lia.</p><sec id="s4a"><title>Patients</title><p>Patients 0&#x02013;15 year old attending 3 public hospitals of Bras&#x000ed;lia (Hospital Universit&#x000e1;rio de Bras&#x000ed;lia, Hospital Regional da Asa Sul and Unidade mixta de Saude de S&#x000e3;o Sebasti&#x000e3;o with 250, 180 and 40 beds respectively) and one public hospital of Brussels (H&#x000f4;pital Universitaire des Enfants Reine Fabiola with 170 beds) were included in this study. This study was approved by the ethical board of all participant hospitals. An informed consent was obtained from each child's parent or guardian. Inclusion criteria were any infections with clinical suspicion of GAS aetiology or GAS isolation by the laboratory. Exclusion criterion was a current antimicrobial treatment. A pre-designed form was filled out by the pediatricians with personal, epidemiological and clinical data. GAS pharyngitis, cutaneous infections and otitis were defined as a positive GAS culture associated with symptoms of sore throat, impetigo and discharge from ear respectively. Scarlet fever was considered as clinically distinct from pharyngitis. Invasive infections were defined by a GAS isolation from a normally sterile body site. Post-streptococcal glomerulonephritis and acute rheumatic fever were defined according to published criteria <xref rid="pone.0000010-Special1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. Physicians were trained to swab with a standardised technique. No clinical follow-up was achieved.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Collection and isolation</title><p>Samples were plated on blood agar (5&#x00025;) and were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 24&#x02013;48H in the presence of 5&#x00025; CO<sub>2</sub>. Bloodcultures were incubated (Bactec&#x000ae;, Becton Dickinson, Frankin Lakes, United States) at 37&#x000b0;C for seven days. Beta haemolytic streptococci were phenotypicaly identified by beta haemolysis on blood agar, colony morphology, gram stain, catalase reaction and sensitivity to 0.04 U bacitracin disk. GAS identification was performed with a positive latex agglutination test containing group A specific antisera (Slidex; Biom&#x000e9;rieux, Paris, France).</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>
<italic>emm</italic> typing</title><p>
<italic>emm</italic>-typing of all isolates was performed according to the protocol described by the Center for Disease Control (CDC; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/ncidod/biotech/strep/protocols.html">http://www.cdc.gov/ncidod/biotech/strep/protocols.html</ext-link>). Primer 1 (5&#x02032;-TAT TCG CTT AGA AAA TTA A-3&#x02032;) and primer 2 (5&#x02032;-GCA AGT TCT TCA GCT TGT TT-3&#x02032;) or primer MF2 (5&#x02032;-GGA TCC ATA AGG AGC ATA AAA ATG GCT A-3&#x02032;) and MR1 (5&#x02032;-TGA TAG CTT AGT TTT CTT CTT TGC GTT TT-3&#x02032;) were used to amplify the 5&#x02032; region of the <italic>emm</italic> gene as described by the CDC. emmseq2 primer (5&#x02032;-TAT TCG CTT AGA AAA TTA AAA ACA GG-3&#x02032;) and MF2 were used for sequencing. The sequences were compared to those in the databases available on the CDC website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/ncidod/biotech/strep/strepblast.htm">http://www.cdc.gov/ncidod/biotech/strep/strepblast.htm</ext-link>) and in GenBank (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/BLAST/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/BLAST/</ext-link>). New sequences were submitted to the CDC streptococcal database and to GenBank (accession number: <italic>emm</italic> 5.50, DQ 114470; <italic>emm</italic> 12.30, DQ 114469; <italic>emm</italic> st 2940.2, DQ 006844; <italic>emm</italic> 53.5, DQ 006846; <italic>emm</italic> 73.5, DQ 006845; <italic>em</italic>m 64.5, DQ 020479; <italic>emm</italic> 94.2, DQ 026516; <italic>emm</italic> 98.2, DQ 020480).</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>
<italic>emm</italic> pattern</title><p>GAS isolates within a given <italic>emm</italic> type usually display the same <italic>emm</italic> pattern <xref rid="pone.0000010-McGregor1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>.The <italic>emm</italic> pattern for each isolate was predicted according to McGregor et al., 2004 <xref rid="pone.0000010-McGregor1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>Statistical Analysis:</title><p>Bilateral chi-square and student t test (SPSS 11.0, Gaussian distribution) were performed to compare general data and nutrition indices. p values&#x0003c;0.05 were considered significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s6"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0000010.s001"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p>emm-types, sub-type and pattern by clinical presentation in Brussels.REA: rearranged, Empy: empyeme, TSS: toxic shock syndrome, RF: rheumatic fever, Vag: vaginal infection, Uri: urinar infection, Ocu: ocular infection.</p><p>(0.11 MB DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0000010.s001.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0000010.s002"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p>emm-types, sub-type and pattern by clinical presentation in Bras&#x000ed;lia.REA: rearranged, TSS: toxic shock syndrome, Cell: celulitis</p><p>(0.17 MB DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0000010.s002.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>This study was performed with the support of an academic exchange program between the Universit&#x000e9; Libre de Bruxelles (Belgium) and the Universidade de Bras&#x000ed;lia (Brazil). We thank all the professionals of the four participant hospitals for their kind collaboration. We thank Maria Gloria Andrade, Jeane Bezerra Rodrigues, Georges Casimir, Maria Custodia Machado Ribeiro, Joceleia de Lira, Daniela de Sales M. dos Santos, Divina Maria Dias, Maria do Carmo Teixeira, Nicole Douat, Amabel Fernandes Correia, Andr&#x000e9; Kahn, Philippe Lepage, Georges Mascart, Francisca Moura de Oliveira, Denise Nogueira, Marne Rodrigues and Marina Sancha Queiroga for their help.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding: </bold>PRS is supported by a grant of the Belgian Kid's Foundation. LVM is chercheur qualifi&#x000e9; du FNRS. This project was funded by the Service de P&#x000e9;diatrie of the Hopital Universitaire des Enfants Reine Fabiola, Brussels, Belgium.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0000010-Carapetis1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carapetis</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Currie</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Epidemiology and prevention of group A streptococcal infections: acute respiratory tract infections, skin infections, and their sequelae at the close of the twentieth century.</article-title>
<source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
<volume>28</volume>
<issue>(2)</issue>
<fpage>205</fpage>
<lpage>10</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10064227</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000010-Stollerman1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stollerman</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Rheumatic fever in the 21st century.</article-title>
<source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
<volume>33</volume>
<issue>(6)</issue>
<fpage>806</fpage>
<lpage>14</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11512086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000010-Carapetis2"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carapetis</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Steer</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulholland</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>The global burden of group A streptococcal diseases.</article-title>
<source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>
<volume>5</volume>
<issue>(11)</issue>
<fpage>685</fpage>
<lpage>94</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16253886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000010-Kaplan1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Recent epidemiology of group A streptococcal infections in North America and abroad: an overview.</article-title>
<source>Pediatrics</source>
<volume>97</volume>
<issue>(6 Pt 2)</issue>
<fpage>945</fpage>
<lpage>8</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8637779</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000010-Bisno1"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bisno</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Molecular basis of group A streptococcal virulence.</article-title>
<source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>
<volume>3</volume>
<issue>(4)</issue>
<fpage>191</fpage>
<lpage>200</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12679262</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000010-Dey1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>McMillan</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yarwood</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>High diversity of group A Streptococcal emm types in an Indian community: the need to tailor multivalent vaccines.</article-title>
<source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
<volume>40</volume>
<issue>(1)</issue>
<fpage>46</fpage>
<lpage>51</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15614691</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000010-Tewodros1"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tewodros</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kronvall</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>M protein gene (emm type) analysis of group A beta-hemolytic streptococci from Ethiopia reveals unique patterns.</article-title>
<source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
<volume>43</volume>
<issue>(9)</issue>
<fpage>4369</fpage>
<lpage>76</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16145079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000010-Abdissa1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdissa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Asrat</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kronvall</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Shittu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Achiko</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>High diversity of group A streptococcal emm types among healthy schoolchildren in Ethiopia.</article-title>
<source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
<volume>42</volume>
<issue>(10)</issue>
<fpage>1362</fpage>
<lpage>7</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16619146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000010-Sakota1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakota</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Fry</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lietman</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Facklam</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Genetically diverse group A streptococci from children in far-western Nepal share high genetic relatedness with isolates from other countries.</article-title>
<source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
<volume>44</volume>
<issue>(6)</issue>
<fpage>2160</fpage>
<lpage>6</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16757615</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000010-McGregor1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGregor</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Spratt</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilek</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Multilocus sequence typing of Streptococcus pyogenes representing most known emm types and distinctions among subpopulation genetic structures.</article-title>
<source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>186</volume>
<issue>(13)</issue>
<fpage>4285</fpage>
<lpage>94</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15205431</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000010-Bessen1"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bessen</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Carapetis</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Beall</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hibble</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Contrasting molecular epidemiology of group A streptococci causing tropical and nontropical infections of the skin and throat.</article-title>
<source>J Infect Dis</source>
<volume>182</volume>
<issue>(4)</issue>
<fpage>1109</fpage>
<lpage>16</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10979907</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000010-Cunningham1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Pathogenesis of group A streptococcal infections.</article-title>
<source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>
<volume>13</volume>
<issue>(3)</issue>
<fpage>470</fpage>
<lpage>511</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10885988</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000010-Special1"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>Special Writing Group of the Committee on Rheumatic Fever, Endocarditis, and Kawasaki Disease of the Council on Cardiovascular Disease in the Young of the American Heart Association</collab>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title>Guidelines for the diagnosis of rheumatic fever. Jones Criteria, 1992 update.</article-title>
<source>Jama</source>
<volume>268</volume>
<issue>(15)</issue>
<fpage>2069</fpage>
<lpage>73</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1404745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000010-Smeesters1"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smeesters</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Melderen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>De aguiar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanderpas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Pharyngitis in low-resources settings: A pragmatic clinical approach to reduce unnecessary antibiotic use.</article-title>
<source>Pediatrics.</source>
<comment>In Press</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000010-Bisno2"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bisno</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gwaltney</surname><given-names>JM</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Practice guidelines for the diagnosis and management of group A streptococcal pharyngitis. Infectious Diseases Society of America.</article-title>
<source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
<volume>35</volume>
<issue>(2)</issue>
<fpage>113</fpage>
<lpage>25</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12087516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000010-McDonald1"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Currie</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Carapetis</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Acute rheumatic fever: a chink in the chain that links the heart to the throat?</article-title>
<source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>
<volume>4</volume>
<issue>(4)</issue>
<fpage>240</fpage>
<lpage>5</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15050943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000010-McGregor2"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGregor</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilek</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Beall</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Group A streptococci from a remote community have novel multilocus genotypes but share emm types and housekeeping alleles with isolates from worldwide sources.</article-title>
<source>J Infect Dis</source>
<volume>189</volume>
<issue>(4)</issue>
<fpage>717</fpage>
<lpage>23</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14767827</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000010-Kim1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Comparison of M-serotypes of Streptococcus pyogenes isolated from healthy elementary school children in two rural areas.</article-title>
<source>J Korean Med Sci</source>
<volume>11</volume>
<issue>(2)</issue>
<fpage>133</fpage>
<lpage>6</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8835760</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000010-Espinosa1"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Espinosa</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez Barreto</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Calderon Jaimes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>M protein gene type distribution among group A streptococcal clinical isolates recovered in Mexico City, Mexico, from 1991 to 2000, and Durango, Mexico, from 1998 to 1999: overlap with type distribution within the United States.</article-title>
<source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
<volume>41</volume>
<issue>(1)</issue>
<fpage>373</fpage>
<lpage>8</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12517875</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000010-Shulman1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shulman</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanz</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabat</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabat</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cederlund</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Group A streptococcal pharyngitis serotype surveillance in North America, 2000&#x02013;2002.</article-title>
<source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
<volume>39</volume>
<issue>(3)</issue>
<fpage>325</fpage>
<lpage>32</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15306998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000010-McNeil1"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McNeil</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Halperin</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Langley</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Safety and immunogenicity of 26-valent group a streptococcus vaccine in healthy adult volunteers.</article-title>
<source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
<volume>41</volume>
<issue>(8)</issue>
<fpage>1114</fpage>
<lpage>22</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16163629</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>