<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">pbio</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosbiol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1544-9173</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1545-7885</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">14737196</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">314472</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0020021</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Cell Biology</subject><subject>Molecular Biology/Structural Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="System Taxonomy"><subject>Saccharomyces</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Role of <italic>Saccharomyces</italic> Single-Stranded DNA-Binding Protein RPA in the Strand Invasion Step of Double-Strand Break Repair</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">In Vivo Role of RPA in DSB Repair</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Xuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Haber</surname><given-names>James E</given-names></name><email>haber@brandeis.edu</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><bold>1</bold><institution>Rosenstiel Center and Department of Biology, Brandeis University</institution><addr-line>Waltham, Massachusetts</addr-line><country>United States of America</country></aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>1</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>1</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e21</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>9</month><year>2003</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>11</month><year>2003</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; 2004 Wang and Haber.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2004</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="d35e117" related-article-type="companion" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pbio.0020074" xlink:title="synopsis" vol="2" page="e74">
<article-title>A DNA-Binding Protein Helps Repair Breaks in DNA Double Helix</article-title>
</related-article><abstract><p>The single-stranded DNA (ssDNA)-binding protein replication protein A (RPA) is essential for both DNA replication and recombination. Chromatin immunoprecipitation techniques were used to visualize the kinetics and extent of RPA binding following induction of a double-strand break (DSB) and during its repair by homologous recombination in yeast. RPA assembles at the HO endonuclease-cut <italic>MAT</italic> locus simultaneously with the appearance of the DSB, and binding spreads away from the DSB as 5&#x02032; to 3&#x02032; exonuclease activity creates more ssDNA. RPA binding precedes binding of the Rad51 recombination protein. The extent of RPA binding is greater when Rad51 is absent, supporting the idea that Rad51 displaces RPA from ssDNA. RPA plays an important role during <italic>RAD51</italic>-mediated strand invasion of the <italic>MAT</italic> ssDNA into the donor sequence <italic>HML</italic>. The replication-proficient but recombination-defective <italic>rfa1-t11</italic> (K45E) mutation in the large subunit of RPA is normal in facilitating Rad51 filament formation on ssDNA, but is unable to achieve synapsis between <italic>MAT</italic> and <italic>HML</italic>. Thus, RPA appears to play a role in strand invasion as well as in facilitating Rad51 binding to ssDNA, possibly by stabilizing the displaced ssDNA.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="toc"><p>By studying the repair of double-strand DNA breaks in vivo, evidence of a new role for the DNA-binding protein RPA has been discovered</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Repair of double-strand breaks (DSBs) by homologous recombination involves the search for homology to locate an intact donor sequence. The search is successful when the broken DNA molecule basepairs with the homologous template, termed synapsis, and forms strand invasion intermediates of recombination. In budding yeast and other higher eukaryotes, this process requires both the Rad51 strand exchange protein and the single-stranded DNA (ssDNA)-binding protein replication protein A (RPA) (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Alani1" ref-type="bibr">Alani et al. 1992</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Shinohara2" ref-type="bibr">Shinohara et al. 1992</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Ogawa1" ref-type="bibr">Ogawa et al. 1993</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Sung1" ref-type="bibr">Sung 1994</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Symington1" ref-type="bibr">Symington 2002</xref>). RPA was first discovered through its essential role in SV40 DNA replication in vitro as a ssDNA-binding protein (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Wold2" ref-type="bibr">Wold et al. 1989</xref>). The RPA complex forms a heterotrimer, which consists of three subunits of 70, 34, and 14 kDa, encoded by the <italic>RFA1</italic>, <italic>RFA2</italic>, and <italic>RFA3</italic> genes, respectively (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Wold1" ref-type="bibr">Wold 1997</xref>). Deletion of any of these genes leads to lethality in yeast (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Heyer2" ref-type="bibr">Heyer et al. 1990</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Brill1" ref-type="bibr">Brill and Stillman 1991</xref>). The biological function of RPA was further demonstrated to be important in homologous recombination in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</named-content> (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Alani1" ref-type="bibr">Alani et al. 1992</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Firmenich1" ref-type="bibr">Firmenich et al. 1995</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Umezu2" ref-type="bibr">Umezu et al. 1998</xref>) and in other aspects of DNA metabolism. Cells carrying a point mutation (K45E) in the largest subunit of RPA (<italic>rfa1-t11</italic>) are proficient for DNA replication, but their ability to perform mating-type (<italic>MAT</italic>) gene switching, single-strand annealing, and meiotic recombination is severely impaired (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Umezu2" ref-type="bibr">Umezu et al. 1998</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Soustelle1" ref-type="bibr">Soustelle et al. 2002</xref>).</p><p>Because RPA is essential for DNA replication, a great deal about its role in recombination has been learned from in vitro studies of Rad51-mediated strand exchange (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Bianco1" ref-type="bibr">Bianco et al. 1998</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Symington1" ref-type="bibr">Symington 2002</xref>). These studies have shown that RPA facilitates the formation of continuous Rad51 filaments on ssDNA by removing inhibitory secondary structures (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Alani1" ref-type="bibr">Alani et al. 1992</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Sugiyama2" ref-type="bibr">Sugiyama et al. 1997</xref>, <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Sugiyama3" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>). A similar requirement is seen in bacteria, where the ssDNA-binding protein SSB apparently plays an analogous role to allow the Rad51 homologue RecA to polymerize across regions that contain secondary structures (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Shibata1" ref-type="bibr">Shibata et al. 1980</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-West1" ref-type="bibr">West et al. 1981</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Kowalczykowski1" ref-type="bibr">Kowalczykowski and Krupp 1987</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Kuzminov1" ref-type="bibr">Kuzminov 1999</xref>). Rad51 further displaces RPA, while RecA displaces SSB, leading to the filament that facilitates the search for homologous double-stranded DNA (dsDNA) sequences and then catalyzes strand invasion and the formation of a displaced single strand (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Kowalczykowski2" ref-type="bibr">Kowalczykowski et al. 1987</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-New1" ref-type="bibr">New et al. 1998</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Eggler1" ref-type="bibr">Eggler et al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Sugiyama1" ref-type="bibr">Sugiyama and Kowalczykowski 2002</xref>). However, order-of-addition experiments have suggested that if RPA/SSB is added to ssDNA prior to Rad51/RecA, successful displacement will not occur because RPA/SSB has higher affinity for ssDNA, unless mediator proteins, such as Rad52 and Rad55/Rad57 in yeast and RecO/RecR in bacteria, are present (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Umezu1" ref-type="bibr">Umezu et al. 1993</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-New1" ref-type="bibr">New et al. 1998</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Shinohara1" ref-type="bibr">Shinohara and Ogawa 1998</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Kuzminov1" ref-type="bibr">Kuzminov 1999</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Sugiyama1" ref-type="bibr">Sugiyama and Kowalczykowski 2002</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Symington1" ref-type="bibr">Symington 2002</xref>). But if Rad51/RecA has polymerized onto ssDNA first under conditions that prevent the formation of secondary structures, further addition of RPA/SSB will stimulate in vitro strand exchange in a species-specific manner (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Heyer1" ref-type="bibr">Heyer and Kolodner 1989</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Morrical1" ref-type="bibr">Morrical and Cox 1990</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Sung1" ref-type="bibr">Sung 1994</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Sugiyama2" ref-type="bibr">Sugiyama et al. 1997</xref>).</p><p>Using the same in vitro system, <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Kantake1" ref-type="bibr">Kantake et al. (2003</xref>) have examined the effects of the <italic>rfa1-t11</italic> (Rfa1-K45E) mutation on strand exchange with Rad51. Although <italic>rfa1-t11</italic> protein bound to ssDNA identically to wild-type and could stimulate strand exchange if Rad51 was preloaded onto ssDNA, the mutant protein exhibited delayed and less-efficient strand exchange if it was first bound to ssDNA, especially at higher concentrations, even in the presence of Rad52. This defect was explained by the slow displacement of <italic>rfa1-t11</italic> from ssDNA by Rad51.</p><p>Recently, immunostaining experiments have been carried out in <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. cerevisiae</named-content> as well as in higher eukaryotes to investigate the association of RPA to DSBs following &#x003b3;-irradiation and during meiosis. These studies have suggested that RPA and Rad51 form subnuclear foci at sites of ssDNA after irradiation and during meiotic recombination (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Gasior1" ref-type="bibr">Gasior et al. 1998</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Golub1" ref-type="bibr">Golub et al. 1998</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Raderschall1" ref-type="bibr">Raderschall et al. 1999</xref>) and that RPA is recruited to these sites prior to Rad51 (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Golub1" ref-type="bibr">Golub et al. 1998</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Gasior2" ref-type="bibr">Gasior et al. 2001</xref>).</p><p>In order to understand better how RPA is involved in DSB repair in vivo, we have looked at its function in <italic>MAT</italic> switching in yeast, which is the well-studied example of DSB-induced homologous recombination (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Haber3" ref-type="bibr">Haber 2002a</xref>). <italic>MAT</italic> switching is initiated when HO endonuclease creates a site-specific DSB at the <italic>MAT</italic> locus, which is then repaired by gene conversion using one of the two heterochromatic donor sequences, <italic>HML</italic> or <italic>HMR</italic> (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Paques1" ref-type="bibr">P&#x000e2;ques and Haber 1999</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Haber2" ref-type="bibr">Haber 2000</xref>, <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Haber3" ref-type="bibr">Haber 2002a</xref>). By using a galactose-inducible HO endonuclease gene (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Jensen1" ref-type="bibr">Jensen et al. 1983</xref>), the induction of the DSB and its repair occur synchronously in a population of cells so that the kinetics of DSB repair and the appearance of intermediates of recombination can be followed by physical monitoring of the process via Southern blot and PCR assays (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Haber1" ref-type="bibr">Haber 1995</xref>, <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Haber3" ref-type="bibr">Haber 2002a</xref>, <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Haber4" ref-type="bibr">Haber 2002b</xref>).</p><p>To learn more precisely about how RPA participates in homologous recombination in vivo, we have used chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) assays (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Dedon1" ref-type="bibr">Dedon et al. 1991</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Sugawara1" ref-type="bibr">Sugawara et al. 2003</xref>) to analyze the association of RPA and Rad51 to DNA as it undergoes <italic>MAT</italic> switching. At the same time, the fate of recombining DNA was analyzed by Southern blot and PCR techniques (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-White1" ref-type="bibr">White and Haber 1990</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Haber1" ref-type="bibr">Haber 1995</xref>). The combination of these approaches has enabled us to visualize the kinetics and extent of RPA binding to a DSB and the homologous template during recombination. We report that the biological function of RPA is also required during the strand invasion step of recombination. <italic>Rfa1-t11</italic> mutant cells are not defective in Rad51 nucleoprotein filament assembly, as observed by ChIP, but are incapable of performing the strand exchange and thus the completion of DSB repair.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Kinetics and Extent of RPA Binding at DSB Ends in the Absence of DNA Repair</title><p>In wild-type yeast cells, a DSB created at the <italic>MAT</italic> locus can be repaired by gene conversion with one of the two donor sequences, <italic>HML</italic> or <italic>HMR</italic>, or the DSB can be left unrepaired in most cells by deleting these donors (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Haber3" ref-type="bibr">Haber 2002a</xref>). In order to monitor RPA binding to DSB ends, we first performed ChIP analysis on strains in which both of the donor loci were deleted so that the DSB at <italic>MAT</italic> could not be repaired and 5&#x02032; to 3&#x02032; exonuclease activity would generate resected ssDNA unimpeded for many hours (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Lee1" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al. 1998</xref>). In these strains, nearly complete cutting of <italic>MAT</italic> by the galactose-induced HO endonuclease occurred within 20 min after induction (see below).</p><p>In wild-type cells, after HO induction, significant RPA binding to sequences close to the HO cleavage site was seen by ChIP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g001">Figure 1</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g001">1</xref>B), using a pair of primers (P1 and P2) that amplify sequences 189 bp to 483 bp distal to the HO cut (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g001">Figure 1</xref>A). As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g002">Figure 2</xref>, RPA was recruited to DSB ends as soon as the DSB could be detected on a Southern blot (20 min after induction). The binding of RPA increased for about 2&#x02013;3 h, until presumably all sequences near <italic>MAT</italic> had been rendered single-stranded (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Frank-Vaillant1" ref-type="bibr">Frank-Vaillant and Marcand 2002</xref>) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g001">Figure 1</xref>B). At later times, one detects RPA binding at increasing distances from the cleavage site, as these regions were rendered single-stranded by 5&#x02032; to 3&#x02032; exonuclease activity (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Lee1" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al. 1998</xref>) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g001">Figure 1</xref>C).</p><fig id="pbio-0020021-g001" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Recruitment of RPA to a DSB in the Absence of DNA Repair</title><p>A strain deleted for donors (yXW1), thus incapable of repairing a DSB by gene conversion, was pregrown in YP&#x02013;lactate medium, and 2% galactose was added to the culture to induce a DSB at <italic>MAT</italic>. DNA was extracted at intervals after HO cutting, to which polyclonal antibody against Rfa1 was applied to immunoprecipitate RPA-bound chromatin. Another set of DNA samples were taken at the same time for Southern blot analysis.</p><p>(A) Map of <italic>MAT</italic> showing the locations of the HO-cut site as well as the StyI restriction sites and the primers (P1 and P2), 189 bp to 483 bp distal to the DSB, used to PCR-amplify RPA-associated <italic>MAT</italic> DNA from the immunoprecipitated extract. Purified genomic DNA was digested with StyI, separated on a 1.4% native gel, and probed with a <sup>32</sup>P-labeled <italic>MAT</italic> distal fragment to monitor the appearance of the HO-cut fragment (see Materials and Methods). The 1-h timepoint represents 1 h after galactose induction of the HO endonuclease.</p><p>(B) PCR-amplified RPA-bound <italic>MAT</italic> DNA in a wild-type strain (yXW1). As controls, primers to an independent locus, <italic>ARG5,6</italic> (see Materials and Methods), were used to amplify DNA from the immunoprecipitated chromatin. PCR samples were run on ethidium bromide-stained gels (reverse images are shown). Quantitated signals were graphed for the wild-type strain. IP represents ratio of the <italic>MAT</italic> IP signal to <italic>ARG5,6</italic> IP signal. Error bars show one standard deviation.</p><p>(C) RPA-bound chromatin was PCR-amplified from sites located proximal and distal to the DSB and then quantitated and graphed as described in (B). The DSB is shown at 0 bp.</p><p>(D) Effect of formaldehyde cross-linking on RPA binding to ssDNA. In both the noncross-linked samples and the cross-linked samples, 4 ng of single-stranded heterologous &#x003b2;-lactamase (<italic>AMP</italic>) gene DNA was added during the extract preparation step of ChIP. The amount of input genomic and heterologous DNA was measured by PCR primers specific to the <italic>ARG5,6</italic> locus and to the <italic>AMP</italic> sequence, respectively. RPA-associated <italic>ARG5,6</italic> and <italic>AMP</italic> DNA were analyzed from the IP samples. PCR samples were run on ethidium bromide-stained gels (reverse images are shown).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020021.g001"/></fig><fig id="pbio-0020021-g002" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Timing of Recruitment of RPA versus Rad51 to the DSB</title><p>An unrepairable DSB was created in the wild-type strain (yXW1), and closer timepoints were harvested at 20 min and 30 min after the HO cut. DNA samples extracted at each timepoint were split. One half was applied with antibody against Rfa1 to immunoprecipitate RPA-associated DNA, while the other half was applied with anti-Rad51 antibody to immunoprecipitate Rad51-bound chromatin. RPA- or Rad51-associated <italic>MAT</italic> DNA was PCR-amplified and run on ethidium bromide-stained gels (reverse images are shown). DNA signals were quantitated and graphed as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g001">Figure 1</xref> for RPA ChIP. PCR-amplified <italic>ARG5,6</italic> signals from the input DNA were used as controls for quantitation and graphing for Rad51 ChIP (see Materials and Methods).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020021.g002"/></fig><p>In carrying out the ChIP measurements, we were aware that RPA is both abundant within the cell and binds strongly and cooperatively to ssDNA in vitro (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Heyer1" ref-type="bibr">Heyer and Kolodner 1989</xref>). It was possible that some of the RPA binding we measured by ChIP could have arisen after the cells were broken and could be independent of formaldehyde cross-linking. Indeed, in the absence of cross-linking, we found that there was substantial binding of RPA to the HO-cut <italic>MAT</italic> locus, which was resistant to both addition of 2 mg of ssDNA (equivalent to a 1,000-fold genome excess) at the time of cell breakage and washing with 4.7 M NaCl, although it greatly reduced background binding (data not shown). However, in formaldehyde cross-linked samples, there was no such adventitious binding of RPA to ssDNA regions, apparently because the formaldehyde-treated proteins are no longer able to bind. This was shown directly by adding 4 ng of purified single-stranded &#x003b2;-lactamase (<italic>AMP</italic>) gene DNA from plasmid pBR322 at the time of cell breakage. Whereas there was substantial ChIP of the <italic>AMP</italic> sequences in noncross-linked samples, there was almost no signal in cells that had first been treated with formaldehyde (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g001">Figure 1</xref>D).</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>RPA Binding Precedes the Binding of the Strand Exchange Protein Rad51</title><p>In vitro studies of the early steps of recombination have suggested that in order to make a continuous and functional nucleoprotein filament, RPA must bind before Rad51 to ssDNA to remove inhibitory secondary structures (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Sugiyama2" ref-type="bibr">Sugiyama et al. 1997</xref>). Indirect immunofluorescence experiments in <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. cerevisiae</named-content> have also suggested that RPA assembles before Rad51 at DSBs after &#x003b3;-irradiation (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Gasior2" ref-type="bibr">Gasior et al. 2001</xref>). Therefore, the timing of recruitment of both RPA and Rad51 proteins to a DSB in vivo were compared by ChIP.</p><p>RPA was detected at <italic>MAT</italic> 20 min after the HO cut, while Rad51 binding was not observed until the 30 min timepoint (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Similar results were obtained in strains that are able to carry out gene conversion (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g004">Figure 4</xref>). These observations strongly support the idea that RPA binding to HO-cut DNA precedes that of Rad51.</p><fig id="pbio-0020021-g004" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Localization of RPA and Rad51 to <italic>HML</italic> and <italic>MAT</italic> during DSB-Induced Gene Conversion</title><p>A strain carrying an <italic>HML</italic>&#x003b1; donor (yXW2), thus able to repair the DSB at <italic>MAT</italic> by gene conversion, was treated with 2% galactose to induce HO endonuclease and then with 2% glucose after 1 h to repress further HO expression. DNA extracted at intervals after HO cutting was split. One half was applied with antibody against Rfa1 to immunoprecipitate RPA-associated DNA, while the other half was applied with anti-Rad51 antibody to immunoprecipitate Rad51-bound chromatin. Another set of DNA samples were taken at the same time for Southern blot analysis.</p><p>(A) Diagram of <italic>MAT</italic> and <italic>HML</italic> showing the locations of the primers, 189 bp to 483 bp distal to the DSB at <italic>MAT</italic> (P1 and P2) and 189 bp to 467 bp from the uncleaved HO recognition site at <italic>HML</italic> (P1 and P3), used to PCR-amplify RPA- and Rad51-associated <italic>MAT</italic> and <italic>HML</italic> DNA from the immunoprecipitated extract.</p><p>(B) Purified genomic DNA was digested with StyI, separated on a 1.4% native gel, and probed with a <sup>32</sup>P-labeled <italic>MAT</italic> distal fragment to monitor the appearance of the HO-cut fragment and the repaired product Y&#x003b1; (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g001">Figure 1</xref>A; see Materials and Methods). The arrowhead indicates the switched product Y&#x003b1;. RPA- and Rad51-bound <italic>MAT</italic> and <italic>HML</italic> DNA were PCR-amplified with primers P1 and P2 and with P1 and P3, respectively. Samples were run on ethidium bromide-stained gels.</p><p>(C and D) Reverse images are shown for RPA ChIP (C) and Rad51 ChIP (D). DNA signals were quantitated and graphed as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g002">Figure 2</xref>. Error bars show one standard deviation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020021.g004"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>In Vivo Competition between RPA and Rad51 for ssDNA</title><p>Studies of RPA in vitro would suggest that the amount of RPA bound to ssDNA may be limited by its displacement by Rad51, through the help of Rad52, and the Rad55/57 heterodimer (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Sung2" ref-type="bibr">Sung 1997a</xref>, <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Sung3" ref-type="bibr">1997b</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-New1" ref-type="bibr">New et al. 1998</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Shinohara1" ref-type="bibr">Shinohara and Ogawa 1998</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Sugiyama1" ref-type="bibr">Sugiyama and Kowalczykowski 2002</xref>). To test this idea, we deleted <italic>RAD51</italic> and measured RPA binding at <italic>MAT</italic>. The extent of RPA binding was approximately 5- to 6-fold higher in the <italic>rad51</italic>&#x00394; strain, consistent with this expectation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g003">Figure 3</xref>). A similar result was found in a <italic>rad52</italic>&#x00394; strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g003">Figure 3</xref>), supporting the hypothesis that the displacement of RPA by Rad51 depends on Rad52, which acts as a mediator between these two ssDNA-binding proteins (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Sung2" ref-type="bibr">Sung 1997a</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-New1" ref-type="bibr">New et al. 1998</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Song1" ref-type="bibr">Song and Sung 2000</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Sugiyama1" ref-type="bibr">Sugiyama and Kowalczykowski 2002</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Sugawara1" ref-type="bibr">Sugawara et al. 2003</xref>).</p><fig id="pbio-0020021-g003" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Effect of <italic>rad51</italic>&#x00394; and <italic>rad52</italic>&#x00394; on the Extent of RPA Binding to an Unrepairable DSB</title><p>An unrepairable DSB was created in wild-type (yXW1), <italic>rad51</italic>&#x00394; (ySL306), and <italic>rad52</italic>&#x00394; (ySL177) strains and RPA-bound chromatin was immunoprecipitated using anti-Rfa1 antibody. PCR-amplified DNA from the <italic>MAT</italic> locus was run on ethidium bromide-stained gels (reverse images are shown). DNA signals were quantitated and graphed as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g001">Figure 1</xref>. Error bars show one standard deviation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020021.g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>RPA Is Recruited to Both the Donor and the Recipient Sequences during Gene Conversion</title><p>We then examined RPA in a strain in which the DSB at <italic>MAT</italic>
<bold>a</bold> could be repaired by gene conversion, using <italic>HML</italic>&#x003b1; as the donor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g004">Figure 4</xref>A). As soon as the DSB was visible, an increase in RPA binding was seen (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g004">4</xref>B and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g004">4</xref>C). RPA binding increased for about 1 h and then decreased nearly to the baseline level about the time that <italic>MAT</italic> switching was completed (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g004">4</xref>B and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g004">4</xref>C).</p><p>Importantly, RPA also appeared to become associated with the donor locus. This was detected by ChIP using the same primer P1 located in the <italic>Z</italic> region shared by <italic>MAT</italic> and <italic>HML</italic> and an <italic>HML</italic> sequence-specific primer P3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g004">Figure 4</xref>A). Whereas RPA could be found associated with <italic>MAT</italic> 20 min after HO induction, its association with <italic>HML</italic> was seen only after 1 h (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g004">Figure 4</xref>C). The association of RPA with <italic>HML</italic> came at about the same time as we saw synapsis between <italic>HML</italic> and <italic>MAT</italic> as revealed by ChIP with anti-Rad51 antibody (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g004">Figure 4</xref>D; also <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Sugawara1" ref-type="bibr">Sugawara et al. 2003</xref>). The extent of RPA binding to <italic>HML</italic> was substantially less than seen at <italic>MAT</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g004">Figure 4</xref>C), where ssDNA may extend further than the 320 bp of homology between <italic>MAT</italic> and <italic>HML</italic>; these more distal ssDNA sequences would not be involved directly in recombination. The lower amount of RPA binding at the donor locus may also arise from a lower concentration of RPA that is needed at the sites of strand invasion or a transient presence of RPA at those loci. But the fact that cross-linked RPA can immunoprecipitate the donor locus might indicate that RPA is recruited onto the single-stranded D-loop that is created by strand invasion. This would be consistent with in vitro studies of Rad51-mediated strand exchange that suggest that strand invasion per se can occur without RPA, but that the heteroduplex DNA is unstable unless the displaced strand is bound by RPA (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Eggler1" ref-type="bibr">Eggler et al. 2002</xref>). A similar requirement for SSB was suggested in RecA-mediated strand invasion (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Lavery1" ref-type="bibr">Lavery and Kowalczykowski 1992</xref>). We cannot entirely rule out the possibility that the apparent association of RPA with <italic>HML</italic> resulted from the cross-linking of synapsed <italic>MAT</italic> and <italic>HML</italic> sequences directly or through Rad51-containing cross-links and where RPA was bound to ssDNA sequences distal to the 320-bp homology shared by <italic>MAT</italic> and its donor. Further evidence of a role for RPA in synapsis will be presented below.</p><p>To understand better the dynamics between RPA and Rad51 during gene conversion, we also examined Rad51 recruitment to <italic>MAT</italic> and <italic>HML</italic> relative to that of RPA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g004">Figure 4</xref>D). Rad51 was only detected at <italic>MAT</italic> 30 min postinduction (compared to 20 min for RPA). Rad51 binding increased for about 1 h and then remained bound for several hours. As reported previously (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Sugawara1" ref-type="bibr">Sugawara et al. 2003</xref>), Rad51 showed a delayed association with the donor <italic>HML</italic>, reflecting the time required to form a functional filament and to search the genome for homologous sequences. These observations provide evidence of the time at which synapsis between <italic>MAT</italic> and <italic>HML</italic> is achieved. Here, too, Rad51 association with the donor remained for several hours, beyond the time when <italic>MAT</italic> switching is completed.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>
<italic>rfa1-t11</italic> Mutant Cells Are Defective in the Synapsis Step of Gene Conversion</title><p>To learn more about RPA function during recombination, we investigated the behavior of the <italic>rfa1-t11</italic> (K45E) mutation in the largest subunit of RPA. This mutation has little effect on DNA replication per se, but severely impairs both gene conversion (<italic>MAT</italic> switching) and single-strand annealing pathways of homologous recombination (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Umezu2" ref-type="bibr">Umezu et al. 1998</xref>) (also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g006">Figure 6</xref>A). Cells containing this mutation displayed hyperresection at meiotic DSB ends and defects in the repair of these DSBs (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Soustelle1" ref-type="bibr">Soustelle et al. 2002</xref>). In vitro biochemical studies have shown that <italic>rfa1-t11</italic> is displaced from ssDNA by Rad51 more slowly than wild-type RPA, and as a consequence, Rad51-mediated strand exchange is inhibited when the ssDNA is complexed with the mutant RPA heterotrimer (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Kantake1" ref-type="bibr">Kantake et al. 2003</xref>). Here, we examined binding of Rfa1-K45E in vivo by ChIP and also its effect on Rad51 localization to an HO-induced DSB, using the same antibodies as against wild-type RPA.</p><fig id="pbio-0020021-g006" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>
<italic>rfa1-t11</italic> Was Not Able to Associate with the Donor Sequence during Gene Conversion</title><p>The wild-type strain carrying the <italic>HML</italic>&#x003b1; donor (yXW2) and an isogenic strain carrying the <italic>rfa1-t11</italic> mutation (yXW3) were treated with 2% galactose to induce HO endonuclease and then with 2% glucose after 1 h to repress further HO expression. DNA extracted at intervals after HO cutting was split. One half was applied with antibody against Rfa1 to immunoprecipitate RPA-associated DNA, while the other half was applied with anti-Rad51 antibody to immunoprecipitate Rad51-bound chromatin. Another set of DNA samples was taken at the same time for Southern blot analysis.</p><p>(A) Purified genomic DNA was digested with StyI, separated on a 1.4% native gel, and probed with a <sup>32</sup>P-labeled <italic>MAT</italic> distal fragment to monitor the appearance of the HO-cut fragment and the repaired product Y&#x003b1; (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g001">Figure 1</xref>A; see Materials and Methods). Arrowheads indicate the switched product Y&#x003b1;.</p><p>(B) RPA-bound <italic>MAT</italic> and <italic>HML</italic> DNA was PCR-amplified with primers P1 and P2 and with P1 and P3, respectively (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g004">Figure 4</xref>A). Samples were run on ethidium bromide-stained gels (reverse images are shown). DNA signals were quantitated and graphed as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g001">Figure 1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020021.g006"/></fig><p>In a strain lacking <italic>HML</italic> and <italic>HMR</italic>, Rfa1-K45E binding was nearly identical to wild-type, both in a <italic>RAD51</italic> and in a <italic>rad51</italic>&#x00393; background (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g005">Figure 5</xref>A). Moreover, binding of Rad51 to ssDNA at the HO-cut <italic>MAT</italic> locus was also comparable to that observed in wild-type cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g005">Figure 5</xref>B). Thus, the Rfa1-t11 protein is neither impaired in loading onto ssDNA, nor does it affect the loading of Rad51 in vivo.</p><fig id="pbio-0020021-g005" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>
<italic>rfa1-t11</italic> Mutation Does Not Affect the Recruitment of Itself or Rad51 to an Unrepairable DSB</title><p>(A) An unrepairable DSB was created in wild-type (yXW1), <italic>rfa1-t11</italic> (ySL31), <italic>rad51</italic>&#x00394; (ySL306), and <italic>rfa1-t11 rad51</italic>&#x00394; (ySL351) strains, and half of the DNA sample was immunoprecipitated with anti-Rfa1 antibody to extract <italic>rfa1-t11</italic>-bound chromatin.</p><p>(B) For wild-type (yXW1) and <italic>rfa1-t11</italic> (ySL31) strains, the other half of the DNA sample was applied with anti-Rad51 antibody to extract Rad51-associated chromatin. PCR-amplified DNA from the <italic>MAT</italic> locus was run on ethidium bromide-stained gels (reverse images are shown). DNA signals were quantitated and graphed as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g002">Figure 2</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020021.g005"/></fig><p>We then examined the effect of <italic>rfa1-t11</italic> during HO-induced switching of <italic>MAT</italic>
<bold>a</bold> to <italic>MAT</italic>&#x003b1;, using <italic>HML</italic>&#x003b1; as the donor. As shown previously (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Umezu2" ref-type="bibr">Umezu et al. 1998</xref>), <italic>rfa1-t11</italic> strongly impaired <italic>MAT</italic> switching, with only 15% product evident after 5 h (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g006">Figure 6</xref>A). RPA bound normally to the <italic>MAT</italic> locus, but unlike what occurs in wild-type strains, its binding remained undiminished at later times (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g006">Figure 6</xref>B). Moreover, there was no increased association of RPA with <italic>HML</italic> over background levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g006">Figure 6</xref>B). When we examined Rad51 binding in this mutant, we found that Rad51 immunoprecipitated with <italic>MAT</italic> DNA, but not with <italic>HML</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g007">Figure 7</xref>A). In support of this important finding, we also used a PCR assay to show that <italic>rfa1-t11</italic> prevented the appearance of newly synthesized DNA using the 3&#x02032; end of the invading strand as a primer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g007">Figure 7</xref>B). In this assay, a primer specific for the Y&#x003b1; region in <italic>HML</italic> (pA) can only amplify a strand invasion product with a primer specific for <italic>MAT</italic>-distal sequences (pB) if the 3&#x02032; end of the strand-invading DNA is extended by DNA polymerase at least 35 nucleotides (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-White1" ref-type="bibr">White and Haber 1990</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g007">Figure 7</xref>B). These data strongly raise the possibility that RPA is required during the process of strand invasion and synapsis and not merely to facilitate formation of a Rad51 filament, as the binding of Rad51 to ssDNA at <italic>MAT</italic> seems to be normal in both kinetics and extent.</p><fig id="pbio-0020021-g007" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>
<italic>rfa1-t11</italic> Mutants Are Defective in the Strand Invasion Step of Gene Conversion</title><p>(A) One half of the DNA extract collected from a typical timecourse experiment as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g006">Figure 6</xref> was applied with anti-Rad51 antibody to immunoprecipitate Rad51-bound chromatin. Primers P1 and P2 and P1 and P3 were used to PCR-amplify Rad51-bound <italic>MAT</italic> and <italic>HML</italic> DNA, respectively (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g004">Figure 4</xref>A). Samples were run on ethidium bromide-stained gels (reverse images are shown). DNA signals were quantitated and graphed as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g002">Figure 2</xref>.</p><p>(B) Input DNA was used to PCR-amplify strand invasion product using a unique primer distal to <italic>MAT</italic> (pB) and a primer within the Y&#x003b1; sequence from <italic>HML</italic> (pA) (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-White1" ref-type="bibr">White and Haber 1990</xref>). PCR-amplified <italic>ARG5,6</italic> signals from the input DNA were used as loading control.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020021.g007"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>ChIP analysis provides a powerful tool for studying in vivo protein&#x02013;DNA and protein&#x02013;protein interactions. Using ChIP and related assays, we have demonstrated important roles of RPA during homologous recombination in vivo that could not have been known with certainty from in vitro studies. RPA is recruited to the DSB ends as soon as the DSB is detected on a Southern blot, and its binding precedes that of Rad51 (see Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g002">2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g004">4</xref>), which supports the idea that RPA is required to remove inhibitory secondary structures on ssDNA for Rad51 to polymerize across these regions (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Sugiyama2" ref-type="bibr">Sugiyama et al. 1997</xref>, <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Sugiyama3" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>). This observation is also consistent with in vivo immunofluorescent staining results, suggesting that RPA foci appear earlier than Rad51 foci after irradiation (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Golub1" ref-type="bibr">Golub et al. 1998</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Gasior2" ref-type="bibr">Gasior et al. 2001</xref>). Rad51 apparently displaces RPA from ssDNA, with the help of Rad52 (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g003">Figure 3</xref>) and perhaps the Rad55/Rad57 auxiliary proteins. We note that our results are different from those reported by <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Wolner1" ref-type="bibr">Wolner et al. (2003</xref>), who observed initial binding of RPA only after 45 min, whereas Rad51 was detected 25 min earlier, although it is not clear whether there is a statistically significant increase in Rad51 binding at the earliest time. In that assay, <italic>RFA1</italic> was tagged with 13 Myc epitope tags, which may have altered its behavior. We believe our results are consistent with the fact that RPA has a higher-affinity constant for ssDNA and is present in much greater abundance in the cell (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Heyer1" ref-type="bibr">Heyer and Kolodner 1989</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Mazin1" ref-type="bibr">Mazin et al. 2000</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Sugawara1" ref-type="bibr">Sugawara et al. 2003</xref>).</p><p>We noticed that when RPA ChIP was carried out in donorless strains as well as in <italic>rfa1-t11</italic> strains that carry the donor loci, there was a continued presence of some RPA near the ends of a DSB. This may occur for several reasons. First, it is likely that the formation and maintenance of the Rad51 filament are a dynamic process, with subunits coming off the end and perhaps being replaced by RPA before being in turn replaced by Rad51. Second, the Rad51 nucleoprotein filament may not be, in vivo, a fully continuous structure, given that there are only about 3,500 monomers of Rad51 in the cell and that Rad51 binding is not highly cooperative (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Mazin1" ref-type="bibr">Mazin et al. 2000</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Sugawara1" ref-type="bibr">Sugawara et al. 2003</xref>). Finally, the very ends of the DSB can religate and be recleaved by HO in a cycle that lasts several hours in the absence of donor sequences (and hence in the absence of homologous recombination) to repair the DSB (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Frank-Vaillant1" ref-type="bibr">Frank-Vaillant and Marcand 2002</xref>). Thus, a fraction of molecules will be newly generated and will show RPA binding before Rad51, as we saw for the initial DSB.</p><p>The ChIP analysis presented here has shown that RPA is required for homologous recombination even after Rad51 has bound to ssDNA. First, RPA can immunoprecipitate donor sequences, the timing of which coincides with the loading of Rad51 at <italic>HML</italic> (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g004">Figure 4</xref>). Second, the replication-proficient but recombination-deficient mutant of the largest subunit of RPA (<italic>rfa1-t11</italic>) is able to allow Rad51 to bind to ssDNA, but is incapable of forming normal levels of strand invasion and primer extension products (see Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g006">6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g007">7</xref>). We offer two possible explanations for this unexpected finding. First, whereas Rad51 can bind to ssDNA in <italic>rfa1-t11</italic>, it may not establish a functional filament capable of carrying out a search for homology and strand invasion, even though the association of Rad51 with ssDNA appears to be normal. But the defect in cells with <italic>rfa1-t11</italic> seems different from that seen in cells lacking Rad55 (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Sugawara1" ref-type="bibr">Sugawara et al. 2003</xref>), where there was delayed and less-extensive binding of Rad51 to ssDNA; moreover, although Rad51 eventually bound, it was unable to catalyze synapsis between <italic>MAT</italic> ssDNA and <italic>HML</italic>. In <italic>rad55</italic>&#x00393; cells, it is likely that the Rad51 filament is discontinuous and unable to function. However, with <italic>rfa1-t11</italic>, the loading of Rad51 onto ssDNA appears to be identical to that seen in wild-type cells (see Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g005">5</xref>B and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g007">7</xref>A).</p><p>Alternatively, in <italic>rfa1-t11</italic> cells, the filament may indeed be functional, but RPA is needed to stabilize the strand invasion intermediate and <italic>rfa1-t11</italic> is unable to carry this out. RPA may be required to bind to the displaced D-loop, to prevent rapid reversal of the process, which is implicated by in vitro studies of strand exchange (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Eggler1" ref-type="bibr">Eggler et al. 2002</xref>). In that study, extensive heteroduplex could be formed without RPA, as revealed by psoralen cross-linking of joint molecule DNA before removal of Rad51 by deproteinization, but without cross-linking, the deproteinized joint molecule DNA fell apart into the original single-stranded and double-stranded substrates very quickly. An analogous role for SSB has been suggested in RecA-mediated strand invasion (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Lavery1" ref-type="bibr">Lavery and Kowalczykowski 1992</xref>), in which SSB prevents the reversal of DNA strand exchange by removing the displaced single strand. It is possible that the Rfa1-K45E mutation renders the mutant RPA complex unable to bind to the displaced ssDNA at <italic>HML</italic> and thus unable to carry out strand exchange, while binding to <italic>MAT</italic> ssDNA that has a free 3&#x02032; end tail is not affected.</p><p>Both in vitro (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Kantake1" ref-type="bibr">Kantake et al. 2003</xref>) and in vivo analyses showed that <italic>rfa1-t11</italic> was able to bind to ssDNA very similarly to wild-type, but our in vivo data did not see any significant impairment of its Rad52-mediated displacement by Rad51. It should be noted that the inhibition of Rad51-mediated strand exchange by <italic>rfa1-t11</italic> in vitro was carried out with saturating amounts of Rad51 (whereas the amount of Rad51 in the cell is quite limited) and that the inhibition of Rad51-mediated strand exchange was impaired primarily when RPA was present in excess (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Kantake1" ref-type="bibr">Kantake et al. 2003</xref>). How these conditions relate to those prevailing in vivo remains unknown. In this regard, it is also noteworthy that in vitro studies did not see any impairment of single-strand annealing (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Kantake1" ref-type="bibr">Kantake et al. 2003</xref>), whereas in vivo, single-strand annealing is nearly eliminated in <italic>rfa1-t11</italic> strains (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Umezu2" ref-type="bibr">Umezu et al. 1998</xref>). Further comparisons of in vitro and in vivo data will be valuable in understanding how the more complex environment within the cell affects processes of recombination.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title/><sec id="s4a1"><title>Strains</title><p>Donorless strains are isogenic derivatives of JKM139, which has the genotype of <italic>ho</italic>&#x00394; <italic>hml</italic>&#x00394;::<italic>ADE1 MAT</italic>
<bold>a</bold>
<italic>hmr</italic>&#x00394;::<italic>ADE1 ura3&#x02013;52 leu2&#x02013;3,112 trp1</italic>::<italic>hisG lys5 ade1&#x02013;100 ade3</italic>::<italic>GAL</italic>::<italic>HO</italic>. The wild-type strain yXW1 was constructed by transforming JKM139 with pGI4 (<italic>bar1</italic>::<italic>ADE3</italic>) (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Wach1" ref-type="bibr">Wach et al. 1994</xref>). ySL83 contains <italic>yku80</italic>&#x00394;::<italic>KAN</italic> and <italic>bar1</italic>::<italic>TRP1</italic>. ySL306 and ySL177 contain <italic>rad51</italic>&#x00394;::<italic>URA3</italic> and <italic>rad52</italic>&#x00394;::<italic>TRP1</italic>, respectively (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Lee1" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al. 1998</xref>, 2001). ySL31 has the point mutation (K45E) in the largest subunit of RPA (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Lee1" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al. 1998</xref>), and ySL351 was derived from ySL31 and contains <italic>rad51</italic>&#x00394;::<italic>LEU2.</italic> Strains capable of undergoing DSB-induced gene conversion were derived from OAy470 (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Aparicio1" ref-type="bibr">Aparicio et al. 1997</xref>), which has the genotype of <italic>ho</italic>&#x00394; <italic>MAT</italic>
<bold>a</bold>
<italic>ura3&#x02013;1 trp1&#x02013;1 leu2&#x02013;3,112 his3&#x02013;11,15 ade2&#x02013;1 can1&#x02013;100 bar1</italic>::<italic>hisG</italic>. A galactose-inducible <italic>GAL</italic>::<italic>HO</italic> gene was integrated at <italic>ADE3</italic> of OAy470 using YIPade3HO constructed by L. L. Sandell (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Sandell1" ref-type="bibr">Sandell and Zakian 1993</xref>) to obtain the wild-type strain yXW2. yXW3 is an isogenic derivative of yXW2, into which the point mutation (K45E) of Rfa1 was introduced by integration and excision of a YIp5 (<italic>URA3</italic>-containing) plasmid (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Lee1" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al. 1998</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4a2"><title>DNA analysis</title><p>When cells were harvested for ChIP at intervals after induction of HO (see below), a second set of DNA samples were collected for Southern blot analysis as described before (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-White1" ref-type="bibr">White and Haber 1990</xref>). The strand invasion/primer extension assay in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g007">Figure 7</xref>B was previously described (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-White1" ref-type="bibr">White and Haber 1990</xref>). The primers used were 5&#x02032;-GCAGCACGGAATATGGGACT-3&#x02032; (pA) and 5&#x02032;-ATGTGAACCGCATGGGCAGT-3&#x02032; (pB).</p></sec><sec id="s4a3"><title>ChIP</title><p>ChIP was carried out as described previously with minor modifications (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Dedon1" ref-type="bibr">Dedon et al. 1991</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020021-Sugawara1" ref-type="bibr">Sugawara et al. 2003</xref>). Cells were pregrown to a density between 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> and 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7</sup> cells/ml in YP&#x02013;lactate medium and HO endonuclease was induced by addition of 2% galactose. Strains undergoing DSB-induced gene conversion were treated with 2% glucose after 1 h to repress further cutting by HO. Proteins were cross-linked by addition of 1% (final concentration) formaldehyde to 45 ml of culture for 10 min, followed by quenching with 125 mM glycine (final concentration) for 5 min. Cells were lysed with glass beads, and the extracts were sonicated to shear the DNA to an average size of 0.5 kb. Extracts were then divided into IP and input samples (12:1 ratio). IP samples were split. Half of the extract was incubated with polyclonal anti-Rfa1 antibody (kindly provided by S. Brill) for 1 h at 4&#x000b0;C and bound to protein G&#x02013;agarose beads for 1 h at 4&#x000b0;C. In the ChIP experiments described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g002">Figure 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g004">Figure 4</xref>D, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g005">Figure 5</xref>B, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g006">Figure 6</xref>, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g007">Figure 7</xref>, the other half of the extract was incubated with affinity-purified anti-Rad51 antibody (provided by P. Sung) or unpurified antibody (provided by A. Shinohara) for 1 h at 4&#x000b0;C and bound to protein A&#x02013;agarose beads for 1 h at 4&#x000b0;C. The protein-bound beads were carried through a series of washes, followed by elution of the proteins and reversal of cross-linking (6 h at 65&#x000b0;C). Samples were treated with proteinase K followed by phenol extraction and ethanol precipitation.</p><p>In the control experiments described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g001">Figure 1</xref>D, 4 ng of purified single-stranded &#x003b2;-lactamase (<italic>AMP</italic>) gene DNA from plasmid pBR322 was added at the time of cell breakage. IP and input samples were further subject to PCR to test the presence of the <italic>AMP</italic> sequences.</p></sec><sec id="s4a4"><title>PCR amplification</title><p>The <italic>MAT</italic>-specific primers were 5&#x02032;-TCCCCATCGTCTTGCTCT-3&#x02032; (P1) and 5&#x02032;-GCATGGGCAGTTTACCTTTAC-3&#x02032; (P2), which amplifies a PCR product of 293 bp. The <italic>HML</italic>-specific primers were 5&#x02032;-TCCCCATCGTCTTGCTCT-3&#x02032; (P1) and 5&#x02032;-CCCAAGGCTTAGTATACACATCC-3&#x02032; (P3), which amplifies a PCR product of 280 bp. Primers used for the amplification of the sites proximal to the DSB (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g001">Figure 1</xref>C) were &#x02212;29.8 kb, 5&#x02032;-TCGTCGTCGCCATCATTTTC-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-GCCCAAGTTTGAGAGAGGTTGC-3&#x02032;; &#x02212;16.6 kb, 5&#x02032;-CGTCTTCTCAGCGAACAACAGC-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-GCAATAACCCACGGAAACACTG-3&#x02032;; &#x02212;9.5 kb, 5&#x02032;-TCAGGGTCTGGTGGAAGGAATG-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-CAAAGGTGGCAGTTGTTGAACC-3&#x02032;; &#x02212;5.3 kb, 5&#x02032;-ATTGCGACAAGGCTTCACCC-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-CACATCACAGGTTTATTGGTTCCC-3&#x02032;; &#x02212;3.6 kb, 5&#x02032;-ATTCTGCCATTCAGGGACAGCG-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-CGTGGGAAAAGTAATCCGATGC-3&#x02032;; &#x02212;1.6 kb, 5&#x02032;-ATGTCCTGACTTCTTTTGACGAGG-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-ACGACCTATTTGTAACCGCACG-3&#x02032;; and &#x02212;0.2 kb, 5&#x02032;-AAAGAAGAAGTTGCAAAGAAATGTGG-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-TGTTGCGGAAAGCTGAAACTAAAAG-3&#x02032;. Oligos used for the sites distal to the DSB were 0.2 kb, 5&#x02032;-CCTGGTTTTGGTTTTGTAGAGTGG-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-GAGCAAGACGATGGGGAGTTTC-3&#x02032;; 2.1 kb, 5&#x02032;-GCCTCTATGTCCCCATCTTGTCTC-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-GTGTTCCCGATTCAGTTTGACG-3&#x02032;; 3.1 kb, 5&#x02032;-TAACCAGCAATACCAAGACAGCAC-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-TTTTACCTACCGCACCTTCTAAGC-3&#x02032;; 5.7 kb, 5&#x02032;-CCAAGGAACTAATGATCTAAGCACA-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-ACCAGCAGTAATAAGTCGTCCTGA-3&#x02032;; and 9.5 kb, 5&#x02032;-TGGATCATGGACAAGGTCCTAC-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-GGCGAAAACAATGGCACTCT-3&#x02032;.</p><p>These PCR primers gave products of about 300 bp. Primers specific for the <italic>ARG5,6</italic> locus were either 5&#x02032;-AGAAAGGGGGTATTATCAATGGCTC-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-AGGAAAATCACGGCGCAAAA-3&#x02032;, which amplifies a PCR product of 533 bp, or 5&#x02032;-CAAGGATCCAGCAAAGTTGGGTGAAGTATGGTA-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-GAAGGATCCAAATTTGTCTAGTGTGGGAACG-3&#x02032;, which amplifies a PCR product of 381 bp. Normalization using these two different pairs of primers has been shown not to affect the final quantification results. Primers used for the amplification of the <italic>AMP</italic> sequences (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020021-g001">Figure 1</xref>D) were 5&#x02032;-GAAGACGAAAGGGCCTCGTG-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-GCTGCAGGCATCGTGGTGTC-3&#x02032;, which amplifies a PCR product of 750 bp. All PCR assays were accompanied by reactions using dilutions of the 0-h input sample to assess the linearity of the PCR signal and to create a calibration curve, as described before (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Sugawara1" ref-type="bibr">Sugawara et al. 2003</xref>). Samples were run on ethidium bromide-stained agarose gels (1.4%) and quantitated using an Innotech Alphaimager&#x02122; and Quantity One software&#x02122; (BioRad, Hercules, California, United States), which was also used to correct for minor deviations from a linear response in signal. Quantification and graphing were carried out as described previously with minor changes (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Sugawara1" ref-type="bibr">Sugawara et al. 2003</xref>). For RPA ChIP analysis, all IP samples were first normalized to IP signals from an independent locus (<italic>ARG5,6</italic>) on chromosome V in a multiplex experiment, by using <italic>ARG5,6</italic> and <italic>MAT</italic> or <italic>HML</italic> primers in the same PCRs. This was accomplished by dividing each <italic>MAT</italic> or <italic>HML</italic> IP signal by the corresponding <italic>ARG5,6</italic> IP signal to correct for differing amounts of chromatin collected at each timepoint. Then <italic>MAT</italic> or <italic>HML</italic> IP signals at later timepoints were normalized and graphed to the 0-h IP signal to measure the relative increase. For Rad51 ChIP analysis, quantification and graphing were carried out as described before (<xref rid="pbio-0020021-Sugawara1" ref-type="bibr">Sugawara et al. 2003</xref>), in which all IP samples were normalized to the <italic>ARG5,6</italic> input signals at the respective time points. Graphing represents the average of at least three independent ChIP timecourse experiments for each strain.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><sec id="s5a"><title>Accession Numbers</title><p>The <italic>Saccharomyces</italic> Genome Database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.yeastgenome.org/">http://www.yeastgenome.org/</ext-link>) ID accession numbers for the entities discussed in this paper are <italic>ARG5,6</italic> (S0000871), <italic>HML</italic> (L0000791), <italic>HMR</italic> (L0000792), <italic>MAT</italic> (L0001031), Rad51 (S0000897), Rad52 (S0004494), Rad55 (S0002483), Rad57 (S0002411), <italic>RFA1</italic> (S0000065), <italic>RFA2</italic> (S0005256), and <italic>RFA3</italic> (S0003709).</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Neal Sugawara for technical support for ChIP analysis. We thank Neal Sugawara, Grzegorz Ira, and Andr&#x000e9; Walther for providing valuable suggestions. We are grateful for the insightful comments of Richard Kolodner and Steve West concerning the manuscript. We thank Steven Brill, Patrick Sung, and Akira Shinohara for gifts of anti-Rfa1 antibody and anti-Rad51 antibodies. This work was supported by National Institutes of Health grants GM20056 and GM61766.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="n1" fn-type="COI-statement"><p>
<bold>Conflicts of interest.</bold> The authors have declared that no conflicts of interest exist.</p></fn><fn id="n2" fn-type="con"><p>
<bold>Author contributions.</bold> XW and JEH conceived and designed the experiments. XW performed the experiments. XW and JEH analyzed the data. XW and JEH wrote the paper.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="n3" fn-type="edited-by"><p>Academic Editor: Steven West, Cancer Research UK</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pbio-0020021-Alani1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Thresher</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolodner</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of DNA-binding and strand-exchange stimulation properties of y-RPA, a yeast single-strand-DNA-binding protein</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>1992</year><volume>227</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1522601</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Aparicio1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aparicio</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Components and dynamics of DNA replication complexes in S. cerevisiae: Redistribution of MCM proteins and Cdc45p during S phase</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1997</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9335335</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Bianco1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bianco</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Tracy</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kowalczykowski</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA strand exchange proteins: A biochemical and physical comparison</article-title><source>Front Biosci</source><year>1998</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>D570</fpage><lpage>D603</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9632377</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Brill1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brill</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stillman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Replication factor-A from <named-content content-type="genus-species">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</named-content> is encoded by three essential genes coordinately expressed at S phase</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1991</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1589</fpage><lpage>1600</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1885001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Dedon1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dedon</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Soults</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Allis</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorovsky</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simplified formaldehyde fixation and immunoprecipitation technique for studying protein&#x02013;DNA interactions</article-title><source>Anal Biochem</source><year>1991</year><volume>197</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1952079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Eggler1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eggler</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Inman</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Rad51-dependent pairing of long DNA substrates is stabilized by replication protein A</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>39280</fpage><lpage>39288</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12169690</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Firmenich1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Firmenich</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Elias-Arnanz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel allele of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae RFA1</italic> that is deficient in recombination and repair and suppressible by <italic>RAD52</italic>
</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1995</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1620</fpage><lpage>1631</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7862153</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Frank-Vaillant1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frank-Vaillant</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcand</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transient stability of DNA ends allows nonhomologous end joining to precede homologous recombination</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1189</fpage><lpage>1199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12453425</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Gasior1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gasior</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kora</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinohara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rad52 associates with RPA and functions with <italic>rad55</italic> and <italic>rad57</italic> to assemble meiotic recombination complexes</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1998</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>2208</fpage><lpage>2221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9679065</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Gasior2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gasior</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivares</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ear</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Hari</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Weichselbaum</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Assembly of RecA-like recombinases: Distinct roles for mediator proteins in mitosis and meiosis</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2001</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>8411</fpage><lpage>8418</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11459983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Golub1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Golub</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Haaf</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wold</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Radding</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interaction of human <italic>rad51</italic> recombination protein with single-stranded DNA binding protein, RPA</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1998</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>5388</fpage><lpage>5393</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9826763</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Haber1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haber</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>
<named-content content-type="genus-species">In vivo</named-content> biochemistry: Physical monitoring of recombination induced by site-specific endonucleases</article-title><source>Bioessays</source><year>1995</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>609</fpage><lpage>620</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7646483</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Haber2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haber</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lucky breaks: Analysis of recombination in <italic>Saccharomyces</italic>
</article-title><source>Mutat Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>451</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10915865</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Haber3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haber</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Switching of <named-content content-type="genus-species">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</named-content> mating-type genes. In: Lambowitz AM, editor. Mobile DNA II. Washington, DC: ASM Press. pp</article-title><year>2002a</year><fpage>927</fpage><lpage>952</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Haber4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haber</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Uses and abuses of HO endonuclease</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol</source><year>2002b</year><volume>350</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12073310</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Heyer1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heyer</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolodner</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Purification and characterization of a protein from <named-content content-type="genus-species">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</named-content> that binds tightly to single-stranded DNA and stimulates a cognate strand exchange protein</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1989</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>2856</fpage><lpage>2862</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2663063</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Heyer2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heyer</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Erdile</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolodner</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An essential <named-content content-type="genus-species">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</named-content> single-stranded DNA binding protein is homologous to the large subunit of human RP-A</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1990</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>2321</fpage><lpage>2329</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2192864</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Jensen1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sprague</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>Herskowitz</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of yeast mating-type interconversion: Feedback control of <italic>HO</italic> gene expression by the mating-type locus</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1983</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>3035</fpage><lpage>3039</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6344075</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Kantake1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kantake</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolodner</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kowalczykowski</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The recombination-deficient mutant RPA (<italic>rfa1-t11</italic>) is displaced slowly from single-stranded DNA by Rad51 protein</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>23410</fpage><lpage>23417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12697761</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Kowalczykowski1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kowalczykowski</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Krupp</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of <named-content content-type="genus-species">Escherichia coli</named-content> SSB protein on the single-stranded DNA-dependent ATPase activity of <named-content content-type="genus-species">Escherichia coli</named-content> RecA protein: Evidence that SSB protein facilitates the binding of RecA protein to regions of secondary structure within single-stranded DNA</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>1987</year><volume>193</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2953903</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Kowalczykowski2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kowalczykowski</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Clow</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Somani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Varghese</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of the <named-content content-type="genus-species">Escherichia coli</named-content> SSB protein on the binding of <named-content content-type="genus-species">Escherichia coli</named-content> RecA protein to single-stranded DNA: Demonstration of competitive binding and the lack of a specific protein&#x02013;protein interaction</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>1987</year><volume>193</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3295259</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Kuzminov1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuzminov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recombinational repair of DNA damage in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Escherichia coli</named-content> and bacteriophage &#x003bb;</article-title><source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source><year>1999</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>751</fpage><lpage>813</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10585965</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Lavery1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lavery</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kowalczykowski</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A postsynaptic role for single-stranded DNA-binding protein in recA protein-promoted DNA strand exchange</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1992</year><volume>267</volume><fpage>9315</fpage><lpage>9320</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1533628</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Lee1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Umezu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolodner</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Saccharomyces Ku70, mre11/rad50 and RPA proteins regulate adaptation to G2/M arrest after DNA damage</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1998</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>399</fpage><lpage>409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9708741</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Lee2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellicioli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Malkova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Foiani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Haber</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Saccharomyces</italic> recombination protein Tid1p is required for adaptation from G2/M arrest induced by a double-strand break</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1053</fpage><lpage>1057</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11470411</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Mazin1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazin</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Bornarth</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Solinger</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Heyer</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kowalczykowski</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rad54 protein is targeted to pairing loci by the Rad51 nucleoprotein filament</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2000</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>583</fpage><lpage>592</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11030338</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Morrical1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morrical</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stabilization of recA protein&#x02013;ssDNA complexes by the single-stranded DNA binding protein of <named-content content-type="genus-species">Escherichia coli</named-content>
</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1990</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>837</fpage><lpage>843</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2186808</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-New1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>New</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaitseva</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kowalczykowski</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rad52 protein stimulates DNA strand exchange by Rad51 and replication protein A</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1998</year><volume>391</volume><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9450760</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Ogawa1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinohara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Egelman</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Similarity of the yeast <italic>RAD51</italic> filament to the bacterial RecA filament</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1993</year><volume>259</volume><fpage>1896</fpage><lpage>1899</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8456314</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Paques1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>P&#x000e2;ques</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Haber</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple pathways of recombination induced by double-strand breaks in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</named-content>
</article-title><source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source><year>1999</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10357855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Raderschall1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raderschall</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Golub</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name><name><surname>Haaf</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nuclear foci of mammalian recombination proteins are located at single-stranded DNA regions formed after DNA damage</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1999</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>1921</fpage><lpage>1926</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10051570</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Sandell1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sandell</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zakian</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Loss of a yeast telomere: Arrest, recovery, and chromosome loss</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1993</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>729</fpage><lpage>739</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8242745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Shibata1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Das Gupta</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Radding</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Homologous pairing in genetic recombination: Formation of D loops by combined action of recA protein and a helix-destabilizing protein</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1980</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>2606</fpage><lpage>2610</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6994103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Shinohara1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shinohara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stimulation by Rad52 of yeast Rad51-mediated recombination</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1998</year><volume>391</volume><fpage>404</fpage><lpage>407</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9450759</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Shinohara2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shinohara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rad51 protein involved in repair and recombination in S. cerevisiae is a RecA-like protein</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1992</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>457</fpage><lpage>470</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1581961</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Song1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional interactions among yeast Rad51 recombinase, Rad52 mediator, and replication protein A in DNA strand exchange</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>15895</fpage><lpage>15904</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10748203</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Soustelle1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soustelle</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Vedel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolodner</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Replication protein A is required for meiotic recombination in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</named-content>
</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2002</year><volume>161</volume><fpage>535</fpage><lpage>547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12072452</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Sugawara1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugawara</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Haber</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vivo roles of Rad52, Rad54, and Rad55 proteins in Rad51-mediated recombination</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2003</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12887906</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Sugiyama1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kowalczykowski</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rad52 protein associates with replication protein A (RPA)-single-stranded DNA to accelerate Rad51-mediated displacement of RPA and presynaptic complex formation</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>31663</fpage><lpage>31672</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12077133</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Sugiyama2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaitseva</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kowalczykowski</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A single-stranded DNA-binding protein is needed for efficient presynaptic complex formation by the <named-content content-type="genus-species">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</named-content> Rad51 protein</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1997</year><volume>272</volume><fpage>7940</fpage><lpage>7945</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9065463</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Sugiyama3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>New</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kowalczykowski</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA annealing by RAD52 protein is stimulated by specific interaction with the complex of replication protein A and single-stranded DNA</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1998</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>6049</fpage><lpage>6054</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9600915</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Sung1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Catalysis of ATP-dependent homologous DNA pairing and strand exchange by yeast RAD51 protein</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1994</year><volume>265</volume><fpage>1241</fpage><lpage>1243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8066464</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Sung2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Function of yeast Rad52 protein as a mediator between replication protein A and the Rad51 recombinase</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1997a</year><volume>272</volume><fpage>28194</fpage><lpage>28197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9353267</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Sung3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Yeast Rad55 and Rad57 proteins form a heterodimer that functions with replication protein A to promote DNA strand exchange by Rad51 recombinase</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1997b</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1111</fpage><lpage>1121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9159392</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Symington1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Symington</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of <italic>RAD52</italic> epistasis group genes in homologous recombination and double-strand break repair</article-title><source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source><year>2002</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>630</fpage><lpage>670</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12456786</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Umezu1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Umezu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolodner</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biochemical interaction of the <named-content content-type="genus-species">Escherichia coli</named-content> RecF, RecO, and RecR proteins with RecA protein and single-stranded DNA binding protein</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1993</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>3875</fpage><lpage>3879</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8483906</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Umezu2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Umezu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugawara</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Haber</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolodner</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic analysis of yeast <italic>RPA1</italic> reveals its multiple functions in DNA metabolism</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1998</year><volume>148</volume><fpage>989</fpage><lpage>1005</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9539419</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Wach1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brachat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pohlmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Philippsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New heterologous modules for classical or PCR-based gene disruptions in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</named-content>
</article-title><source>Yeast</source><year>1994</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1793</fpage><lpage>1808</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7747518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-West1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cassuto</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Howard-Flanders</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RecA protein promotes homologous-pairing and strand-exchange reactions between duplex DNA molecules</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1981</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>2100</fpage><lpage>2104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6941272</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-White1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name><surname>Haber</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intermediates of recombination during mating type switching in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</named-content>
</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1990</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>663</fpage><lpage>673</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2178924</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Wold1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wold</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Replication protein A: A heterotrimeric, single-stranded DNA-binding protein required for eukaryotic DNA metabolism</article-title><source>Annu Rev Biochem</source><year>1997</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9242902</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Wold2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wold</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Virshup</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of cellular proteins required for simian virus 40 DNA replication</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1989</year><volume>264</volume><fpage>2801</fpage><lpage>2809</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2536723</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020021-Wolner1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>van Komen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recruitment of the recombinational repair machinery to a DNA double-strand break in yeast</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2003</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12887907</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ChIP</term><def><p>chromatin immunoprecipitation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DSB</term><def><p>double-strand break</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>dsDNA</term><def><p>double-stranded DNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IP</term><def><p>immunoprecipitation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>MAT</italic></term><def><p>mating type</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RPA</term><def><p>replication protein A</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SSB</term><def><p>single-stranded binding protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ssDNA</term><def><p>single-stranded DNA</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></back></article>