<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">pbio</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosbiol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1544-9173</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1545-7885</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">14737191</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">300883</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0020015</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Cell Biology</subject><subject>Development</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="System Taxonomy"><subject>Drosophila</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Multiple Apoptotic Caspase Cascades Are Required in Nonapoptotic Roles for <italic>Drosophila</italic> Spermatid Individualization</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Caspases Required for Spermatogenesis</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huh</surname><given-names>Jun R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vernooy</surname><given-names>Stephanie Y</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Hong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Nieng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Yigong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Ming</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>Bruce A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="n4">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><bold>1</bold><institution>Division of Biology, California Institute of Technology</institution><addr-line>Pasadena, California</addr-line><country>United States of America</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><bold>2</bold><institution>Department of Molecular Biology, Lewis Thomas Laboratory</institution><addr-line>Princeton University, Princeton, New Jersey</addr-line><country>United States of America</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><bold>3</bold><institution>Department of Neurology, Brain Research Institute</institution><addr-line>The David Geffen School of Medicine at the University of California at Los Angeles, Los Angeles, California</addr-line><country>United States of America</country></aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>12</month><year>2003</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>15</day><month>12</month><year>2003</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e15</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>9</month><year>2003</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2003</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; 2003 Huh et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2003</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="d35e190" related-article-type="companion" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pbio.0020034" xlink:title="synopsis" vol="2" page="e34">
<article-title>&#x0201c;Suicide&#x0201d; Proteins Contribute to Sperm Creation</article-title>
</related-article><abstract><p>Spermatozoa are generated and mature within a germline syncytium. Differentiation of haploid syncytial spermatids into single motile sperm requires the encapsulation of each spermatid by an independent plasma membrane and the elimination of most sperm cytoplasm, a process known as individualization. Apoptosis is mediated by caspase family proteases. Many apoptotic cell deaths in <italic>Drosophila</italic> utilize the REAPER/HID/GRIM family proapoptotic proteins. These proteins promote cell death, at least in part, by disrupting interactions between the caspase inhibitor DIAP1 and the apical caspase DRONC, which is continually activated in many viable cells through interactions with ARK, the <italic>Drosophila</italic> homolog of the mammalian death-activating adaptor APAF-1. This leads to unrestrained activity of DRONC and other DIAP1-inhibitable caspases activated by DRONC. Here we demonstrate that ARK- and HID-dependent activation of DRONC occurs at sites of spermatid individualization and that all three proteins are required for this process. dFADD, the <italic>Drosophila</italic> homolog of mammalian FADD, an adaptor that mediates recruitment of apical caspases to ligand-bound death receptors, and its target caspase DREDD are also required. A third apoptotic caspase, DRICE, is activated throughout the length of individualizing spermatids in a process that requires the product of the <italic>driceless</italic> locus, which also participates in individualization. Our results demonstrate that multiple caspases and caspase regulators, likely acting at distinct points in time and space, are required for spermatid individualization, a nonapoptotic process.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="toc"><p>Known as executors of programmed cell death, several caspases are here shown to be involved in <italic>Drosophila</italic> spermatogenesis, a process that resembles in many ways the generation of individual sperm cells in mammals, including humans</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Most, if not all, cells have the potential to carry out the apoptotic cell death program (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Jacobson1" ref-type="bibr">Jacobson et al. 1997</xref>). Key players in this process are caspase family proteases. Apical caspases are activated through interactions with adapter molecules in response to death signals arising from cellular compartments such as the mitochondria and plasma membrane death receptors. These caspases transduce death signals by cleaving and activating effector caspases. Effector caspases then cleave and alter the function of a number of cellular proteins, leading to the morphological and biochemical events associated with apoptosis (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Kumar1" ref-type="bibr">Kumar and Doumanis 2000</xref>). Proteolysis is an irreversible protein modification. Therefore, caspase activation is normally kept under tight control in viable cells. However, in <italic>Drosophila</italic> the apoptotic effector caspase DRICE is cleaved and activated throughout the length of elongated spermatids, and testis-specific expression of the baculovirus caspase inhibitor p35 results in male sterility, despite the fact that apoptosis is not an obligate step in spermatogenesis (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Arama1" ref-type="bibr">Arama et al. 2003</xref>). These observations demonstrate that caspase activity is important for male fertility, but leave a number of questions unanswered: For what events in spermatid differentiation are caspases required? Which caspases mediate this requirement? How are they activated and where do they act? And how do these cells avoid apoptosis?</p><p>Spermatid development in <italic>Drosophila</italic> takes place within a syncytium (cyst), in which 64 haploid spermatid nuclei descended from a diploid primary spermatogonial cell are connected by abundant cytoplasmic bridges (reviewed in <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Lindsley1" ref-type="bibr">Lindsley and Tokuyasu 1980</xref>). In mammals, similar bridges facilitate the sharing of haploid gene products between spermatids, thereby allowing spermatid development to be directed by the products of both sets of parental chromosomes (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Erickson1" ref-type="bibr">Erickson 1973</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Braun1" ref-type="bibr">Braun et al. 1989</xref>). It is presumed that intercellular bridges play a similar role in <italic>Drosophila</italic>. Ultimately, these bridges must be eliminated in a process known as individualization in order to form freely swimming sperm. At the end of male meiosis, each cyst contains 64 haploid spermatids, each approximately 2 mm long, encapsulated by two somatic cyst cells. The 64 nuclei are located at the basal end of the testis, near the seminal vesicle, and the flagellar tails extend apically, throughout the length of the testis. Individualization in <italic>Drosophila</italic> initiates when an actin-based structure known as an investment cone assembles around each spermatid nucleus (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Tokuyasu1" ref-type="bibr">Tokuyasu et al. 1972</xref>). These assemble into a macroscopic structure known as the individualization complex (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Fabrizio1" ref-type="bibr">Fabrizio et al. 1998</xref>), which moves along the length of the cyst toward the sperm tails. The individualization complex is the site at which the cyst membrane is remodeled to enclose each sperm. Cytoplasm and organelles are extruded from between the sperm tails and pushed ahead of the individualization complex, forming a visible bulge known as the cystic bulge. When the cystic bulge reaches the sperm tails, it is detached and becomes known as the waste bag (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Tokuyasu1" ref-type="bibr">Tokuyasu et al. 1972</xref>). A similar process, involving encapsulation of syncytial spermatids within individual plasma membranes and elimination of excess cytoplasm, also occurs during mammalian spermatogenesis (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-de1" ref-type="bibr">de Krester and Kerr 1994</xref>). The importance of cytoplasm elimination for human fertility is suggested by the fact that many conditions or treatments resulting in infertility disrupt this process (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Russell1" ref-type="bibr">Russell 1991</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Keating1" ref-type="bibr">Keating et al. 1997</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Akbarsha1" ref-type="bibr">Akbarsha et al. 2000</xref>). Cytoplasm elimination during spermatogenesis may also represent a strategy by which male gametes eliminate cytoplasmic parasites, thereby preventing their transmission to the zygote (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Randerson1" ref-type="bibr">Randerson and Hurst 2001</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Caspase Activity Is Required for Spermatid Individualization</title><p>To determine whether caspase activity is required for spermatid individualization, we examined cysts from flies in which caspase activity in the male germline was inhibited. We generated flies that expressed the broad-specificity <italic>Drosophila</italic> caspase inhibitor DIAP1 or the baculovirus caspase inhibitor p35 under the control of the male germline-specific &#x003b2;<sub>2</sub>-tubulin promoter (&#x003b2;2tub-DIAP1 and &#x003b2;2tub-p35 flies, respectively) (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Hay1" ref-type="bibr">Hay 2000</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Santel1" ref-type="bibr">Santel et al. 2000</xref>). Cysts undergoing individualization contain activated versions of the effector caspase DRICE, as visualized with an anti-active DRICE-specific antibody (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Arama1" ref-type="bibr">Arama et al. 2003</xref>). Testis from wild-type animals always contained active DRICE-positive cysts with prominent cystic bulges and waste bags (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g001">Figure 1</xref>A). In contrast, while elongated cysts from &#x003b2;2tub-DIAP1 and &#x003b2;2tub-p35 flies remained active DRICE-positive, cystic bulges and waste bags were largely absent and reduced in size when present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g001">Figure 1</xref>B and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g001">1</xref>C). In addition, the normally coordinated tailward movement of investment cones in active DRICE-positive wild-type cysts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g001">Figure 1</xref>D) was dramatically disrupted in &#x003b2;2tub-DIAP1 males (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g001">Figure 1</xref>E). Cysts from &#x003b2;2tub-p35 males showed milder defects in investment cone movement (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g001">Figure 1</xref>F). These phenotypes, in conjunction with related observations by <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Arama1" ref-type="bibr">Arama et al. (2003</xref>), suggest, but do not prove, that caspase inhibition results in defects in individualization. To further test this hypothesis, we examined spermatids for individualization defects directly, using transmission electron microscopy (EM). In cysts from wild-type animals in which individualization had occurred, spermatid tails consisted largely of a flagellar axoneme and major and minor mitochondrial derivatives, all of which were tightly surrounded by a unit plasma membrane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g001">Figure 1</xref>G and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g001">1</xref>J). In contrast, in many cysts from &#x003b2;2tub-DIAP1 and &#x003b2;2tub-p35 flies, spermatids failed to separate from each other and contained excess cytoplasm, often including an enlarged minor mitochondrial derivative (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g001">Figure 1</xref>H and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g001">1</xref>K and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g001">Figure 1</xref>I and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g001">1</xref>L, respectively). Phenotypes similar to those seen in cysts from &#x003b2;2tub-DIAP1 and &#x003b2;2tub-p35 flies were also observed in cysts from flies in which levels of the caspase <italic>Drosophila</italic> caspase-1 (DCP-1) were decreased specifically in the male germline using RNA interference (RNAi) (&#x003b2;2tub-Dcp-1-RNAi flies) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sg001">Figure S1</xref>). Short prodomain caspases such as DCP-1 and DRICE are activated in response to cleavage by upstream signal-transducing caspases (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Hawkins2" ref-type="bibr">Hawkins et al. 2000</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Hay1" ref-type="bibr">Hay 2000</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Meier1" ref-type="bibr">Meier et al. 2000</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Shi1" ref-type="bibr">Shi 2002</xref>). Together, these observations demonstrate that caspase activity is required for individualization and suggest that DCP-1 (but perhaps not DRICE; see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">Discussion</xref> below) is an important downstream target caspase.</p><fig id="pbio-0020015-g001" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Caspase Activity Is Required for Spermatid Individualization</title><p>(A&#x02013;C) Testis of different genotypes were visualized with antibodies specific for activated Drice (green). (A) Wild-type testis. Active DRICE is present in multiple elongated cysts. Cystic bulges (cb) and waste bags (wb) are indicated by arrows. (B and C) Testes from &#x003b2;2tub-DIAP1 and &#x003b2;2tub-p35 males, respectively. Active DRICE is present in elongated cysts, but cystic bulges and waste bags are reduced in number and size.</p><p>(D&#x02013;F) Phalloidin-stained investment cones from testes of different genotypes (red). Spermatid axonemes in (D)&#x02013;(F) are highlighted by the AXO49 antibody, which recognizes polyglycylated &#x003b2;2tub (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Bressac1" ref-type="bibr">Bressac et al. 1995</xref>) (blue). (D) In wild-type testes, investment cones move as a coordinated group. (E and F) Coordinated investment cone movement is disrupted in cysts from &#x003b2;2tub-DIAP1 and &#x003b2;2tub-p35 males, respectively.</p><p>(G&#x02013;L) EM sections of elongated cysts of different genotypes. (G) A cyst from a wild-type male that has undergone individualization. The boxed region is shown at higher magnification in (J), along with the locations of the major mitochondrial derivative (mj), minor mitochondrial derivative (mi), and axoneme (ax). A single spermatid unit is outlined with a dashed line. (H and I) In cysts from &#x003b2;2tub-DIAP1 and &#x003b2;2tub-p35 males, respectively, many spermatid units are present in a common cytoplasm that contains organelles, often including an enlarged minor mitochondrial derivative. Boxed regions of &#x003b2;2tub-DIAP1 and &#x003b2;2tub-p35 cysts shown in (H) and (I) are shown at higher magnification in (K) and (L), respectively. Several examples of multiple spermatids present in a common cytoplasm are outlined by the dashed line in (K) and (L). Scale bar for EM micrographs = 1 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020015.g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Ark and Dronc Participate in Spermatid Individualization</title><p>What are the pathways that lead to caspase activation during individualization? Cell death in many contexts in the fly requires the activity of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> APAF-1 homolog ARK, which promotes activation of the apical caspase DRONC (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Dorstyn1" ref-type="bibr">Dorstyn et al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Igaki1" ref-type="bibr">Igaki et al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Muro1" ref-type="bibr">Muro et al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Zimmermann1" ref-type="bibr">Zimmermann et al. 2002</xref>). DRONC, in turn, can cleave and activate the downstream caspases DCP-1 and DRICE (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Hawkins2" ref-type="bibr">Hawkins et al. 2000</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Meier1" ref-type="bibr">Meier et al. 2000</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Muro1" ref-type="bibr">Muro et al. 2002</xref>). Genetic and biochemical evidence implicates all three of these caspases as apoptosis inducers (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Kumar1" ref-type="bibr">Kumar and Doumanis 2000</xref>). Animals homozygous for a hypomorphic <italic>Ark</italic> allele (<italic>Ark<sup>CD4</sup></italic>) showed a high level of male sterility (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Rodriguez1" ref-type="bibr">Rodriguez et al. 1999</xref>), despite the fact that cell death is not an obligate step in spermatogenesis (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Fuller1" ref-type="bibr">Fuller 1993</xref>). This suggested to us that ARK-dependent DRONC activity might be important. To test this hypothesis, we decreased ARK levels specifically in the male germline by expressing double-stranded RNA homologous to <italic>Ark</italic> under the control of the &#x003b2;2tub promoter (&#x003b2;2tub-Ark-RNAi flies) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g002">Figure 2</xref>I). To decrease levels of active DRONC, we generated flies that expressed a dominant-negative version of DRONC (Dn-DRONC) under the control of the &#x003b2;2tub promoter (&#x003b2;2tub-Dn-DRONC flies). Similar versions of DRONC are potent suppressors of DRONC-dependent cell death in other contexts (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Hawkins2" ref-type="bibr">Hawkins et al. 2000</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Meier1" ref-type="bibr">Meier et al. 2000</xref>). DRICE was still activated in elongated cysts from &#x003b2;2tub-Ark-RNAi and &#x003b2;2tub-Dn-DRONC males (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g002">Figure 2</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g002">2</xref>C). However, as with active DRICE-positive cysts from &#x003b2;2tub-DIAP1 and &#x003b2;2tub-p35 flies, cystic bulges and waste bags were largely absent, and coordinated investment cone movement was disrupted (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g002">Figure 2</xref>B and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g002">2</xref>D). Examination of &#x003b2;2tub-ARK-RNAi and &#x003b2;2tub-Dn-DRONC spermatids using EM showed that inhibition of ARK (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g002">Figure 2</xref>E, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g002">2</xref>G, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g002">2</xref>H) and DRONC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g002">Figure 2</xref>F) function resulted in individualization failure in many cysts. In addition, many single spermatid units that were surrounded by a unit plasma membrane still contained large fingers of excess cytoplasm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g002">Figure 2</xref>E and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g002">2</xref>G). (See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">Discussion</xref> below.)</p><fig id="pbio-0020015-g002" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>ARK and DRONC Are Required for Spermatid Individualization</title><p>(A and C) Testis from &#x003b2;2tub-Ark-RNAi and &#x003b2;2tub-Dn-DRONC males, respectively. Active DRICE-positive cysts are present, but cystic bulges and waste bags are largely absent.</p><p>(B and D) Investment cone movements in testis from &#x003b2;2tub-Ark-RNAi and &#x003b2;2tub-Dn-DRONC, respectively, are uncoordinated.</p><p>(E, G, and H) EM images of an elongated cyst from a &#x003b2;2tub-Ark-RNAi male. Some individualization failures are observed (E, G, and H), two of which are highlighted by the dashed lines in (G) and (H). In addition, many spermatids that have apparently undergone individualization still contain large amounts of excess cytoplasm (E and G).</p><p>(F) EM image of a cyst from a &#x003b2;2ub-Dn-DRONC male. A large region in which individualization did not occur is outlined.</p><p>(I) Western blot from wild-type (Wt) and &#x003b2;2tub-Ark-RNAi (DArki) testis probed with anti-ARK and anti-DRICE antibodies. ARK, but not DRICE, levels are greatly reduced in &#x003b2;2tub-Ark-RNAi testis.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020015.g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>ARK-Dependent Activation of DRONC Occurs at Sites of Individualization and Requires the Apoptosis Inducer HID</title><p>To determine where active DRONC is localized and thus where DRONC is likely to be functioning during individualization, we generated an antibody that recognized versions of DRONC that had undergone autoactivation-associated cleavage at glutamate-352 (TQT<italic>E</italic>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sg002">Figure S2</xref>). In contrast to active DRICE, which appeared uniformly throughout the cyst, just as the individualization complex began its apical movement away from the spermatid nuclei (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g003">Figure 3</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g003">3</xref>B), active DRONC showed a dynamic pattern of localization. It was initially observed in a punctate pattern just apical to the juxtanuclear individualization complex (arrowhead in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g003">Figure 3</xref>C). The individualization complex moved through this region (arrow in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g003">Figure 3</xref>C), and active DRONC then trailed the individualization complex for the remainder of its apical movement through the cyst (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g003">Figure 3</xref>D). As expected, DRONC activation required ARK and was eliminated in testis in which ARK levels were decreased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g003">Figure 3</xref>E) or in which access of wild-type DRONC to ARK was inhibited by expression of inactive Dn-DRONC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g003">Figure 3</xref>F).</p><fig id="pbio-0020015-g003" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>DRONC Activation Occurs in Association with Individualization Complexes and Is ARK-Dependent</title><p>(A and B) Wild-type testis stained for active DRICE (green), phalloidin-stained filamentous actin (red), and TOTO-3-stained DNA (blue). (A) Active DRICE is present throughout the length of cysts undergoing individualization. (B) Higher magnification of the testis in (A). The arrowhead points to a cyst in which the individualization complex has assembled around the spermatid nuclei, but DRICE activation has not occurred. The arrow points to a neighboring cyst in which the individualization complex has just begun to move away from the spermatid nuclei. Active DRICE is now present throughout the length of this cyst, indicating that DRICE activation within a cyst occurs rapidly and globally.</p><p>(C) Active DRONC (green) is initially present in a punctate pattern, apical to the individualization complex (red) at the base of the testis (arrowheads). The individualization complex then moves through the region containing active DRONC (arrow).</p><p>(D) Subsequently, active DRONC is found associated with the trailing edge of the individualization complex as it moves apical within the cyst. A higher magnification view of active DRONC staining in the left-most cyst is shown in the inset.</p><p>(E and F) Active DRONC is eliminated in cysts from &#x003b2;2tub-Ark-RNAi and &#x003b2;2tub-Dn-DRONC testis, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020015.g003"/></fig><p>How is DRONC activation during individualization regulated? DRONC undergoes continuous ARK-dependent activation in many viable cells (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Dorstyn1" ref-type="bibr">Dorstyn et al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Igaki1" ref-type="bibr">Igaki et al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Muro1" ref-type="bibr">Muro et al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Rodriguez2" ref-type="bibr">Rodriguez et al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Zimmermann1" ref-type="bibr">Zimmermann et al. 2002</xref>). DIAP1 promotes the survival of these cells by ubiquitylating DRONC (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Wilson1" ref-type="bibr">Wilson et al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Chai1" ref-type="bibr">Chai et al. 2003</xref>) and by inhibiting the activity of caspases activated by DRONC (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Hawkins1" ref-type="bibr">Hawkins et al. 1999</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al. 1999</xref>). REAPER/HID/GRIM family proteins promote DRONC activity and apoptosis by disrupting DIAP1&#x02013;caspase interactions, thereby preventing DIAP1-dependent ubiquitylation of DRONC and inhibition of caspases activated by DRONC (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al. 1999</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Goyal1" ref-type="bibr">Goyal et al. 2000</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Lisi1" ref-type="bibr">Lisi et al. 2000</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Wilson1" ref-type="bibr">Wilson et al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Chai1" ref-type="bibr">Chai et al. 2003</xref>). To determine whether the REAPER/HID/GRIM family proteins played a similar role during individualization, we examined available mutants for these genes. Cysts from flies lacking <italic>reaper</italic> (<italic>XR38</italic>/<italic>H99</italic>) (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Peterson1" ref-type="bibr">Peterson et al. 2002</xref>) showed normal investment cone movement. In contrast, the coordinated movement of investment cones was disrupted in <italic>hid<sup>&#x0200a;05014</sup></italic>/<italic>H99</italic> cysts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g004">Figure 4</xref>D, compared with <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g004">Figure 4</xref>C), indicating a requirement for HID in spermatogenesis. In addition, HID protein was enriched in the cystic bulge region of wild-type cysts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g004">Figure 4</xref>A), but not those from animals that lacked HID (<italic>hid<sup>&#x0200a;05014</sup></italic>/<italic>H99</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g004">Figure 4</xref>B). These observations suggested that HID participates in DRONC activation, stabilization, or both and thereby in spermatid individualization.</p><fig id="pbio-0020015-g004" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>HID, dFADD, and DREDD Participate in Individualization</title><p>(A) HID protein (green) is concentrated in the region of the cystic bulge, which is marked by the presence of the phalloidin-stained individualization complex (red).</p><p>(B) HID immunoreactivity is absent in testis from <italic>hid&#x0200a;<sup>05014</sup>/H99</italic> flies.</p><p>(C) Active DRONC (green) is associated with the trailing edge of the individualization complex in a wild-type cyst.</p><p>(D) Active DRONC is absent from the individualization complex in cysts from <italic>hid&#x0200a;<sup>05014</sup>/H99</italic> males.</p><p>(E) EM section from <italic>hid&#x0200a;<sup>05014</sup>/H99</italic> testis. Essentially all spermatids have failed to individualize.</p><p>(F) Higher magnification view of boxed area in (E). Multiple spermatid units sharing a common cytoplasm are outlined by the dashed line.</p><p>(G) Representative EM section of cyst from <italic>dFadd&#x0200a;<sup>f02804</sup></italic>/<italic>dFadd&#x0200a;<sup>f02804</sup></italic> testis. Essentially all spermatids have failed to individualize.</p><p>(H) EM section of cyst from <italic>Dredd&#x0200a;<sup>B118</sup></italic>/<italic>Dredd&#x0200a;<sup>B118</sup></italic> testis in which individualization has failed to occur. In some other cysts from this same male, individualization proceeded apparently normally (data not shown).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020015.g004"/></fig><p>Several observations support this hypothesis. First, cysts from two different <italic>hid</italic> allelic combinations, <italic>hid<sup>&#x0200a;A329</sup></italic>/<italic>hid<sup>&#x0200a;A329</sup></italic> (data not shown) and <italic>hid<sup>&#x0200a;05014</sup></italic>/<italic>H99</italic>, showed defects in individualization similar to those observed in &#x003b2;2tub-DIAP1 or &#x003b2;2tub-p35 males, demonstrating a requirement for HID in this process (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g004">Figure 4</xref>E and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g004">4</xref>F). Second, localized active DRONC was eliminated in <italic>hid<sup>&#x0200a;05014</sup></italic>/<italic>H99</italic> (and <italic>hid<sup>&#x0200a;A329</sup></italic>/<italic>hid<sup>&#x0200a;A329</sup></italic>; data not shown) flies, consistent with the idea that HID promotes individualization, at least in part, by promoting DRONC activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g004">Figure 4</xref>D, compared with <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g004">Figure 4</xref>C). HID, by virtue of its ability to disrupt IAP (inhibitor of apoptosis)&#x02013;caspase interactions, may also regulate the activation of other caspase cascades during spermatid individualization (see below).</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Spermatid Individualization Utilizes Multiple Pathways of Caspase Activation</title><p>Together the above observations demonstrate that components of a canonical apoptosis-inducing pathway involving ARK, DRONC, and HID are required for spermatid individualization. However, it is important to note that the individualization defects observed in testis from &#x003b2;2tub-Ark-RNAi and &#x003b2;2tub-Dn-DRONC males (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g002">Figure 2</xref>) were less severe then those seen in &#x003b2;2tub-DIAP1, &#x003b2;2tub-p35, or <italic>hid<sup>&#x0200a;05014</sup></italic>/<italic>H99</italic> males (see Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g001">1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g004">4</xref>). These differences may reflect incomplete inactivation of ARK and DRONC. Alternatively, they may reflect roles for ARK- and DRONC-independent caspase activities. DREDD is an interesting candidate to mediate such an activity since it is an apical caspase that can promote cell death in some contexts (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Chen1" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al. 1998</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Hu1" ref-type="bibr">Hu and Yang 2000</xref>). Its activation is stimulated through interactions with dFADD, the <italic>Drosophila</italic> homolog of mammalian FADD, an adaptor that mediates recruitment of apical caspases to ligand-bound death receptors, thereby promoting caspase activation (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Hu1" ref-type="bibr">Hu and Yang 2000</xref>). Elongated cysts from <italic>dFadd<sup>&#x0200a;f02804</sup></italic>/<italic>dFadd<sup>&#x0200a;f02804</sup></italic> and <italic>Dredd<sup>&#x0200a;B118</sup></italic>/<italic>Dredd<sup>&#x0200a;B118</sup></italic> males (both are genetic null mutations) contained active DRICE, but often showed uncoordinated investment cone movement (data not shown). At the EM level, elongated cysts from testis of single <italic>dFadd<sup>&#x0200a;f02804</sup></italic>/<italic>dFadd&#x0200a;<sup>f02804</sup></italic> and <italic>Dredd<sup>&#x0200a;B118</sup></italic>/<italic>Dredd<sup>&#x0200a;B118</sup></italic> males showed a range of phenotypes. About 50% of cysts from <italic>Dredd<sup>&#x0200a;B118</sup></italic>/<italic>Dredd<sup>&#x0200a;B118</sup></italic> males and almost all cysts from <italic>dFadd<sup>&#x0200a;f02804</sup></italic>/<italic>dFadd<sup>&#x0200a;f02804</sup></italic> males (greater than 90%) displayed defects in individualization similar to those of &#x003b2;2tub-DIAP1 and &#x003b2;2tub-p35 flies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g004">Figure 4</xref>G and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g004">Figure 4</xref>H, respectively). In other cysts, individualization occurred apparently normally (data not shown). Together these observations argue that dFADD and DREDD participate in individualization. The fact that loss of <italic>dFadd</italic> resulted in phenotypes more severe than those due to loss of <italic>Dredd</italic> suggests that dFADD has functions in individualization independent of promoting DREDD activation.</p><p>Finally, we noted that DRICE activation was insensitive to inhibition (but perhaps not to complete elimination) of ARK and DRONC; to complete loss of HID, DREDD, or FADD; and to expression of the potent general caspase inhibitors DIAP1, p35, or p49 (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g001">Figures 1&#x02013;4</xref>; data not shown). This, together with the observation that DRONC and DRICE were activated in distinct spatial and temporal patterns (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g003">Figure 3</xref>A&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g003">3</xref>D), suggests that DRICE activation occurs through an unknown HID-, ARK-, DRONC-, dFADD-, and DREDD-independent mechanism. It has been proposed that DRICE activation in spermatids is essential for fertility and that DRICE activation is mediated by an isoform of cytochrome c, cytochrome c-d (cyt-c-d), based on the observation that males homozygous for a P-element insertion (<italic>bln<sup>1</sup></italic>) in the <italic>cyt-c-d</italic> gene were sterile and lacked active DRICE staining in testis (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Arama1" ref-type="bibr">Arama et al. 2003</xref>). However, as illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g005">Figure 5</xref>, the region surrounding the <italic>bln<sup>1</sup></italic> insertion contains multiple transcription units. In addition, cysts from <italic>bln<sup>1</sup></italic> males showed multiple defects in spermatogenesis prior to individualization, including failure to carry out polyglycylation of axonemal microtubules (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g005">Figure 5</xref>C and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g005">5</xref>E), and aberrant development of the major and mitochondrial derivatives (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g005">Figure 5</xref>F&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g005">5</xref>H). These observations leave it unclear whether cyt-c-d is in any direct sense required for DRICE activation or whether DRICE is required for fertility. We serendipitously identified a line of flies carrying an X chromosome mutation (<italic>driceless</italic>) in which DRICE activation during spermatid individualization was completely eliminated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g006">Figure 6</xref>A) (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref> for details). Testis from these flies contained large cystic bulges in which individualization complexes were present as a coordinated front, as in wild-type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g006">Figure 6</xref>B). In contrast to <italic>bln<sup>1</sup></italic> males, <italic>driceless</italic> males were fertile and investment cones moved apically. As expected from this phenotype, some cysts from <italic>driceless</italic> males underwent individualization normally (approximately 50%) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g006">Figure 6</xref>C). However, in others, individualization failed completely (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g006">Figure 6</xref>D and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g006">6</xref>E).</p><fig id="pbio-0020015-g005" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>The <italic>bln<sup>1</sup></italic> P-Element Insertion, Which Inhibits Cyt-c-d Expression, Results in Pleiotropic Defects in Spermatogenesis</title><p>(A) Genomic organization of the cyt-c-d region. Upper half of the panel illustrates the structure of the region, as described by <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Arama1" ref-type="bibr">Arama et al. (2003</xref>). The lower half of the panel indicates the relative locations of several other genes in the region, as annotated by the Berkeley Drosophila Genome Project (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://flybase.bio.indiana.edu/search/">http://flybase.bio.indiana.edu/search/</ext-link>) as of August 2002. The <italic>bln<sup>1</sup></italic> P element is inserted within the cyt-c-d transcription unit. This P element is also inserted within the transcription unit of a second gene, <italic>CR31808-RA</italic> (<italic>RE70695</italic>). Both of these genes and the <italic>bln<sup>1</sup></italic> P element reside within the intron of a third gene, <italic>CG31782</italic>.</p><p>(B and D) Wild-type and <italic>bln<sup>1</sup></italic> testis, respectively, stained with anti-active DRICE antibodies. Active DRICE immunoreactivity is eliminated in <italic>bln<sup>1</sup></italic> testis, as described in <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Arama1" ref-type="bibr">Arama et al. (2003</xref>).</p><p>(C and E) Wild-type and <italic>bln<sup>1</sup></italic> testis, respectively, stained with AXO49 antibodies (blue), which recognize polyglycylated &#x003b2;2tub present in axonemal microtubules, and phalloidin (red). Polyglycylation occurs prior to individualization (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Bressac1" ref-type="bibr">Bressac et al. 1995</xref>). Axonemes of elongated cysts from wild-type flies stain with AXO49 (C), while those from <italic>bln<sup>1</sup></italic> males do not (E).</p><p>(F&#x02013;I) EMs of cysts of different developmental stages from wild-type (F and G) and <italic>bln<sup>1</sup></italic> (H) testis. (F) Wild-type cyst prior to individualization. Note the structures of the major and minor mitochondrial derivatives, in particular the fact that the major mitochondrial derivative is increased in size and is electron dense. (G) Wild-type cyst following individualization. (H) Representative example of the most mature cysts found in <italic>bln<sup>1</sup></italic> testis. Note the dramatically increased cell size and the lack of differentiation of the major and mitochondrial derivatives, as compared to wild-type.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020015.g005"/></fig><fig id="pbio-0020015-g006" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>
<italic>driceless</italic> Males Lack Active Drice Staining and Show Defects in Individualization</title><p>(A) Testis from <italic>driceless</italic> male stained with active DRICE. Active DRICE staining is eliminated.</p><p>(B) Elongated cysts from <italic>driceless</italic> male. AXO49 staining (blue) outlines the location of three cystic bulges. Individualization complexes (arrows) are marked with phalloidin (red).</p><p>(C) Example of a cyst from a <italic>driceless</italic> male in which individualization has proceeded normally.</p><p>(D) Example of a cyst from a <italic>driceless</italic> male in which individualization has failed to occur.</p><p>(E) Boxed area in (D) shown at higher magnification. A region in which individualization has failed is outlined with a dashed line.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020015.g006"/></fig><p>The above observations indicate that DRICELESS promotes individualization, but leave the role of DRICE (which we have thus far been unable to effectively inactivate with RNAi) unclear. Interestingly, cysts from <italic>driceless</italic> males also showed reduced levels of localized active DRONC staining (data not shown), raising the possibility that DRICELESS has at least some of its effects on individualization through regulation of DRONC activity. We do not favor a simple linear model in which DRICELESS mediates its effects on individualization only by promoting DRONC-dependent activation of DRICE. This is because removal of HID or inhibition of ARK or DRONC, each of which inhibited individualization, had no significant effect on DRICE activation. An attractive alternative is that DRICELESS-dependent activation of DRICE promotes individualization, at least in part, by indirectly facilitating local activation of DRONC and perhaps other caspases, such as DREDD (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">Discussion</xref> below), that are themselves activated through distinct pathways. Positive feedback pathways that perform a similar caspase-activating function have been described in a number of apoptotic contexts (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Adams1" ref-type="bibr">Adams 2003</xref>). DRICE can cleave DIAP1 near its N-terminus. This promotes DIAP1 degradation through the N-end rule ubiquitylation pathway (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Ditzel1" ref-type="bibr">Ditzel et al. 2003</xref>), providing one possible mechanism by which active DRICE could facilitate the activation of other caspases. Characterization of <italic>driceless</italic> should provide insight into the functional relationships between these caspases in spermatogenesis.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>All together, our observations demonstrate that multiple caspases and caspase regulators, acting at distinct points in space and time, are utilized to promote spermatid individualization. In one pathway, whose mechanism of activation is unknown, active DRICE appears throughout elongated spermatids just as individualization begins. DRICELESS, which promotes individualization, is required for DRICE activation. But whether active DRICE mediates the requirement for DRICELESS is unknown. In a second pathway, HID, concentrated through unknown mechanisms in the cystic bulge, promotes the local ARK-dependent activation of the apical caspase DRONC, presumably at least in part through disruption of complexes between DRONC and DIAP1. As discussed above, active DRICE may facilitate this activation. Components of a second pathway for apical caspase activation, dFADD and DREDD, are also important for individualization. These proteins bind each other (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Hu1" ref-type="bibr">Hu and Yang 2000</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Horng1" ref-type="bibr">Horng and Medzhitov 2001</xref>), and dFADD expression promotes DREDD activation (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Hu1" ref-type="bibr">Hu and Yang 2000</xref>). Adaptors such as mammalian FADD mediate recruitment of apical caspases to ligand-bound death receptors, thereby promoting caspase activation. Interestingly, dFADD and DREDD are absolutely required for the innate immune response to gram-negative bacterial infection (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Hultmark1" ref-type="bibr">Hultmark 2003</xref>). In this pathway, dFADD-dependent activation of DREDD promotes cleavage and activation of the transcription factor RELISH. DREDD activation is mediated by homophilic death domain interactions between dFADD and IMD (an immune deficiency gene) that occur downstream of the peptidoglyclan recognition protein PGRP-LC receptor binding to bacterial cell wall components (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Hultmark1" ref-type="bibr">Hultmark 2003</xref>). Homophilic death domain interactions also mediate binding of dFADD to the adaptor dMyD88, a component of the Toll receptor-dependent immune response to fungal infection (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Horng1" ref-type="bibr">Horng and Medzhitov 2001</xref>). It will be interesting to determine whether these or other receptor pathways mediate the requirements for dFADD and DREDD during spermatid individualization.</p><p>How do caspases contribute to spermatid individualization? Testis from flies mutant for any one of the above pathways (<italic>Ark</italic>, <italic>Dronc</italic>, and <italic>Hid</italic>; <italic>dFadd</italic> and <italic>Dredd</italic>; and <italic>Driceless</italic>) contained cysts in which individualization failed to occur. Interestingly, however, other cysts in the same testis, or from testis of sibling males, carried out individualization apparently normally. Thus, these flies were fertile, though in some cases at a reduced frequency (&#x003b2;2tub-Ark-RNAi and <italic>dFadd<sup>&#x0200a;f02804</sup></italic>/<italic>dFadd<sup>&#x0200a;f02804</sup></italic>; <italic>hid</italic> mutants have defects in external genitalia that prevent mating). These observations suggest that no one of these caspase pathways is absolutely required for individualization. The stochastic nature of the defects observed complete failure of individualization in some mutant cysts and apparently normal individualization in others may reflect a requirement for a threshold level of caspase activity, which can be achieved through multiple pathways, or as a result of positive feedback between pathways, in order for a cyst to initiate individualization. Consistent with these possibilities, double mutants between components of the <italic>Ark</italic> and <italic>Dronc</italic> caspase cascade and mutants in the <italic>dFadd</italic> and <italic>Dredd</italic> cascade were almost completely sterile (<italic>Dredd<sup>&#x0200a;B118</sup></italic>/<italic>Dredd&#x0200a;<sup>B118</sup></italic>; <italic>Ark<sup>CD4</sup></italic>/<italic>Ark<sup>CD4</sup></italic>, 8% fertile, <italic>n</italic> = 12) or completely sterile (<italic>Ark<sup>CD4</sup></italic>/<italic>Ark<sup>CD4</sup></italic>; <italic>dFadd&#x0200a;<sup>f02804</sup></italic>/<italic>dFadd<sup>&#x0200a;f02804</sup></italic>, <italic>n</italic> = 12), while single mutants for any of these components showed significant fertility (<italic>Dredd<sup>&#x0200a;B118</sup></italic>/<italic>Dredd<sup>&#x0200a;B118</sup></italic>, 79% fertile, <italic>n</italic> = 24; <italic>Ark<sup>CD4</sup></italic>/<italic>Ark<sup>CD4</sup></italic>, 70% fertile, <italic>n</italic> = 20; <italic>dFadd<sup>&#x0200a;f02804</sup></italic>/<italic>dFadd<sup>&#x0200a;f02804</sup></italic>, 71% fertile, <italic>n</italic> = 14).</p><p>Caspase activity may also participate more directly in processes that mediate encapsulation or cytoplasm elimination. Several observations suggest a role for caspases in at least the latter process. First, in contrast to the situation in wild-type cysts, active DRICE was not effectively swept up into the stunted cystic bulges formed in the presence of caspase inhibitors such as p35 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g007">Figure 7</xref>) or in other contexts in which caspase activity was inhibited (&#x003b2;2tub-DIAP1, &#x003b2;2tub-Dcp-1-RNAi, &#x003b2;2tub-Ark-RNAi, &#x003b2;2tub-Dn-DRONC, <italic>hid<sup>&#x0200a;05014</sup></italic>/<italic>H99</italic>, <italic>dFadd<sup>&#x0200a;f02804</sup></italic>/<italic>dFadd<sup>&#x0200a;f02804</sup></italic>; data not shown). Second, spermatids in cysts with decreased levels of ARK often contained large fingers of excess cytoplasm despite the fact that in some cysts membrane encapsulation occurred apparently normally (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020015-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Together these observations are interesting because they also suggest that the processes of investment cone movement and spermatid encapsulation can be separated from that of cytoplasm elimination. Investment cones carry out a daunting task. They move apically within a cyst for more than 2 mm, sieving and sweeping an ever-increasing body of cytoplasmic organelles, components of the nuclear membrane, nucleoplasm, and bulk cytoplasm in front of them. Little is known about how investment cones function other than that movement is actin-based and that a number of actin-binding proteins are located in or around these structures (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Hicks1" ref-type="bibr">Hicks et al. 1999</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Noguchi1" ref-type="bibr">Noguchi and Miller 2003</xref>). It is tempting to speculate that spermatid caspase activity functions, at least in part, to free organelles from preexisting attachments, thus facilitating their apical transport. In this way, caspase activity would provide a permissive environment for investment cone movement and cytoplasm removal. More active roles in promoting membrane remodeling or investment cone-dependent force generation or movement, based on spatially restricted cleavage of cytoskeletal components or other proteins, can also be imagined. The identification of caspase substrates will be important in understanding how caspases regulate this process.</p><fig id="pbio-0020015-g007" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Active DRICE Is Eliminated from the Cytoplasm of Wild-Type Spermatids Following Passage of the Individualization Complex, but Not from Spermatids in Which Caspase Activity Has Been Inhibited</title><p>(A) Cystic bulge from a wild-type cyst stained with active DRICE (red). The cystic bulge (arrowhead) is moving to the left. Active DRICE staining is absent in areas of the spermatid bundle that the individualization complex has passed through and in which excess cytoplasm has been eliminated (arrow).</p><p>(B) Cystic bulge from a &#x003b2;2tub-p35 cyst. The cystic bulge (arrowhead) is decreased in size, and active DRICE is present in areas of the spermatid bundle through which the individualization complex has moved (arrows). These observations suggest caspase inhibition results in at least a partial failure to eliminate excess cytoplasm, but that this is not necessarily associated with lack of movement of the individualization complex.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020015.g007"/></fig><p>What is the relationship of our observations in <italic>Drosophila</italic> to spermatid differentiation in mammals? During step 18 of murine spermatid differentiation, a lobe of cytoplasm accumulates around the spermatid head. It then separates from the spermatid body and is ultimately phagocytosed by the associated Sertoli cell (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-de1" ref-type="bibr">de Krester and Kerr 1994</xref>). Separation of this mass, known as the residual body, removes a large volume of spermatid cytoplasm. It also brings about the encapsulation of each spermatid within a single plasma membrane, since the cytoplasmic bridges linking spermatids are between the membrane compartments defined by the residual bodies. Finally, it severs the connection between the spermatid and the Sertoli cell that supported and anchored it, thereby freeing the now-individualized spermatozoa to enter the seminiferous tubule. Residual bodies show several features commonly associated with apoptosis: their plasma membrane binds Annexin V, and they are phagocytosed by Sertoli cells (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Blanco-Rodriguez1" ref-type="bibr">Blanco-Rodriguez and Martinez-Garcia 1999</xref>), which also phagocytose apoptotic germ cells (compare <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Shiratsuchi1" ref-type="bibr">Shiratsuchi et al. 1997</xref> and references therein). In addition, residual body cytoplasm is condensed and contains elevated levels of CASPASE-1 (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Blanco-Rodriguez1" ref-type="bibr">Blanco-Rodriguez and Martinez-Garcia 1999</xref>) and the proapoptotic BCL-2 family member BAK (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Krajewski1" ref-type="bibr">Krajewski et al. 1996</xref>). These observations suggest that, as in <italic>Drosophila</italic>, local activation of apoptotic caspase cascades within late-stage spermatids promotes their individualization and elimination of excess cytoplasm. Mice lacking the proapoptotic proteins APAF-1 or the BLC-2 family member BAX are infertile and have dramatic defects in spermatogenesis (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Knudson1" ref-type="bibr">Knudson et al. 1995</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Honarpour1" ref-type="bibr">Honarpour et al. 2000</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Russell2" ref-type="bibr">Russell et al. 2002</xref>). However, these phenotypes are thought to be an indirect consequence of a failure in an earlier, normally occurring postnatal spermatogonial cell death. A test of the importance of caspase activity in mammalian spermatid differentiation will be most directly achieved by determining the consequences of caspase inhibition specifically in these cells.</p><p>Finally, how is it that elongated spermatids avoid apoptosis in the presence of activated apoptotic caspases for prolonged periods of time? Perhaps the caspase substrates are different from those targeted during apoptosis. But, if so, then what is the basis for the selective targeting? If the targets are the same as those activated during apoptosis, then how is the caspase cascade kept from promoting an apoptotic cell fate? Tight control over the subcellular site of caspase activation (or stabilization of the active caspase), such as we observed with DRONC, provides one possible solution. Others may also exist. In particular, it is important to recognize that while active caspase-specific antibodies recognize caspases that are in the cleaved and therefore activated conformation, these caspases may be kept inactive through interactions with other proteins or as a result of posttranslational modification. <italic>Drosophila</italic> is a powerful system in which to isolate male-sterile mutants (compare <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Castrillon1" ref-type="bibr">Castrillon et al. 1993</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Fuller1" ref-type="bibr">Fuller 1993</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Fabrizio1" ref-type="bibr">Fabrizio et al. 1998</xref>). It is likely that an exploration of the relationship between the genes identified by these mutations and the apoptotic regulators described here will provide insight into these questions.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title/><sec id="s4a1"><title>Fly strains and constructs</title><p>All crosses and stocks were maintained at 25&#x000b0;C. The following fly stocks were used: <italic>w1118, Ark<sup>CD4</sup>/Cyo</italic> (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Rodriguez1" ref-type="bibr">Rodriguez et al. 1999</xref>), <italic>H99/TM3</italic> (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-White1" ref-type="bibr">White et al. 1994</xref>), <italic>hid<sup>05014</sup>/TM3</italic> (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Grether1" ref-type="bibr">Grether et al. 1995</xref>), <italic>dFadd&#x0200a;<sup>f02804</sup>/TM6B</italic> (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Naitza1" ref-type="bibr">Naitza et al. 2002</xref>), <italic>Dredd&#x0200a;<sup>B118</sup>/FM7</italic> (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Leulier1" ref-type="bibr">Leulier et al. 2000</xref>), <italic>GMR-Dronc<sup>&#x0200a;F118E</sup></italic> (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Chai1" ref-type="bibr">Chai et al. 2003</xref>), and <italic>bln<sup>1</sup>/Cyo</italic> (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Castrillon1" ref-type="bibr">Castrillon et al. 1993</xref>). <italic>Dronc<sup>&#x0200a;F118E</sup></italic> contains a mutation that prevents interaction between DRONC and DIAP1. Thus, <italic>Dronc&#x0200a;<sup>F118E</sup></italic> has enhanced activity in vivo (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Chai1" ref-type="bibr">Chai et al. 2003</xref>). The P-element vector p&#x003b2;2Tub contains sequences from the &#x003b2;2tub locus (85D) sufficient to direct testis germline-specific expression. It was generated by removing an XhoI&#x02013;EcoRI promoter fragment from pGMR (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Hay2" ref-type="bibr">Hay et al. 1994</xref>) and introducing in its place a 340-bp fragment from the &#x003b2;2tub locus (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Santel1" ref-type="bibr">Santel et al. 2000</xref>), amplified by PCR with the primers 5&#x02032;-gcg ctc gag atc ctc tat tgc ttc caa ggc acc and 5&#x02032;-gcg gaa ttc agt tag ggc ccc ttt ttc aca ccg. Coding region fragments for Dn-DRONC (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Hawkins2" ref-type="bibr">Hawkins et al. 2000</xref>) and DIAP1C422Y (which results in stabilization of DIAP1 by blocking its ability to autoubiquitinate [<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Yoo1" ref-type="bibr">Yoo et al. 2002</xref>]) were introduced into p&#x003b2;2Tub to produce pTub-Dn-DRONC and pTub-DIAP1, respectively. A vector to express double-stranded RNA for ARK was generated as follows. A 900-bp fragment of <italic>Ark</italic> genomic DNA corresponding to the first exon and intron was amplified using primers 5&#x02032;-gcg gaa ttc ccg aag agg cat cgc gag cat ata cg and 5&#x02032;-cgc aga tct ata agg ggt gag tgc tcc cag cgg ctc. This was introduced into p&#x003b2;2Tub using EcoRI and BglII. A second fragment corresponding to the first exon, but in reverse orientation, was amplified using primers 5&#x02032;-gcg gcg gcc gc gct aac gca ggg tcc ttc gga ggc and 5&#x02032;-cgc agg cct aag agg cat cgc gag cat ata cgc. This was introduced into the intermediate described above using NotI and StuI, generating pTub-Ark-RNAi. A similar strategy was used to generate pTub-Dcp-1-RNAi. A 540-bp fragment of <italic>Dcp-1</italic> genomic DNA corresponding to the first exon and intron was amplified using primers 5&#x02032;-ctg ccg gaa ttc ttc gac ata ccc tcg ctg and 5&#x02032;-cgc gga aga tct gtt gcg cca gga gaa gta g. A second fragment corresponding to the first exon, but in reverse orientation, was amplified using primers 5&#x02032;-aag gaa aaa a gcg gcc gc cgg aat ggt cga gta gga gaa g and 5&#x02032;-cgc gga agg cct ttg aaa acc tgg gat tc. Germline transformants of pTub-Dn-DRONC, pTub-DIAP1, and pTub-Ark-RNAi were created using standard procedures. Testis characterized in this paper carried multiple copies of the relevant &#x003b2;2tub expression transgene. These were &#x003b2;2tub-DIAP1, &#x003b2;2tub-p35, and &#x003b2;2tub-Dn-DRONC (four copies); &#x003b2;2tub-Ark-RNAi (three copies); &#x003b2;2tub-Dcp-1-RNAi (six copies).</p></sec><sec id="s4a2"><title>Isolation of the <italic>driceless</italic> mutant</title><p>We stained testis from <italic>puc<sup>&#x0200a;E69</sup>/TM6B</italic> males (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Martin-Blanco1" ref-type="bibr">Martin-Blanco et al. 1998</xref>) with active DRICE antibodies. These males lacked active DRICE staining, but fully elongated axonemes were present, as visualized by staining with AXO49 antibody. The mutation was mapped to the X chromosome using standard procedures.</p></sec><sec id="s4a3"><title>Immunocytochemistry</title><p>Conditions for immunocytochemistry and confocal microscopy were as described in <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Yoo1" ref-type="bibr">Yoo et al. (2002</xref>). Palloidin-Alexafluor488 (Molecular Probes Inc., Eugene, Oregon, United States) was used at 1:40 concentration to label filamentous actin; TOTO-3 was used for DNA labeling at 1:10,000 (Molecular Probes Inc.). Antibodies were used at the following concentrations: purified rabbit anti-active DRICE (1:50) (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Yoo1" ref-type="bibr">Yoo et al. 2002</xref>); purified rabbit anti-DRONC (1:100) (this paper); mouse anti-DIAP1 (1:400) (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Yoo1" ref-type="bibr">Yoo et al. 2002</xref>); mouse anti-AXO49 (1:5,000) (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Bressac1" ref-type="bibr">Bressac et al. 1995</xref>), rabbit anti-HID (1:1,000) (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Yoo1" ref-type="bibr">Yoo et al. 2002</xref>), and purified rabbit anti-active DRONC peptide (1:50) and anti-DCP-1 (1:100) (this paper). Anti-DCP-1 antibodies were produced in rabbits and purified using a C-terminal 6&#x000d7; His-tagged version of the DCP-1 p20 subunit as the immunogen. Anti-DRONC antibodies were raised against the C-terminal fragment of the DRONC large subunit (amino acid residues 336&#x02013;352; EPVYTAQEEKWPDTQTE), and anti-active DRONC-specific antibodies were raised in rabbits using a synthetic nonapeptide corresponding to residues just N-terminal to the DRONC autoactivation cleavage site E352 (EKWPD<italic>TQTE</italic>), both of which were conjugated with keyhole limpet hemocyanin as the immunogen (Covance Research Products Inc., Richmond, California, United States). Active DRONC-specific antibodies were purified by sequential protein affinity purification. Antisera were first applied to a column bound with full-length inactive DRONC (<italic>Dronc<sup>C318A</sup></italic>) to eliminate antibodies reactive with uncleaved DRONC. The flowthrough was applied to a DRONC large subunit (residues 1&#x02013;352) affinity column. Bound proteins were eluted using 100 mM glycine (pH 2.5). These antibodies detect the large fragment of active DRONC (cleaved after E352), but do not recognize full-length DRONC (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sg002">Figure S2</xref>). Anti-DRONC antibodies were purified using full-length inactive DRONC (<italic>Dronc<sup>C318A</sup></italic>). Western blot analysis to demonstrate binding specificity was carried out with 100 ng of full-length <italic>Dronc<sup>C318A</sup></italic> and <italic>Dronc<sup>1&#x02013;352</sup></italic>. These were detected using purified anti-DRONC peptide (1:100) or purified anti-active DRONC peptide (1:100) antibodies.</p></sec><sec id="s4a4"><title>Male fertility tests</title><p>Individual male flies were placed with 4- to 5-d-old virgin females in vials for 3 d at 25&#x000b0;C. They were then transferred to fresh vials with four new females and allowed to mate for another 3 d. Males were scored as sterile if they failed to produce progeny by day 6.</p></sec><sec id="s4a5"><title>Western blotting of adult testis</title><p>Testes extracts were prepared in 50 &#x003bc;l of cell lysis buffer (20 mM HEPES&#x02013;KOH [pH 7.6], 150 mM NaCl, 10% glycerol, 1% Triton X-100, 2 mM EDTA, 1&#x000d7; protease inhibitor cocktail [Roche, Basel, Switzerland], and 1 mM DTT) from 30&#x02013;50 adults of the appropriate genotype. Total protein (70 &#x003bc;g) was used for Western blot analysis using rabbit anti-ARK (1:1,000) (generously provided by Lai Wang and Xiaodong Wang) or purified rabbit anti-DCP-1 (1:100). Filters were stripped using Restore Western blot stripping buffer (Pierce Biotechnology, Rockford, Illinois, United States) and reprobed with rabbit anti-full-length DRICE (1:1,000) (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Dorstyn1" ref-type="bibr">Dorstyn et al. 2002</xref>) as a loading control.</p></sec><sec id="s4a6"><title>Electron microscopy</title><p>Testes were dissected from adult 2- to 4-d-old males raised at 25&#x000b0;C and prepared for EM as described by <xref rid="pbio-0020015-Tokuyasu1" ref-type="bibr">Tokuyasu et al. (1972</xref>). Thin sections were observed and photographed using a Philips 201 transmission electron microscope (Royal Philips Electronics, Eindhoven, The Netherlands) at 80 kV accelerating voltage. Elongated cysts in which spermatids should have been undergoing or have undergone individualization were identified by their central position in the testis as well as the stage of differentiation of major and mitochondrial derivatives (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Tokuyasu1" ref-type="bibr">Tokuyasu et al. 1972</xref>). At least two to three testes of each genotype were examined.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sg001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><title>Inhibition of <italic>Dcp-1</italic> Prevents Spermatid Individualization</title><p>(A) EM section from &#x003b2;2tub-Dcp-1-RNAi testis. Individualization has failed to occur throughout the cyst.</p><p>(B) The boxed area in M is shown at a higher magnification. Spermatid units sharing a common cytoplasm are outlined by the dashed line.</p><p>(C) Western blot from wild-type (Wt) and &#x003b2;2tub-Dcp-1-RNAi (Dcpi) testis probed with anti-DCP-1 and anti-DRICE antibodies. DCP-1, but not DRICE, levels are greatly reduced in &#x003b2;2tub-Dcp-1-RNAi testis.</p><p>(552 KB JPEG).</p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0020015.sg001.jpg"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sg002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><title>Antibodies Specific for Active DRONC</title><p>(A) Third instar eye imaginal disc from <italic>GMR-Dronc<sup>&#x0200a;F118E</sup></italic> larvae stained with purified anti-DRONC peptide antiserum (green). All cells posterior to the morphogenetic furrow labeled with this antiserum, as expected based on the pattern of GMR (glass multimer reporter)-dependent gene expression (<xref rid="pbio-0020015-Hay2" ref-type="bibr">Hay et al. 1994</xref>). Eye discs from wild-type larvae showed only very low, uniform levels of staining (data not shown). The inset shows a Western blot probed with purified anti-DRONC peptide antiserum. The first lane was loaded with full-length DRONC mutated in its active site (<italic>Dronc<sup>C318A</sup></italic>). The second lane was loaded with a version of DRONC consisting of only residues 1&#x02013;352. This protein terminates following glutamate-352, the DRONC autoactivation cleavage site, and is equivalent to the large subunit of cleaved and active Dronc. The anti-DRONC antibodies react well with both proteins.</p><p>(B) Third instar eye imaginal disc from <italic>GMR-Dronc&#x0200a;<sup>F118E</sup></italic> larvae stained with anti-active DRONC antiserum extensively purified to select for antibodies that react only with versions of DRONC that have been cleaved at glutamate-352, as described in the Materials and Methods. Only cells in the most posterior region of the eye disc, which are presumably undergoing apoptosis, react with these purified antibodies. The inset shows a Western blot, similar to that in (A), which was probed with the purified active DRONC-specific antibodies. These antibodies react with the glutamate-352-cleaved version of DRONC, but not with full-length DRONC.</p><p>(374 KB JPEG).</p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0020015.sg002.jpg"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><sec id="s5a"><title>Accession Numbers</title><p>The National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>) accession number for p35 is P08160.</p><p>The FlyBase (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://flybase.bio.indiana.edu/search/">http://flybase.bio.indiana.edu/search/</ext-link>) accession numbers of the sequences discussed in this paper are <italic>Ark</italic> (FBgn0024252), cyt-c-d (FBgn0000408), <italic>Dcp-1</italic> (FBgn0010501), <italic>dFadd</italic> (FBgn0038928), <italic>Diap1</italic> (FBgn0003691), <italic>Dredd</italic> (FBgn0020381), <italic>Drice</italic> (FBgn0019972), <italic>Dronc</italic> (FBgn0026404), <italic>Grim</italic> (FBgn0015946), <italic>Hid</italic> (FBgn0003997), and <italic>Reaper</italic> (FBgn0011706).</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Jules Hoffmann, Bruno Lemaitre, Marco Di Fruscio, Kristen White, John Abrams, Alfonso Martinez-Arias, and Takashi Adachi-Yamada for fly stocks; M. E. Bre for AXO49; Lai Wang and Xiaodong Wang for anti-ARK antibodies; Pat Koen and Jean Edens for assistance with EM; and David Anderson for use of his confocal microscope. This work was supported by grants to BAH from the Ellison Medical Foundation and The Burroughs Wellcome Fund (New Investigators Award) and by National Institutes of Health grant R01 GM057422.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="n1" fn-type="COI-statement"><p>
<bold>Conflicts of interest.</bold> The authors have declared that no conflicts of interest exist.</p></fn><fn id="n2" fn-type="con"><p>
<bold>Author contributions.</bold> JRH and BAH conceived and designed the experiments. JRH and SYV performed the experiments. JRH and BAH analyzed the data. JRH, HY, NY, YS, MG, and BAH contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools. JRH and BAH wrote the paper.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="n3" fn-type="edited-by"><p>Academic Editor: Kathryn Miller, Washington University</p></fn><fn id="n4" fn-type="current-aff"><p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email>haybruce@its.caltech.edu</email>
</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pbio-0020015-Adams1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ways of dying: Multiple pathways to apoptosis</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2003</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>2481</fpage><lpage>2495</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14561771</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Akbarsha1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akbarsha</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Latha</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Murugaian</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retention of cytoplasmic droplet by rat cauda epididymal spermatozoa after treatment with cytotoxic and xenobiotic agents</article-title><source>J Reprod Fertil</source><year>2000</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>385</fpage><lpage>390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11058454</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Arama1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arama</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Agapite</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Steller</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Caspase activity and a specific cytochrome c are required for sperm differentiation in <italic>Drosophila</italic>
</article-title><source>Dev Cell</source><year>2003</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>687</fpage><lpage>697</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12737804</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Blanco-Rodriguez1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blanco-Rodriguez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez-Garcia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Apoptosis is physiologically restricted to a specialized cytoplasmic compartment in rat spermatids</article-title><source>Biol Reprod</source><year>1999</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>1541</fpage><lpage>1547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10570001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Braun1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Behringer</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Peschon</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brinster</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmiter</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetically haploid spermatids are phenotypically diploid</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1989</year><volume>337</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>376</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2911388</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Bressac1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bressac</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bre</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Darmanaden-Delorme</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Laurent</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Levilliers</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A massive new posttranslational modification occurs on axonemal tubulin at the final step of spermatogenesis in <italic>Drosophila</italic>
</article-title><source>Eur J Cell Biol</source><year>1995</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>346</fpage><lpage>355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8521874</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Castrillon1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castrillon</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonczy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rawson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Eberhart</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Toward a molecular genetic analysis of spermatogenesis in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila melanogaster</named-content>: Characterization of male-sterile mutants generated by single P element mutagenesis</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1993</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>505</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8244010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Chai1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Huh</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J-W</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular mechanisms of Reaper/Grim/Hid-mediated suppression of DIAP1-dependent Dronc ubiquitination</article-title><source>Nat Struct Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>892</fpage><lpage>898</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14517550</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Chen1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Erskine</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Thach</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Abrams</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dredd, a novel effector of the apoptosis activators <italic>reaper</italic>, <italic>grim</italic>, and <italic>hid</italic> in <italic>Drosophila</italic>
</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><year>1998</year><volume>201</volume><fpage>202</fpage><lpage>216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9740659</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-de1"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Krester</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Knobil</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Neill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cytology of testis</article-title><source>The physiology of reproduction</source><year>1994</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Raven Press</publisher-name><fpage>1177</fpage><lpage>1290</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Ditzel1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ditzel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tenev</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zachariou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Degradation of DIAP1 by the N-end rule pathway is essential for regulating apoptosis</article-title><source>Nat Cell Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12692559</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Dorstyn1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dorstyn</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Read</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cakouros</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Huh</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The role of cytochrome c in caspase activation in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila melanogaster</named-content> cells</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>156</volume><fpage>1089</fpage><lpage>1098</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11901173</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Erickson1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erickson</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Haploid gene expression versus meiotic drive: The relevance of intercellular bridges during spermatogenesis</article-title><source>Nat New Biol</source><year>1973</year><volume>243</volume><fpage>210</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4514960</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Fabrizio1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fabrizio</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hime</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemmon</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bazinet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic dissection of sperm individualization in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila melanogaster</named-content>
</article-title><source>Development</source><year>1998</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>1833</fpage><lpage>1843</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9550716</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Fuller1"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fuller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Martinez-Arias</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bate</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The development of <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila melanogaster</named-content>
</article-title><source>Spermatogenesis</source><year>1993</year><publisher-loc>Cold Spring Harbor, New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Press</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>76</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Goyal1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goyal</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>McCall</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Agapite</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartweig</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Steller</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of apoptosis by <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila reaper</named-content>, <italic>hid</italic> and <italic>grim</italic> through inhibition of IAP function</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2000</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>589</fpage><lpage>597</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10675328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Grether1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grether</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Abrams</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Agapite</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Steller</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>head involution defective</italic> gene of <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila melanogaster</named-content> functions in programmed cell death</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1995</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1694</fpage><lpage>1708</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7622034</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Hawkins1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A cloning method to identify caspases and their regulators in yeast: Identification of <italic>Drosophila</italic> IAP1 as an inhibitor of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> caspase DCP-1</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1999</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>2885</fpage><lpage>2890</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10077606</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Hawkins2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Vernooy</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Drosophila</italic> caspase Dronc cleaves following glutamate or aspartate and is regulated by DIAP1, HID, and GRIM</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>27084</fpage><lpage>27093</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10825159</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Hay1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding IAP function and regulation: A view from <italic>Drosophila</italic>
</article-title><source>Cell Death Differ</source><year>2000</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1045</fpage><lpage>1056</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11139277</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Hay2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of baculovirus P35 prevents cell death in <italic>Drosophila</italic>
</article-title><source>Development</source><year>1994</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>2121</fpage><lpage>2129</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7925015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Hicks1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hicks</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogat</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bownes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Class VI unconventional myosin is required for spermatogenesis in <italic>Drosophila</italic>
</article-title><source>Mol Biol Cell</source><year>1999</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>4341</fpage><lpage>4353</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10588662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Honarpour1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Honarpour</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammer</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adult Apaf-1-deficient mice exhibit male infertility</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><year>2000</year><volume>218</volume><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>258</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10656767</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Horng1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horng</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Medzhitov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>
<italic>Drosophila</italic> MyD88 is an adaptor in the Toll signaling pathway</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2001</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>12654</fpage><lpage>12658</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11606776</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Hu1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>dFADD, a novel death domain-containing adaptor protein for the <italic>Drosophila</italic> caspase Dredd</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>30761</fpage><lpage>30764</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10934188</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Hultmark1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hultmark</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>
<italic>Drosophila</italic> immunity: Paths and patterns</article-title><source>Curr Opin Immunol</source><year>2003</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12495727</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Igaki1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Igaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto-Goto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tokushige</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Miura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Down-regulation of DIAP1 triggers a novel <italic>Drosophila</italic> cell death pathway mediated by Dark and Dronc</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>23103</fpage><lpage>23106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12011068</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Jacobson1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Weil</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Raff</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Programmed cell death in animal development</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1997</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>354</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9039261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Keating1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keating</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Grundy</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fivey</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigation of the association between the presence of cytoplasmic residues on the human sperm midpiece and defective sperm function</article-title><source>J Reprod Fertil</source><year>1997</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9227359</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Knudson1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knudson</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tung</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tourtellotte</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Korsmeyer</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bax-deficient mice with lymphoid hyperplasia and male germ cell death</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1995</year><volume>270</volume><fpage>96</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7569956</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Krajewski1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krajewski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Krajewska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunohistochemical analysis of <italic>in vivo</italic> patterns of Bak expression, a proapoptotic member of the Bcl-2 protein family</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>1996</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>2849</fpage><lpage>2855</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8665525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Kumar1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Doumanis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The fly caspases</article-title><source>Cell Death Differ</source><year>2000</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1039</fpage><lpage>1044</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11139276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Leulier1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leulier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Khush</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Abrams</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemaitre</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Drosophila</italic> caspase Dredd is required to resist gram-negative bacterial infection</article-title><source>EMBO Rep</source><year>2000</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11269502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Lindsley1"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindsley</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Tokuyasu</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Ashburner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spermatogenesis</article-title><source>Genetics and biology of <italic>Drosophila</italic></source><year>1980</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>294</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Lisi1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lisi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazzon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diverse domains of THREAD/DIAP1 are required to inhibit apoptosis induced by REAPER and HID in <italic>Drosophila</italic>
</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2000</year><volume>154</volume><fpage>669</fpage><lpage>678</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10655220</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Martin-Blanco1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin-Blanco</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gampel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ring</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Virdee</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirov</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>
<italic>puckered</italic> encodes a phosphatase that mediates a feedback loop regulating JNK activity during dorsal closure in <italic>Drosophila</italic>
</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1998</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>557</fpage><lpage>570</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9472024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Meier1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Silke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Leevers</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Evan</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Drosophila</italic> caspase Dronc is regulated by DIAP1</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2000</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>598</fpage><lpage>611</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10675329</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Muro1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muro</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Clem</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Drosophila</italic> DIAP1 protein is required to prevent accumulation of a continuously generated, processed form of the apical caspase Dronc</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>49644</fpage><lpage>49650</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12397080</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Naitza1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naitza</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosse</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kappler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Georgel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Belvin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Drosophila</italic> immune defense against gram-negative infection requires the death protein dFADD</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2002</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>575</fpage><lpage>581</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12433364</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Noguchi1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A role for actin dynamics in individualization during spermatogenesis in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila melanogaster</named-content>
</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2003</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>1805</fpage><lpage>1816</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12642486</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Peterson1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Carney</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>
<italic>reaper</italic> is required for neuroblast apoptosis during <italic>Drosophila</italic> development</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2002</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>1467</fpage><lpage>1476</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Randerson1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Randerson</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurst</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The uncertain evolution of the sexes</article-title><source>Trends Ecol Evol</source><year>2001</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>571</fpage><lpage>579</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Rodriguez1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dark is a <italic>Drosophila</italic> homologue of Apaf-1/CED-4 and functions in an evolutionarily conserved death pathway</article-title><source>Nat Cell Biol</source><year>1999</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>272</fpage><lpage>279</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10559939</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Rodriguez2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Abrams</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unrestrained caspase-dependent cell death caused by loss of Diap1 function requires the <italic>Drosophila</italic> Apaf-1 homolog, Dark</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2002</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>2189</fpage><lpage>2197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11980716</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Russell1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The perils of sperm release: &#x0201c;Let my children go.&#x0201d;</article-title><source>Int J Androl</source><year>1991</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>311</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1794915</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Russell2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiarini-Garcia</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Korsmeyer</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Knudson</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bax-dependent spermatogonia apoptosis is required for testicular development and spermatogenesis</article-title><source>Biol Reprod</source><year>2002</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>950</fpage><lpage>958</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11906913</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Santel1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaufmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyland</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Renkawitz-Pohl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The initiator element of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> &#x003b2;2 tubulin gene core promoter contributes to gene expression <italic>in vivo</italic> but is not required for male germ-cell specific expression</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1439</fpage><lpage>1446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10684940</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Shi1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of caspase activation and inhibition during apoptosis</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>459</fpage><lpage>470</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11931755</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Shiratsuchi1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shiratsuchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Umeda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohba</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakanishi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recognition of phosphatidylserine on the surface of apoptotic spermatogenic cells and subsequent phagocytosis by Sertoli cells of the rat</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1997</year><volume>272</volume><fpage>2354</fpage><lpage>2358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8999945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Tokuyasu1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tokuyasu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamics of spermiogenesis in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila melanogaster</named-content>. I. Individualization process</article-title><source>Z Zellforsch Mikrosk Anat</source><year>1972</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>479</fpage><lpage>506</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4622067</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Wang1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>H-A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Drosophila</italic> caspase inhibitor DIAP1 is essential for cell survival and is negatively regulated by Hid</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1999</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>453</fpage><lpage>463</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10481910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-White1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Grether</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Abrams</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic control of programmed cell death in <italic>Drosophila</italic>
</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1994</year><volume>264</volume><fpage>677</fpage><lpage>683</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8171319</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Wilson1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Goyal</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ditzel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zachariou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The DIAP1 RING finger mediates ubiquitination of Dronc and is indispensable for regulating apoptosis</article-title><source>Nat Cell Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12021771</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Yoo1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Huh</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Muro</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Apoptosis inducers Hid, Rpr and Grim negatively regulate levels of the caspase inhibitor DIAP1 by distinct mechanisms</article-title><source>Nat Cell Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>416</fpage><lpage>424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12021767</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020015-Zimmermann1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricci</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Droin</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of ARK in stress-induced apoptosis in <italic>Drosophila</italic> cells</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>156</volume><fpage>1077</fpage><lpage>1087</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11901172</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>&#x003b2;2tub</term><def><p>&#x003b2;<sub>2</sub>-tubulin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>cyt-c-d</term><def><p>cytochrome c-d</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DCP-1</term><def><p>
<italic>Drosophila</italic> caspase-1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Dn</term><def><p>dominant negative</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EM</term><def><p>electron microscopy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GMR</term><def><p>glass multimer reporter</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IAP</term><def><p>inhibitor of apoptosis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IMD</term><def><p>immune deficiency</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PGRP</term><def><p>peptidoglyclan recognition protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RNAi</term><def><p>RNA interference</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></back></article>