<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">pbio</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosbiol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1544-9173</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1545-7885</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15024427</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">368173</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0020079</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Cell Biology</subject><subject>Molecular Biology/Structural Biology</subject><subject>Systems Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="System Taxonomy"><subject>Saccharomyces</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Extensive Association of Functionally and Cytotopically Related mRNAs with Puf Family RNA-Binding Proteins in Yeast</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">RNA Targets of Yeast Puf Proteins</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>Andr&#x000e9; P</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Herschlag</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><email>herschla@cmgm.stanford.edu</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>Patrick O</given-names></name><email>pbrown@cmgm.stanford.edu</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><bold>1</bold><institution>Department of Biochemistry, Stanford University School of Medicine</institution><addr-line>Stanford, California</addr-line><country>United States of America</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><bold>2</bold><institution>Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Stanford University School of Medicine</institution><addr-line>Stanford, California</addr-line><country>United States of America</country></aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>3</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>3</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>16</day><month>3</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>2</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e79</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>10</month><year>2003</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>9</day><month>1</month><year>2004</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; 2004 Gerber et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2004</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="d35e143" related-article-type="companion" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pbio.0020082" xlink:title="synopsis" vol="2" page="e82">
<article-title>mRNA Targets of RNA-Binding Proteins Suggest an Extensive System for Post-Transcriptional Regulation</article-title>
</related-article><abstract><p>Genes encoding RNA-binding proteins are diverse and abundant in eukaryotic genomes. Although some have been shown to have roles in post-transcriptional regulation of the expression of specific genes, few of these proteins have been studied systematically. We have used an affinity tag to isolate each of the five members of the Puf family of RNA-binding proteins in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</named-content> and DNA microarrays to comprehensively identify the associated mRNAs. Distinct groups of 40&#x02013;220 different mRNAs with striking common themes in the functions and subcellular localization of the proteins they encode are associated with each of the five Puf proteins: Puf3p binds nearly exclusively to cytoplasmic mRNAs that encode mitochondrial proteins; Puf1p and Puf2p interact preferentially with mRNAs encoding membrane-associated proteins; Puf4p preferentially binds mRNAs encoding nucleolar ribosomal RNA-processing factors; and Puf5p is associated with mRNAs encoding chromatin modifiers and components of the spindle pole body. We identified distinct sequence motifs in the 3&#x02032;-untranslated regions of the mRNAs bound by Puf3p, Puf4p, and Puf5p. Three-hybrid assays confirmed the role of these motifs in specific RNA&#x02013;protein interactions in vivo. The results suggest that combinatorial tagging of transcripts by specific RNA-binding proteins may be a general mechanism for coordinated control of the localization, translation, and decay of mRNAs and thus an integral part of the global gene expression program.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="toc"><p>Messenger RNAs that are associated with each of the five Puf RNA-binding proteins can be grouped according to function and localization, suggesting that tagging of transcripts by specific RNA-binding proteins coordinates the control of their localization, translation, and decay</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The dynamic structure and physiology of a cell depend on coordinated synthesis, assembly, and localization of its macromolecular components (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Orphanides1" ref-type="bibr">Orphanides and Reinberg 2002</xref>). The timing and level of expression of the genes that encode these components are controlled by transcription factors that regulate initiation of transcription in a gene-specific manner by binding to specific DNA sequences proximal to the genes they regulate. The combinatorial binding and activity of specific transcription factors confer a distinctive program of regulation on each individual gene while enabling coherent global responses of large sets of genes in physiological and developmental programs. Much less is known about either the system architecture or molecular mechanisms that underlie regulation of the post-transcriptional steps in the gene expression program.</p><p>There are approximately 15,000 mRNA molecules in each <named-content content-type="genus-species">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</named-content> cell during exponential growth in rich medium (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Hereford1" ref-type="bibr">Hereford and Rosbash 1977</xref>) and at least a 10-fold larger number in a typical mammalian cell (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Hastie1" ref-type="bibr">Hastie and Bishop 1976</xref>). The extent to which the location, activity, and fates of these diverse populations of mRNAs are coordinated and the post-transcriptional mechanisms that might mediate their coordinated regulation remain largely unknown. RNA-binding proteins (RBPs) have been implicated in diverse aspects of post-transcriptional gene regulation, including RNA processing, export, localization, degradation, and translational control (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Dreyfuss1" ref-type="bibr">Dreyfuss et al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Maniatis1" ref-type="bibr">Maniatis and Reed 2002</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Mazumder1" ref-type="bibr">Mazumder et al. 2003</xref>). Although there appear to be hundreds of RBPs encoded in eukaryotic genomes (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Costanzo1" ref-type="bibr">Costanzo et al. 2001</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Issel-Tarver1" ref-type="bibr">Issel-Tarver et al. 2002</xref>), for only a few of these proteins have the RNA targets been systematically identified (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Takizawa1" ref-type="bibr">Takizawa et al. 2000</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Tenenbaum1" ref-type="bibr">Tenenbaum et al. 2000</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Brown1" ref-type="bibr">Brown et al. 2001</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Hieronymus1" ref-type="bibr">Hieronymus and Silver 2003</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Li1" ref-type="bibr">Li et al. 2003</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Shepard1" ref-type="bibr">Shepard et al. 2003</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Waggoner1" ref-type="bibr">Waggoner and Liebhaber 2003</xref>). For example, a recent study in <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. cerevisiae</named-content> found that two nuclear RNA export factors were each associated with large and distinct mRNA populations, and common functional themes were found among the 1,000 or so proteins encoded by each population (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Hieronymus1" ref-type="bibr">Hieronymus and Silver 2003</xref>). These observations support a role for RBPs in the coordinated regulation of mRNA subpopulations (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Keene2" ref-type="bibr">Keene and Tenenbaum 2002</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Keene1" ref-type="bibr">Keene 2003</xref>).</p><p>Systematic identification of the mRNA targets of RBPs can be a powerful approach to understanding the cellular roles of RBPs and the mechanisms by which they might regulate the post-transcriptional lives of mRNAs. We have focused first on the Pumilio&#x02013;Fem-3-binding factor (FBF) (Puf) proteins from <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. cerevisiae</named-content>, which belong to a structurally related family of cytoplasmic RBPs that are implicated in developmental processes in various eukaryotes (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Wickens1" ref-type="bibr">Wickens et al. 2002</xref>). Puf proteins are defined by the presence of several (typically eight) consecutive repeats of the Pumilio homology domain (Pum-HD), which confers RNA binding activity (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Zamore1" ref-type="bibr">Zamore et al. 1997</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al. 2002a</xref>). The Puf proteins characterized to date have been reported to bind to 3&#x02032;-untranslated region (UTR) sequences encompassing a so-called UGUR tetranucleotide motif and thereby to repress gene expression by affecting mRNA translation or stability. Despite the widespread occurrence of Puf family members, only a few mRNA targets have been identified for these RBPs (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Wickens1" ref-type="bibr">Wickens et al. 2002</xref>). For example, in <italic>Drosophila</italic>, the PUMILIO protein binds maternal <italic>hunchback</italic> mRNA and, in concert with NANOS protein, represses translation of the mRNA at the posterior pole during early embryogenesis. The <named-content content-type="genus-species">Caenorhabditis elegans</named-content> Puf homologs, called Fem-3-binding factors (FBFs), regulate the switch from spermatogenesis to oogenesis by repressing <italic>fem-3</italic> translation, and they are implicated in the propagation of germline stem cells through binding and inhibition of <italic>gld-1</italic> mRNA expression (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Zhang1" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al. 1997</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Crittenden1" ref-type="bibr">Crittenden et al. 2002</xref>). Less is known about the human homologs: PUMILIO-2 protein interacts with DAZ (deleted in azoospermia) protein and is expressed in embryonic stem cells and germ cells, whereas PUMILIO-1 is almost ubiquitously expressed (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Moore1" ref-type="bibr">Moore et al. 2003</xref>).</p><p>In <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. cerevisiae</named-content>, five proteins, termed Puf1p to Puf5p, bear six to eight Puf repeats (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020079-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Little is known about the physiological function of these proteins. Mutations in either <italic>PUF4</italic> or <italic>PUF5</italic> result in diminished longevity (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Kennedy1" ref-type="bibr">Kennedy et al. 1997</xref>). <italic>PUF1</italic> was isolated as a multicopy suppressor of certain microtubule mutants (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Machin1" ref-type="bibr">Machin et al. 1995</xref>), and a <italic>PUF2</italic> null mutant displayed increased resistance to cycloheximide and paromomycin (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Waskiewicz-Staniorowska1" ref-type="bibr">Waskiewicz-Staniorowska et al. 1998</xref>). However, <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. cerevisiae</named-content> mutants lacking all five <italic>PUF</italic> genes are viable (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Olivas1" ref-type="bibr">Olivas and Parker 2000</xref>). A genome-wide analysis of mRNA expression patterns in yeast mutants lacking all five <italic>PUF</italic> genes found differential expression of 7%&#x02013;8% of all mRNAs under steady-state conditions, but no common theme was found among the affected genes (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Olivas1" ref-type="bibr">Olivas and Parker 2000</xref>). Only two specific mRNA targets have been identified for yeast Puf proteins: Puf3p binds to the <italic>COX17</italic> mRNA 3&#x02032;-UTR in vitro and may regulate its turnover (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Olivas1" ref-type="bibr">Olivas and Parker 2000</xref>), and Puf5p negatively regulates expression of reporter genes substituting for the HO endonuclease (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Tadauchi1" ref-type="bibr">Tadauchi et al. 2001</xref>).</p><fig id="pbio-0020079-g001" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Protein Domain Structure of Yeast Puf Proteins</title><p>Pum-HD repeats (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Zamore1" ref-type="bibr">Zamore et al. 1997</xref>) are shown as red ovals and classical RNA-binding domains (RBDs) are depicted as blue boxes. Regions of low complexity, such as proline-, serine-, threonine-, and/or methionine-rich domains, are shown in gray boxes; asparagine stretches are striped. The numbers correspond to the length of proteins in amino acids.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020079.g001"/></fig><p>Using DNA microarrays to identify the specific mRNAs that interact with the five <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. cerevisiae</named-content> Puf proteins, we have found that each Puf protein bound to a large set of distinct and functionally related mRNAs. We identified novel and conserved sequence elements in the mRNAs bound by Puf3p, Puf4p, and Puf5p. The results suggest a system for large-scale coordinated control of cytoplasmic mRNAs and provide insights into the physiological logic of the gene expression program.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Systematic Identification of mRNAs Associated with Specific RBPs</title><p>To identify RNAs associated with Puf proteins, tandem-affinity purification (TAP)-tagged proteins were purified from whole-cell extracts of <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. cerevisiae</named-content> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020079-g002">Figure 2</xref>). The TAP tag (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Rigaut1" ref-type="bibr">Rigaut et al. 1999</xref>), a sequence encoding two IgG-binding units of protein A, a specific protease recognition site, and a calmodulin-binding domain, was fused in-frame at the C-terminus of the respective open reading frame (ORF) in its original chromosomal location (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Ghaemmaghami1" ref-type="bibr">Ghaemmaghami et al. 2003</xref>). This design was intended to preserve normal regulation of the expression of the fusion protein. Cells of the TAP-tagged strains showed growth rates and cell morphologies similar to wild-type cells. Cells were grown to mid-log phase in rich medium, extracts were prepared, and ribonucleoprotein complexes were recovered by affinity selection on IgG beads and subsequent cleavage with tobacco etch virus (TEV) protease (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>). To control for nonspecifically enriched mRNAs, the same procedure was performed with wild-type cells lacking the TAP tag. TEV protease cleavage was superior to direct elution of proteins from beads, as it gave lower contamination from nonspecifically interacting RNAs in the resulting purified fractions (data not shown). RNA was isolated from the purified protein samples and from extracts. We obtained 0.8&#x02013;2 &#x003bc;g of RNA from the Puf affinity-isolated samples gathered from 1-l cultures, but no detectable RNA (&#x0003c;0.1 &#x003bc;g) was recovered when the same procedure was applied to untagged control cells. The yield of RNA from the Puf affinity isolation procedure was sufficient to perform further labeling steps directly, without amplification of RNA by PCR, as had been required in previous studies (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Takizawa1" ref-type="bibr">Takizawa et al. 2000</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Hieronymus1" ref-type="bibr">Hieronymus and Silver 2003</xref>). Two samples from each cell population, total RNA, and RNA isolated by the Puf affinity procedure were used to prepare cDNA probes labeled with different fluorescent dyes, which were mixed and hybridized to <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. cerevisiae</named-content> DNA microarrays containing all known and putative ORFs, introns, and the mitochondrial genome (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>). The ratio of the fluorescent hybridization signals from the two differentially labeled RNA samples, at the array element representing each specific gene, provided an assay for enrichment of the corresponding mRNA by the Puf-affinity procedure.</p><fig id="pbio-0020079-g002" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Strategy for Analyzing Genome-Wide RNA&#x02013;Protein Interactions</title><p>Protein A-tagged Puf proteins were captured with IgG&#x02013;Sepharose and released from the beads by cleavage with TEV protease. RNAs associated with the released proteins were isolated, and cDNA copies were fluorescently labeled and hybridized to yeast DNA microarrays. The Cy5/Cy3 fluorescence ratio for each locus reflects its enrichment by affinity for the cognate protein.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020079.g002"/></fig><p>Puf3p is the only one of the five <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. cerevisiae</named-content> Puf proteins for which direct in vitro interaction with an mRNA (<italic>COX17</italic>) has previously been described, thereby providing an internal positive control (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Olivas1" ref-type="bibr">Olivas and Parker 2000</xref>). <italic>COX17</italic> mRNA was substantially and consistently enriched in four independent Puf3p affinity isolations (ratio = 10 &#x000b1; 1.4; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020079-g003">Figure 3</xref>A), but not in mock isolations (ratio = 0.8 &#x000b1; 1.2). In general, after filtering for spots with high background or irregular shapes, enrichment values for the entire set of arrayed sequences were reproducible (median of standard deviations in all arrayed spots = 0.35 on a log<sub>2</sub> scale) (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>). To define targets specific to each Puf protein, we first selected all sequences for which enrichment factors in the corresponding affinity isolation procedures were at least two standard deviations above the mean for all arrayed sequences (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sg001">Figure S1</xref>; for samples isolated by the Puf3p-affinity procedure, this corresponded to an enrichment factor of greater than or equal to 2.5). Second, we eliminated from this selected group any sequences that were also consistently enriched in the mock procedure (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>). Although no cutoff can perfectly distinguish the actual physiological targets from false positives, the high reproducibility of the results (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020079-g003">Figure 3</xref>B), the occurrence of distinct mRNA populations associated with the different Puf proteins, and the characterization of these targets described in the subsequent sections, including the identification of distinct sequence motifs and in vivo confirmation of the role of these motifs in specific RNA&#x02013;protein interactions, strongly support the validity of the majority of the targets. Finally, the list of target mRNAs did not change substantially by application of other statistical methods for selection (see <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Lieb1" ref-type="bibr">Lieb et al. 2001</xref>).</p><fig id="pbio-0020079-g003" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Defining Puf Target RNAs</title><p>(A) Distribution of average Cy5/Cy3 fluorescence ratios from four independent microarray hybridizations analyzing Puf3p targets. The arrow depicts enrichment of <italic>COX17</italic> mRNA, which is known to bind to Puf3p (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Olivas1" ref-type="bibr">Olivas and Parker 2000</xref>). The red dashed line indicates the threshold applied for defining 220 target RNAs (a magnification is shown of the enriched region).</p><p>(B) Cluster of RNA targets for Puf proteins. Rows represent genes (unique cDNA elements) and columns represent individual experimental samples. Each Puf protein and an untagged strain (mock control) were assayed in quadruplicate. The color code indicates enrichments (green&#x02013;red color scale). The number of mRNAs interacting with each Puf protein is indicated in parentheses. mRNAs clustering with the mock controls were removed as false positives (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020079.g003"/></fig><p>A large number of arrayed sequences, 818, identified transcripts associated with at least one Puf protein (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020079-g003">Figure 3</xref>B; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="st001">Table S1</xref>), with 735 encoding distinct ORFs. This represents approximately 12% of the known and predicted protein-coding sequences in the <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. cerevisiae</named-content> genome. Of these, 90 transcripts interact with more than one Puf protein. The largest overlap was observed between the groups of transcripts associated with Puf1p and Puf2p&#x02014;which also have the greatest overall similarity in amino acid sequence among the Puf proteins (45% identical); 36 of the 40 Puf1p targets were also associated with Puf2p. Twenty-eight mRNAs were bound by both Puf4p and Puf5p, and 16 were bound both by Puf2p and Puf5p. Seven transcripts were enriched with three different Puf proteins (<italic>DHH1</italic> and <italic>YOL109w</italic> mRNAs with Puf1p, Puf2p, and Puf5p; <italic>NOP1</italic> mRNA with Puf1p, Puf4p, and Puf5p; <italic>SUR7</italic> and <italic>SFL1</italic> mRNAs with Puf2p, Puf4p, and Puf5p; and <italic>IFM1</italic> mRNA with Puf3p, Puf4p, and Puf5p). The remaining 645 target mRNAs were each associated with only one of the Puf proteins. Thus, each Puf protein associates with a distinct and highly specific subset of mRNAs (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="st003">Tables S3&#x02013;S7</xref>).</p><p>We estimated the number of Puf proteins per cell by a filter affinity blot analysis using protein A as a standard for calibration (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="st002">Table S2</xref>). We found that Puf1p, Puf2p, Puf3p, and Puf5p were similar in abundance, with 350&#x02013;400 molecules per cell. Puf4p was approximately twice as abundant (approximately 900 molecules per cell). The relatively low abundance of the Puf proteins is therefore comparable to that of transcription factors, protein kinases, and cell cycle proteins (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Futcher1" ref-type="bibr">Futcher et al. 1999</xref>). Moreover, our measurements imply that the intracellular concentrations of the Puf proteins range between 20 and 50 nM, approximately one order of magnitude higher than the dissociation constants for binding of their metazoan homologs to the cognate target RNAs. The number of Puf proteins per cell approximates the estimated numbers of cognate Puf target mRNA molecules present in the cell (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Holstege1" ref-type="bibr">Holstege et al. 1998</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Wang2" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al. 2002b</xref>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="st002">Table S2</xref>), consistent with a model in which each Puf protein molecule is associated with one mRNA molecule in the cell.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Puf3p Specifically Binds mRNAs Encoding Mitochondrial Proteins</title><p>As a first step toward identifying functional themes among the mRNAs associated with each Puf protein, we retrieved the Gene Ontology (GO) annotations for process, function, and compartment from the <italic>Saccharomyces</italic> Genome Database (SGD) (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Issel-Tarver1" ref-type="bibr">Issel-Tarver et al. 2002</xref>). (The target mRNAs for each Puf protein are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="st003">Tables S3&#x02013;S7</xref>.) We then searched for significant shared GO terms in the lists of Puf mRNA targets (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="st008">Table S8</xref>).</p><p>Puf3p associated almost exclusively with transcripts of nuclear genes that encode mitochondrial proteins (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 10<sup>&#x02212;88</sup>; see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="st005">Table S5</xref>). In particular, of the 154 Puf3p-associated transcripts for which GO annotation of subcellular localization was available, 135 (87%) were assigned to mitochondria (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020079-g004">Figure 4</xref>A). Of the Puf3p-associated mitochondrial gene products, 80 (59%) are involved in protein biosynthesis, including structural components of the ribosome (55 genes), tRNA ligases (12 genes), and translational regulators (nine genes). Twenty-two of the Puf3p-bound transcripts are involved in mitochondrial organization and biogenesis, 17 in aerobic respiration, and 12 in mitochondrial translocation. Based on this striking cytotopic (relating to location in the cell) concordance, we suggest that the remaining 66 Puf3p mRNA substrates (30%) for which no GO annotations were available are likely to encode mitochondrial proteins. (While this paper was under review, a genome-wide analysis of protein localization in <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. cerevisiae</named-content> [<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Huh1" ref-type="bibr">Huh et al. 2003</xref>] reported a mitochondrial localization for 27 additional Puf3p targets, raising the total to 162 of the 220 putative Puf3p mRNA targets encoding mitochondrial proteins.)</p><fig id="pbio-0020079-g004" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Classification of mRNAs Interacting with Puf Proteins</title><p>(A) Column charts showing compartmentalization of characterized gene products encoded by the Puf targets. The same compartments are shown for the entire genome in the columns designed &#x0201c;All&#x0201d; (YPD, May 2003). The number of genes represented in the charts is indicated on the top of columns. An asterisk indicates classes with <italic>p</italic> values of less than 0.001.</p><p>(B) Fraction of membrane-associated gene products among the Puf targets. We classified the targets by combining both GO and YPD annotations (May 2003). &#x0201c;Plasma membrane&#x0201d; (light blue) is a subpopulation of the total membrane-associated proteins (blue). Soluble cytoplasmic or nuclear proteins were classified as &#x0201c;non-membrane.&#x0201d; &#x0201c;All&#x0201d; refers to the genome-wide compartmentalization of characterized genes, and respective numbers were retrieved from YPD. &#x0201c;Puf2 Top 40&#x0201d; refers to the 40 highest enriched Puf2p targets and equals the total number of Puf1p targets.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020079.g004"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Puf1p- and Puf2p-Associated mRNAs Disproportionately Encode Membrane-Associated Proteins</title><p>Of all the characterized <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. cerevisiae</named-content> genes for which any information about subcellular localization is available, 18% are currently classified as encoding membrane-associated proteins (Yeast Proteome Database [YPD], May 2003; see <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Costanzo1" ref-type="bibr">Costanzo et al. 2001</xref>). A much greater fraction of the mRNAs associated with Puf1p and Puf2p encode membrane-associated proteins: 16 of the 28 (57%) known proteins encoded by Puf1p-interacting mRNAs and 55 of 106 (52%) known proteins encoded by Puf2p-interacting mRNAs (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020079-g003">Figure 3</xref>B; see Tables <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="st003">S3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="st004">S4</xref>). Transcripts encoding proteins associated with the plasma membrane were particularly enriched among the Puf1p- and Puf2p-bound mRNAs. Most of the mRNAs bound by Puf1p were also associated with Puf2p. However, Puf2p bound uniquely to many additional mRNAs (146 Puf2p mRNA targets versus 40 for Puf1p). In terms of cellular processes, many Puf1p- and Puf2p-associated transcripts encode proteins with roles in transmembrane transport and vesicular trafficking of proteins: 9 out of 26 (34%; <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0002) of annotated Puf1p targets and 24 out of 104 (23%; <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>) annotated Puf2p targets (compared to 9% of all characterized genes) (YPD, May 2003). This group includes transporters for spermine (Tpo1, Tpo2, Tpo3), proteins (Nce101, Nce102, Ast1, Vps72, Mas6, Sfk1, Mup3), vesicles (Sso2, Snc2, Yip1, Aps3, Ypr157w), and lipids (Pdr16, Ykl091c, Fps1 [glycerol]). (Tpo2 and Tpo3 may cross-hybridize on arrays because of their high sequence identity [89%], but Tpo1 does not [<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Shepard1" ref-type="bibr">Shepard et al. 2003</xref>]).</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Puf4p and Puf5p Interact Selectively with mRNAs Encoding Nuclear Components </title><p>Among the Puf5p targets (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="st006">Table S6</xref>), we found two common themes. First, a remarkable fraction encodes nuclear proteins that participate in covalent modification of histones, chromatin-remodeling complexes, or transcriptional regulation (64 of the 113 annotated genes [57%; <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup>]). Second, the Puf5p-associated transcripts included a substantial fraction of the mRNAs known to encode components or regulators of the mitotic spindle apparatus in yeast: 14 mRNAs that encode microtubule-based spindle components, including seven of the 25 (28%; <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>) structural components of the spindle pole body (Kar1, Ccd31, Spc19, Spc42, Bbp1, Cnm67, and Nuf2) (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Wigge1" ref-type="bibr">Wigge et al. 1998</xref>). Messages encoding nuclear and cytoplasmic proteins that regulate polarized growth (Ame1, Boi2, Bsp1, Bub1, Bud9, Dad2, Elm1, Gic1, Kar9, Rax2, Ste7), some of them known to interact with spindle components, were also Puf5p targets.</p><p>Transcripts encoding nucleolar proteins were highly enriched among the Puf4p-bound mRNAs: 36 of the 133 (27%) annotated genes in this group encode nucleolar proteins, as compared to 3% of all the annotated genes in the <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. cerevisiae</named-content> genome (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 10<sup>&#x02212;12</sup>). Of these 36, 29 are directly involved in ribosomal RNA (rRNA) synthesis, processing, and ribosome maturation (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 10<sup>&#x02212;15</sup>), major functions of the nucleolus (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Fatica1" ref-type="bibr">Fatica and Tollervey 2002</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Gerbi1" ref-type="bibr">Gerbi et al. 2003</xref>) (see Tables <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="st005">S5</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="st008">S8</xref>).</p><p>Twenty-eight transcripts were enriched in both the Puf4p and Puf5p affinity isolations, including six transcripts encoding components of the nucleosome (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 10<sup>&#x02212;11</sup>), among them the four core histone proteins (histones 2A and 2B, histone 3, and histone 4; note that histones 2A and 2B are 98% identical and therefore cross-hybridize).</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Diverse Functional Links among Transcripts Associated with Each Puf Protein</title><p>In addition to the cytotopic relationships within each group of Puf-associated mRNAs, we were struck by the frequency with which transcripts encoding different components of protein complexes or systems of interacting proteins were bound by the Puf proteins. For example, most of the nuclear transcripts encoding components of the mitochondrial ribosome (55 out of the 77 known genes; <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Gan1" ref-type="bibr">Gan et al. 2002</xref>) were Puf3p-associated. This observation prompted us to search for other protein complexes and functional systems that shared similarly Puf-associated mRNAs.</p><p>Other examples of coordinate &#x0201c;tagging&#x0201d; of transcripts encoding subunits of multiprotein complexes include Puf4p association of mRNAs encoding three of the four protein components of the H/ACA core particle (Cbf5p, Gar1p, and Nhp2p), which synthesizes pseudouridine in rRNAs (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Henras1" ref-type="bibr">Henras et al. 1998</xref>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sg002">Figure S2</xref>; no data were obtained for the fourth component, Nop10p). Puf5p bound mRNAs encoding histone acetylases (Ada2p, Spt8p, and Hfi1p), which are components of the Spt&#x02013;Ada&#x02013;Gcn5&#x02013;acetyltransferase (SAGA) complex, and transcripts encoding at least four of the six members of the RSC (remodels the structure of chromatin) family of DNA-stimulated ATPases with bromodomains (Bdf1p, Bdf2p, Rsc2p, and Rsc4p; no array data were obtained for the two other members, Rsc1p and Spt7p). As mentioned above, the mRNAs encoding at least three of the four core histones were enriched in both Puf4p and Puf5p affinity isolations.</p><p>We also found numerous cases in which the transcripts encoding multiple members of a functional group of proteins were bound by the same Puf protein. For example, the transcripts encoding the Tpo1, Tpo2, and Tpo3 proteins, the three known spermine transporters in the plasma membrane (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Albertsen1" ref-type="bibr">Albertsen et al. 2003</xref>; see note above about cross-hybridization), and the two known genes implicated in the nonclassical protein export pathway (<italic>NCE101</italic>, <italic>NCE102</italic>) (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Cleves1" ref-type="bibr">Cleves et al. 1996</xref>) were bound by Puf1p and Puf2p and by Puf2p, respectively. Puf5p was associated with all of the histone deacetylases (HDACs) that act on histones located around coding sequences&#x02014;Sin3p (a class I HDAC), Hda1p (a class II HDAC), and both components of the Set3C complex (Hst1p and Snt1p) (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Kurdistani1" ref-type="bibr">Kurdistani and Grunstein 2003</xref>). (Two other HDACs, Hos1p and Hos3p, which deacetylate histones around the ribosomal DNA locus, were not enriched in Puf5p affinity isolations.)</p><p>Finally, we identified cases in which the mRNAs encoding multiple components of a specific regulatory system were bound by the same Puf protein. For example, Puf2p associates with mRNAs encoding diverse proteins regulating Pma1p, which is an ATP-dependent proton transporter located in the plasma membrane, and with <italic>PMA1</italic> mRNA itself (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sg002">Figure S2</xref>). All of the mRNAs encoding nucleolar glycine/arginine-rich (GAR) domain-bearing proteins (Sbp1p, Nsr1p, Nop1p, Gar1p) as well as <italic>HMT1</italic> mRNA, encoding a dimethylase that modifies the nucleolar GAR proteins (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Xu1" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al. 2003</xref>), were associated with Puf4p, while none of the mRNAs encoding the distinct group of nonnucleolar GAR proteins were bound by Puf4p (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sg002">Figure S2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Sequence Motifs in the 3&#x02032;-UTR of mRNA Targets Direct Binding by Puf Proteins</title><p>The Puf homologs in <italic>Drosophila</italic> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. elegans</named-content> bind to sequences in the 3&#x02032;-UTR of mRNAs (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Wickens1" ref-type="bibr">Wickens et al. 2002</xref>). We therefore examined the sets of mRNAs associated with each of the <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. cerevisiae</named-content> Puf proteins for the presence of common sequence motifs in 5&#x02032;-UTRs and 3&#x02032;-UTRs, using multiple expectation maximization for motif elicitation (MEME) as a motif discovery tool (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Bailey1" ref-type="bibr">Bailey and Elkan 1994</xref>). We identified distinct 10- or 11-nucleotide sequence motifs in the 3&#x02032;-UTR among the mRNAs interacting with Puf3p, Puf4p, and Puf5p (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020079-g005">Figure 5</xref>A, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="st009">Tables S9&#x02013;S11</xref>). We have thus far been unable to identify conserved sequence elements among Puf1p and Puf2p targets; these proteins may recognize structural elements in the RNA rather than simple sequence strings, possibly via their classical RNA-binding domains instead of their six-repeat Pumillio domains.</p><fig id="pbio-0020079-g005" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Sequence Motifs Interacting with Puf Proteins</title><p>(A) Consensus motifs detected within 3&#x02032;-UTR sequences of Puf3p, Puf4p, and Puf5p target mRNAs. Height of the letters specifies the probability of appearing at the position in the motif. Letters with less than 10% appearance were omitted. Fraction of genes bearing a motif in the 3&#x02032;-UTR sequence is indicated to the right. Y-helicase proteins are nearly identical in sequence and were excluded from this analysis.</p><p>(B) Scheme of three-hybrid assay for monitoring RNA&#x02013;protein interactions in vivo (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Bernstein1" ref-type="bibr">Bernstein et al. 2002</xref>).</p><p>(C) &#x003b2;-Galactosidase activity for three-hybrid assay. Proteins assayed are indicated on top, RNAs to the left. Abbreviations: pum, pum-HD; cons., consensus motif; UGU/AGA, UGU in consensus sequence mutated to AGA.</p><p>(D) Activation of <italic>HIS3</italic> reporter gene and resistance to 3-aminotriazole (3-AT), a competitive inhibitor of the <italic>HIS3</italic> gene product, in a three-hybrid assay (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Bernstein1" ref-type="bibr">Bernstein et al. 2002</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020079.g005"/></fig><p>The conserved motifs we identified in the Puf3p, Puf4p, and Puf5p targets each include a UGUR tetranucleotide sequence, which is a feature of all previously reported RNA targets of Puf family proteins (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Wickens1" ref-type="bibr">Wickens et al. 2002</xref>). Furthermore, in each case, the consensus sequence contains a conserved dinucleotide (UA), located two, three, or four nucleotides downstream of the UGUR motif, in the consensus sites for Puf3p, Puf4p, and Puf5p. Remarkably, the Puf3p consensus motif matches a sequence (CYUGUAAAUA) previously identified by computational tools in 3&#x02032;-UTR sequences of nuclear genes coding for mitochondrial proteins (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Jacobs1" ref-type="bibr">Jacobs Anderson and Parker 2000</xref>).</p><p>We examined the distribution of the consensus sequence motifs in the entire <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. cerevisiae</named-content> genome (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pbio-0020079-t001">Table 1</xref>). Of the genes whose mRNAs were predicted by computational analysis to contain one of these three target sequences in their 3&#x02032;-UTRs, 42% were identified experimentally as targets in the corresponding affinity isolation procedure (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pbio-0020079-t001">Table 1</xref>). The consensus motifs were occasionally found in the coding sequence of an experimentally identified target gene, but were much rarer in the predicted 5&#x02032;-UTR sequences (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pbio-0020079-t001">Table 1</xref>). Moreover, only a few mRNAs had two copies of the motifs: five mRNAs among the Puf3p targets, six among the Puf4p targets, and one among the Puf5p targets (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="st005">Tables S5&#x02013;S7</xref>). As our computational method did not detect the cognate consensus sequence elements in all the experimentally identified targets, alternative sequences or structural elements in RNAs might also allow specific interactions with Puf proteins, some mRNAs may be associated indirectly as part of larger complexes, and some of the putative mRNA targets identified by our affinity procedure are likely to be false positives.</p><table-wrap id="pbio-0020079-t001" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Number of Consensus Motifs Found in the Genome and in Puf Targets</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020079.t001"/><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><p>
<sup>a</sup>Known and putative ORFs (6,330 genes) from SGD</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><p>
<sup>b</sup>The probability that the motifs are enriched in Puf targets by chance</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><p>
<sup>c</sup>Average lengths of predicted UTR sequences (134 bp of 5&#x02032;-UTR sequences, 237 bp of 3&#x02032;-UTR sequences; <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Mignone1" ref-type="bibr">Mignone et al. 2002</xref>). Syntax for multiple bases: H = A/C/T, W = A/T, Y = C/T</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>To test the in vivo function of the putative recognition elements identified by the computational analysis, we assayed RNA&#x02013;protein interactions in vivo using the yeast three-hybrid system (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Bernstein1" ref-type="bibr">Bernstein et al. 2002</xref>) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020079-g005">Figure 5</xref>B). Puf3p, Puf4p, and Puf5p bound specifically to a sequence matching to the cognate consensus sequence, as assayed by activation of the <italic>lacZ</italic> and <italic>HIS3</italic> reporter genes (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020079-g005">Figure 5</xref>C and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020079-g005">5</xref>D). For Puf3p and Puf4p, the Pum-HD alone was sufficient to confer specific binding (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020079-g005">Figure 5</xref>C and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020079-g005">5</xref>D), but no interaction could be seen with the Puf5p Pum-HD alone (data not shown). These interactions were specific: mutations in the UGU of the Puf3p consensus sequence disrupted binding, and each Puf protein interacted with its cognate consensus sequence in preference to the closely related consensus sequences recognized by the other Puf proteins. We detected a weak interaction between Puf3p and the Puf4p target sequence, an interaction that was not seen with the Puf3p Pum-HD alone. These results suggest that binding of the Puf proteins to these specific <italic>cis</italic>-acting elements directs their functions to specific sets of mRNAs.</p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>Subcellular Distribution of Puf Proteins</title><p>We investigated the localization of the TAP-tagged Puf proteins by immunofluorescence with antibodies against the TAP tag (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>). All five Puf proteins were predominantly localized to multiple discrete foci in the cytoplasm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020079-g006">Figure 6</xref>). The predominantly cytoplasmic localization is consistent with previous reports for <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. cerevisiae</named-content> Puf3p and Puf5p (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Tadauchi1" ref-type="bibr">Tadauchi et al. 2001</xref>) and for the homologous proteins in higher eukaryotes (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Lehmann1" ref-type="bibr">Lehmann and N&#x000fc;sslein-Volhard 1991</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Zhang1" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al. 1997</xref>). The distribution of the foci of Puf proteins was not obviously related to distinct cellular organelles or structures, with the exception of Puf1p and Puf2p, which localized in foci enriched near the periphery of the cell. Because of the diffuse and pleiomorphic distribution of mitochondria in the cell, we cannot exclude the possibility that Puf3p, which specifically bound transcripts of proteins destined for the mitochondria, is associated with mitochondria.</p><fig id="pbio-0020079-g006" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Localization of Puf Proteins</title><p>TAP-tagged Puf proteins were visualized in fixed cells. DNA was costained with 4&#x02032;,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole dimethylsulfoxide (DAPI).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020079.g006"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2h"><title>Altered Levels of Puf3p-Associated mRNAs in a <italic>puf3</italic>&#x00394; Mutant </title><p>A previous study compared steady-state mRNAs levels of cells bearing deletions of all five Puf proteins and wild-type cells grown in rich media (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Olivas1" ref-type="bibr">Olivas and Parker 2000</xref>). Only 12 of the 148 (8%) mRNAs whose abundance changed by more than 2-fold were selectively enriched in our affinity isolations with Puf proteins. The lack of a simple relationship between the mRNA binding specificity we observed and the reported effects of these multiple mutations on global gene expression prompted us to design a more specific experiment to search for a possible connection between specific mRNAs levels and binding to Puf proteins. We focused on Puf3p, as its strong association with mRNA-encoding mitochondrial proteins suggested that we should look for a regulatory function for this protein in mitochondrial physiology. Indeed, we found that <italic>puf3</italic>&#x00394; cells grew more slowly than isogenic <italic>puf3<sup>+</sup></italic> cells on minimal media plates with glycerol as the carbon source (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sg003">Figure S3</xref>). We therefore compared mRNA levels in the <italic>puf3</italic>&#x00394; and <italic>puf3<sup>+</sup></italic> cells grown under these conditions by DNA microarray hybridization. Although the magnitude of the change was small, the relative expression levels of the 220 Puf3p-associated mRNAs were selectively increased in <italic>puf3</italic>&#x00394; cells, compared to all other mRNAs analyzed (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 10<sup>&#x02212;34</sup>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020079-g007">Figure 7</xref>). Of the 16 mRNAs whose abundance was increased by more than 2-fold in the <italic>puf3</italic>&#x00394; mutant, 11 (70%) were among the transcripts identified as Puf3p targets by our co-purification experiments, and all encode mitochondrial proteins. This result could reflect a direct effect of Puf3p on its target mRNAs, for example, by promoting mRNA decay (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Olivas1" ref-type="bibr">Olivas and Parker 2000</xref>). However, the levels of transcripts involved in respiration and mitochondrial function, including many that did not appear to be bound directly by Puf3p, were increased in the <italic>puf3</italic>&#x00394; mutant, suggesting the possibility that the elevated abundance of Puf3p target mRNAs could instead be an indirect response to impaired mitochondrial and respiratorial function in <italic>puf3</italic>&#x00394; cells.</p><fig id="pbio-0020079-g007" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Gene Expression Profiling of <italic>puf3</italic> Mutants</title><p>Distribution of average Cy5/Cy3 fluorescence ratios from three independent microarray hybridizations comparing mRNA levels of <italic>puf3</italic>&#x00394; with wild-type cells grown in minimal media with glycerol. The left frequency axis refers to all genes (black line); the axis to the right refers to Puf3p and Puf4p (control) targets, shown as red and blue lines, respectively. Relative expression levels of the 220 Puf3p mRNA targets in <italic>puf3</italic>&#x00394; cells were selectively increased compared to all other mRNAs analyzed (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 10<sup>&#x02212;34</sup>), whereas Puf4p targets were not (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05). Thirty-nine genes involved in aerobic respiration (according to GO annotation and SGD), but not bound by Puf3p, were similarly enriched (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>) in the <italic>puf3</italic> mutant as random sets of 39 Puf3p targets (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup>). Likewise, 220 randomly selected mRNAs coding for mitochondrial proteins that were not associated with Puf3p in the experiments herein were weakly enriched in the mutant (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 10<sup>&#x02212;8</sup>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020079.g007"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>In an analysis of just five of the hundreds of RBPs encoded by the <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. cerevisiae</named-content> genome, we found that more than 700 transcripts appeared to be specifically bound by one or more RBPs, with each of the five Puf family proteins &#x0201c;tagging&#x0201d; a distinct set of mRNAs. These sets encode functionally and cytotopically related proteins. For three of the Puf proteins, we identified distinct short sequences in the associated specific set of mRNAs, typically in the 3&#x02032;-UTR, which were sufficient for specific binding to the cognate Puf protein in vivo. Many sets of mRNAs encoding proteins localized to the same subcellular compartment, protein complex, or functional system were bound by the same Puf protein. Puf3p, which specifically associated with cytoplasmic mRNAs encoding mitochondrial proteins, generally affected the steady-state levels of its mRNA targets as reflected by their increased abundance in <italic>puf3</italic> mutant cells.</p><p>The selective &#x0201c;tagging&#x0201d; by sequence-specific RBPs of mRNAs that share common physiological roles suggests a general and widespread mechanism for coordinated control of their expression. Previous reports have identified coordinated regulation of small sets of functionally related mRNAs by specific RBPs. For example, mammalian stem&#x02013;loop binding protein (SLBP) associates with all five classes of histone mRNAs and guides proper 3&#x02032;-end formation (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Dominski1" ref-type="bibr">Dominski and Marzluff 1999</xref>). Iron regulatory proteins (IRPs) bind to and regulate translation of five different mRNAs encoding proteins involved in iron metabolism (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Eisenstein1" ref-type="bibr">Eisenstein and Ross 2003</xref>), and a cytoplasmic poly(A) polymerase regulates multiple mRNAs in early development (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Mendez1" ref-type="bibr">Mendez and Richter 2001</xref>). Based on these and other examples (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Tenenbaum1" ref-type="bibr">Tenenbaum et al. 2000</xref>), <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Keene2" ref-type="bibr">Keene and Tenenbaum (2002</xref>) have suggested that messenger RBPs could define &#x0201c;post-transcriptional operons.&#x0201d; Our results provide strong support for this general idea of coordination of gene expression via RBPs and suggest that the post-transcriptional control afforded by combinatorial binding of RBPs to mRNAs could allow greater regulatory flexibility than a simple operon (see also <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Keene2" ref-type="bibr">Keene and Tenenbaum 2002</xref>). Further, we suggest that RBPs may play important roles in subcellular localization and efficient assembly of protein complexes.</p><p>The RBPs encoded in eukaryotic genomes rival specific transcription factors in their numbers and diversity, raising the intriguing possibility that specific regulation of the localization, translation, and survival of mRNAs might be comparable in their richness and complexity to regulation of transcription itself. Each of the five Puf proteins interacts with a distinct large set of mRNAs, comprising more than 700 different mRNAs in total. Five other RBPs in <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. cerevisiae</named-content> have been subjected to a similar genome-wide survey of their mRNA targets. She2p, which plays a critical role in selective targeting of specific mRNAs to the bud tip (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Shepard1" ref-type="bibr">Shepard et al. 2003</xref>), Khd1p, which has also been implicated in localizing gene expression to the nascent bud (A. P. Gerber, unpublished data), and Scp160p, an RBP implicated in genome stability (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Li1" ref-type="bibr">Li et al. 2003</xref>), were each found to bind from 20 to hundreds of distinct mRNAs, and two proteins implicated in RNA export from the nucleus, Yra1p and Mex67p, were each associated with more than 1,000 mRNAs (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Hieronymus1" ref-type="bibr">Hieronymus and Silver 2003</xref>). Thus, just ten of the 567 <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. cerevisiae</named-content> proteins known or predicted from the genome sequence to have RNA binding activity (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Costanzo1" ref-type="bibr">Costanzo et al. 2001</xref>) have been found to bind, in a functionally specific pattern, a total of approximately 2,500 different transcripts (approximately 40% of the transcriptome). The extent and specificity of the RNA&#x02013;protein interactions represented by the proteins studied to date, extrapolated to the hundreds of putative RBPs that remain to be investigated, suggest the existence of an extensive network of RNA&#x02013;protein interactions that coordinate the post-transcriptional fate of large sets of cytotopically and functionally related RNAs through each stage of its &#x0201c;lifecycle.&#x0201d; It further suggests a potential regulatory repertoire comparable in its diversity and richness to that of the DNA-binding transcription factors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020079-g008">Figure 8</xref>). Indeed, the combinatorial binding of mRNAs by multiple RBPs could, in principle, define a specific post-transcriptional fate for each individual mRNA (for an example, see <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Sonoda1" ref-type="bibr">Sonoda and Wharton 2001</xref>).</p><fig id="pbio-0020079-g008" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>Specific Proteins Bind Functional Groups of Genes for Regulation</title><p>At the transcriptional level (top), transcription factors (TFs) regulate initiation of transcription (green arrow) in the nucleus by binding to sequence elements (yellow box) proximal to their target coding regions (boxes). At the post-transcriptional level (middle), RBPs regulate decay, translation, or localization of mRNAs in a coordinated fashion by interaction with sequence/structural elements in the RNA that are often found in 3&#x02032;-UTR regions (red box). Functional relations at the protein level (bottom) can be reflected at both the transcriptional and post-transcriptional levels: sets of genes that encode functionally related proteins, such as subunits of stochiometric complexes (blue) or components of the same regulatory or metabolic pathway (gray and cross-hatched boxes), may be regulated by common transcription factors and their mRNAs post-transcriptionally coregulated by RBPs (dashed interactions).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020079.g008"/></fig><p>Many sets of mRNAs bound by the same Puf protein encode proteins that act in the same subcellular location, form stochiometric complexes, or are implicated in the same cellular pathway. This organization is most clearly exemplified by Puf3p, which selectively bound mRNAs encoding mitochondrial proteins, including at least 70% of all mitochondrial ribosomal proteins (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020079-g004">Figure 4</xref>). Combinations of RBPs could specify smaller sets of RNAs encoding more precisely defined functional groups of proteins. For example, the mRNAs encoding the core histone proteins were among the small set of mRNAs that were associated with both Puf4p and Puf5p. These results therefore hint that networks of functional and physical interactions among proteins could be reflected in a corresponding network of mRNA&#x02013;protein interactions that coordinate post-transcriptional control of their expression and fate.</p><p>For three of the Puf proteins, we found that RNA&#x02013;protein interactions were directed by compact sequence elements, usually located in the 3&#x02032;-UTR of the mRNA (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020079-g005">Figure 5</xref>). Interactions with 3&#x02032;-UTR sequences have been described for many cytoplasmic RBPs involved in post-transcriptional regulation (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Mazumder1" ref-type="bibr">Mazumder et al. 2003</xref>). Our analysis has revealed that such recognition elements are probably much more widespread than previously recognized. Sequence and structural elements in mRNAs that are related to the function or cellular localization of the encoded proteins may be a general feature of eukaryotic genes, paralleling the role of the DNA sequences that direct specific transcription factors to promoters and enhancers (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Cliften1" ref-type="bibr">Cliften et al. 2003</xref>).</p><p>The multifocal cytoplasmic distribution of Puf proteins raises the possibility that the mRNAs associated with each Puf protein are colocalized (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020079-g006">Figure 6</xref>). In mammalian cells, specific mRNA molecules and specific messenger RBPs have also been found to be localized to specific &#x0201c;granular&#x0201d; subcytoplasmic loci, although the generality of this phenomenon has not been established (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Andersen1" ref-type="bibr">Andersen and Kedersha 2002</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Eystathioy1" ref-type="bibr">Eystathioy et al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Farina1" ref-type="bibr">Farina et al. 2003</xref>). One function of the Puf proteins and related proteins that bind specific families of mRNAs could be to localize functionally related mRNAs to specific cytoplasmic loci. Physical clustering of functionally related groups of mRNAs could aid the assembly of complexes and the coordinated control of translation or RNA turnover. In support of this idea, it has recently been suggested that mRNA decay in the cytoplasm of <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. cerevisiae</named-content> occurs in distinct loci (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Sheth1" ref-type="bibr">Sheth and Parker 2003</xref>) and, further, that mRNAs encoding different subunits of stoichiometric complexes do indeed have concordant decay rates (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Wang2" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al. 2002b</xref>). We propose that the location in the cell at which any mRNA is translated or degraded is not left to chance. Instead, every mRNA that leaves the nucleus may be delivered, in a process directed by specific protein&#x02013;RNA interactions, to one of a limited number of specific foci in the cytoplasm, designated as destinations for a specific functionally related family of mRNAs. These foci could serve to colocalize and coregulate synthesis of proteins that need to assemble or act together, thereby facilitating efficient and rapid assembly and localization of the proteins. The number of distinct families of functionally specialized foci may be quite large. The locations of these foci need not correspond to recognizable cellular features, but may simply be ad hoc sites for localized, coordinated translation of proteins that are to be assembled into a complex or a functional unit. Specific predictions of this hypothesis, such as colocalized translation of the subunits of stoichiometric complexes, should be amenable to direct experimental tests.</p><p>Combinatorial binding of mRNAs by specific regulatory proteins, linking their post-transcriptional regulation to specific signal transduction pathways, could allow rapid and efficient reprogramming of gene expression during development or in response to changing physiological conditions. Indeed, regulation of specific genes by external signals via RPBs has been described in higher eukaryotes (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Lasko1" ref-type="bibr">Lasko 2003</xref>). For example, the signal transduction and activation of RNA (STAR) proteins contain RNA-binding motifs combined with protein&#x02013;protein interaction domains and phosphorylation sites, which could allow integration of stimuli conducted by signal transduction cascades (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Lasko1" ref-type="bibr">Lasko 2003</xref>). Similarly, the Puf proteins contain numerous putative phosphorylation motifs, as well as domains with characteristics often implicated in protein&#x02013;protein interactions, such as glutamine/arginine-rich regions (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Michelitsch1" ref-type="bibr">Michelitsch and Weissman 2000</xref>) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020079-g001">Figure 1</xref>).</p><p>Coordination of cellular processes has long been thought to be mediated primarily at the transcriptional and post-translational level. Our results join a growing body of studies (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Tenenbaum1" ref-type="bibr">Tenenbaum et al. 2000</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Eystathioy1" ref-type="bibr">Eystathioy et al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Wang2" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al. 2002b</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Hieronymus1" ref-type="bibr">Hieronymus and Silver 2003</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Shepard1" ref-type="bibr">Shepard et al. 2003</xref>; see also <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Keene2" ref-type="bibr">Keene and Tenenbaum 2002</xref>) that suggest that the localization, translation, and stability of mRNAs are subject to extensive and important regulation and coordination by interaction with a diverse set of RBPs. Systematic mapping of these interactions and deciphering their roles, molecular mechanisms, and coordination will undoubtedly yield important new insights into biological regulation and the gene expression program.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title/><sec id="s4a1"><title>Oligonucleotide primers</title><p>Restriction sites are in italics: Puf3-F1, 5&#x02032;-cg<italic>ggatcc</italic>ATGGAAATGAACATGGATATGGATATGG-3&#x02032;; Puf3-R1, 5&#x02032;-g<italic>gaattc</italic>TCACACCTCCGCATTTTCAACCAATG-3&#x02032;; Puf3-F6nco, 5&#x02032;-<italic>cCATGg</italic>CACTAAAAGACATCTTTGG-3&#x02032;; Puf4-F2nco, 5&#x02032;-<italic>ccatgG</italic>CGGACGCAGTTTTAGACCAATA-3&#x02032;; Puf4-R1eco, 5&#x02032;-<italic>gaattc</italic>gTGAATCTAAATGTAACATTCCG-3&#x02032;; Puf5-F2nco, 5&#x02032;-<italic>ccATGG</italic>TCGAAATCAGCGCACTACC-3&#x02032;; Puf5-R1xho, 5&#x02032;-<italic>ctcgag</italic>cACTTGGAAGTAATTCTTTTGTA-3&#x02032;; M16-1, 5&#x02032;-GGG<italic>CTCGAG</italic>tagggaataccttgtaaatatcctatgaaaGCATG-3&#x02032;; M16-2, 5&#x02032;-Ctttcataggatatttacaaggtattcccta<italic>CTCGAG</italic>CCC-3&#x02032;; M16-1mut, 5&#x02032;-GGG<italic>CTCGAG</italic>tagggaatacctacaaaatatcctatgaaaGCATG-3&#x02032;; M16-2mut, 5&#x02032;-Ctttcataggatattttgtaggtattcccta<italic>CTCGAG</italic>CCC-3&#x02032;; Caf-1, 5&#x02032;-GGG<italic>CTCGAG</italic>tgggcacgattgtaataatacttcatgataaGCATG-3&#x02032;; Caf-2, 5&#x02032;-Cttatcatgaagtattattacaatcgtgccca<italic>CTCGAG</italic>CCC-3&#x02032;; Yor-1, 5&#x02032;-GGG<italic>CTCGAG</italic>gctttcatcatctgtataatatttatatgtcGCATG-3&#x02032;; and Yor-2, 5&#x02032;-Cgacatataaatattatacagatgatgaaagc<italic>CTCGAG</italic>CCC-3&#x02032;.</p></sec><sec id="s4a2"><title>Strains and plasmid construction</title><p>The TAP-tagged Puf3p strain (SC1249) was obtained from Cellzome (Heidelberg, Germany) (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Gavin1" ref-type="bibr">Gavin et al. 2002</xref>). TAP-tagged Puf1p, Puf2p, Puf4p, and Puf5p strains were a gift from Dr. Erin O'Shea (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Ghaemmaghami1" ref-type="bibr">Ghaemmaghami et al. 2003</xref>). Correct genomic integration of each tag was verified by PCR and by immunoblot analysis of cell extracts (data not shown). Strain BY4741 was used for mock-control affinity isolations of RNA, and deletions of the <italic>PUF3</italic> and <italic>PUF4</italic> genes in this strain were obtained from Dr. Ron Davis (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Winzeler1" ref-type="bibr">Winzeler et al. 1999</xref>).</p><p>The ORF of <italic>PUF3</italic> was amplified by PCR with primers Puf3-F1 and Puf3-R1 from <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. cerevisiae</named-content> genomic DNA and cloned into pCR2.1 using the TOPO TA Cloning Kit (Invitrogen, San Diego, California, United States). The <italic>PUF3</italic> ORF was sequenced and subcloned into pACTII via NcoI and EcoRI restriction sites, resulting in plasmid pACTII-Puf3. A full-length Puf5p construct pGAD-<italic>MPT5</italic> was a gift from Dr. Kenji Irie (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Tadauchi1" ref-type="bibr">Tadauchi et al. 2001</xref>).</p><p>Sequences encoding the Pum-HD domains of Puf3p (amino acids 535&#x02013;879), Puf4p (amino acids 557&#x02013;888), and Puf5p (amino acids 202&#x02013;578) were PCR-amplified from genomic DNA with oligo pairs Puf3-F6nco/Puf3-R1, Puf4-F2nco/Puf4-R1eco, and Puf5-F2nco/Puf5-R1xho, respectively. Products were ligated into pCR2.1-TOPO, sequenced, and further cloned into pACTII via restriction sites present in the oligonucleotides used for amplification.</p><p>The RNA consensus sequences interacting with Puf proteins plus ten nucleotides of flanking sequences were cloned into the SmaI and SphI sites of the vector pIIIA/MS2-2 (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Bernstein1" ref-type="bibr">Bernstein et al. 2002</xref>) using annealed synthetic oligonucleotides. The <italic>PUF3</italic> RNA consensus sequence spanning nucleotides 24&#x02013;33 in the 3&#x02032;-UTR of YBL038w/<italic>MRPL16</italic> was constructed with oligonucleotides M16-1 and M16-2. In M16mut the conserved UGU motif was changed to ACA. The <italic>PUF4</italic> consensus (nucleotides 24&#x02013;34 in the 3&#x02032;-UTR of YOR145c) was constructed with oligonucleotides Yor-1 and Yor-2. The <italic>PUF5</italic> consensus (nucleotides 105&#x02013;114 in the 3&#x02032;-UTR of YNL278w/<italic>CAF120</italic>) was constructed with oligonucleotides Caf-1 and Caf-2.</p></sec><sec id="s4a3"><title>Isolating RNAs specifically associated with selected RBPs</title><p>For a detailed protocol, see the Supporting Information on our Web site. In brief, 1 l of cells were cultured in YPAD medium (yeast&#x02013;peptone&#x02013;dextrose [YPD] supplemented with 20 mg/ml adenine&#x02013;sulfate) at 30&#x000b0;C and collected during exponential growth by centrifugation. Cells were washed twice with ice-cold buffer A (20 mM Tris&#x02013;HCl [pH 8.0], 140 mM KCl, 1.8 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.1% Nonidet P-40 [NP-40], 0.02 mg/ml heparin) and resuspended in 5 ml of buffer B (buffer A plus 0.5 mM dithiothreitol [DTT], 1 mM phenylmethylsulfonylfluoride, 0.5 &#x003bc;g/ml leupeptin, 0.8 &#x003bc;g/ml pepstatin, 20 U/ml DNase I, 100 U/ml RNasin [Promega, Madison, Wisconsin, United States], and 0.2 mg/ml heparin). Cells were broken mechanically with glass beads, and extracts were incubated with 400-&#x003bc;l slurry (50% [v/v]) IgG&#x02013;agarose beads (Sigma, St. Louis, Missouri, United States) for 2 h at 4&#x000b0;C. The beads were washed four times for 15 min at 4&#x000b0;C with buffer C (20 mM Tris&#x02013;HCl [pH 8.0], 140 mM KCl, 1.8 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.5 mM DTT, 0.01% NP-40, 10 U/ml RNasin). Puf proteins were released from the beads by incubation with 80 U of TEV protease (Invitrogen) for 2 h at 15&#x000b0;C. RNA was isolated from the TEV eluates, which corresponds to the purified fraction and from extracts (input) by extraction with phenol/chloroform and isopropanol precipitation.</p></sec><sec id="s4a4"><title>Microarray analysis and data selection</title><p>Equal amounts of a pool of five synthetically prepared <named-content content-type="genus-species">Bacillus subtilis</named-content> RNAs were added to each RNA sample prior to labeling and served as a control for the labeling procedure (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Wang2" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al. 2002b</xref>). Total RNA (3 &#x003bc;g) derived from the extract and 300 ng of affinity-isolated RNA (or up to 40% of isolated RNA) were labeled with Cy3 and Cy5 fluorescent dyes, respectively, following cDNA synthesis with amino-allyl dUTP in addition to the four natural dNTPs using a 1:1 mixture of oligo(dT) and random nonamer primers. The Cy3- and Cy5-labeled cDNA samples were mixed and competitively hybridized to DNA microarrays representing all <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. cerevisiae</named-content> ORFs, introns, and the mitochondrial genome (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://brownlab.stanford.edu/protocols.html">http://brownlab.stanford.edu/protocols.html</ext-link>). Microarrays were scanned with an Axon Instruments (Foster City, California, United States) Scanner 4000. Scanning parameters were adjusted to give similar fluorescent intensities for <named-content content-type="genus-species">B. subtilis</named-content> spots in both channels. Data were collected with the GENEPIX 3.0 Program (Axon Instruments), and spots with abnormal morphology were excluded from further analysis. Arrays were computer normalized by the Stanford Microarray Database (SMD) (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Gollub1" ref-type="bibr">Gollub et al. 2003</xref>). Log<sub>2</sub> median ratios were retrieved from SMD and exported into Microsoft (Redmond, Washington, United States) Excel after filtering for regression correlation of greater than 0.6 (filters for large variations in the ratios of pixels within each spot), CH1I/CH1B of greater than 1.8 (signal over background in the channel measuring total RNA from extract), and CH2I/CH2B of greater than 1.0 (affinity-isolated RNA signal greater than background) and for data from at least two independent measurements. Average log<sub>2</sub> ratios were calculated for each gene across the four independent experiments performed for each Puf protein (microarrays and raw data can be downloaded from our supporting Web sites [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://microarray-pubs.stanford.edu/yeast_puf/">http://microarray-pubs.stanford.edu/yeast_puf/</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genome-www5.stanford.MicroArray/SMD/">http://genome-www5.stanford.MicroArray/SMD/</ext-link>]). Genes for which the enrichment ratios were at least two standard deviations above the median across all genes were selected. A total of 923 genes were selected in this way. To eliminate nonspecifically enriched RNAs from this gene list, the results from the affinity enrichments for each of the Puf proteins and the data obtained from four independent mock affinity enrichments were clustered by the Pearson correlation algorithm (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Eisen1" ref-type="bibr">Eisen et al. 1998</xref>). Transcripts of 84 genes were enriched beyond the two standard deviation threshold in all the Puf affinity isolations as well as in the mock procedure. These were presumed to represent RNAs whose enrichment was unrelated to specific interactions with Puf proteins and therefore were excluded from further analysis. Among the finally selected target mRNAs (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="st003">Tables S3&#x02013;S7</xref>), most were represented in the four independent measurements: <italic>PUF1</italic>, 98%; <italic>PUF2</italic>, 97%; <italic>PUF3</italic>, 82%; <italic>PUF4</italic>, 93%; <italic>PUF5</italic>, 97%.</p></sec><sec id="s4a5"><title>Gene expression profiling</title><p>
<italic>puf3</italic> mutant and wild-type cells were cultured in minimal media supplemented with 3% glycerol and harvested during exponential growth (OD<sub>600</sub> = 0.5). Total RNA (8 &#x003bc;g) isolated from wild-type and mutant cells were used to prepare Cy3 and Cy5 fluorescently labeled cDNA as described above, except that only an oligo(dT) primer was used. The two differentially labeled cDNAs were mixed together and hybridized to yeast DNA microarrays. Arrays were scanned and the data were collected, entered into SMD, and computer normalized (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Gollub1" ref-type="bibr">Gollub et al. 2003</xref>). Log<sub>2</sub> median ratios were retrieved from SMD after filtering for regression correlation of greater than 0.6 and signal over background of greater than 1.5. Results from three independent experiments were averaged for this analysis (raw data can be retrieved from our Web site).</p></sec><sec id="s4a6"><title>Motif searches</title><p>As the exact 5&#x02032;- and 3&#x02032;-UTR lengths are unknown for most of the Puf target mRNAs, we used the estimated average lengths from yeast (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Mignone1" ref-type="bibr">Mignone et al. 2002</xref>). Hence, the coding 237 nucleotides of predicted 3&#x02032;-UTR and 134 nucleotides of predicted 5&#x02032;-UTR sequences were retrieved from SGD for the Puf target genes. The sequences were searched for motifs in the sense strand with the program MEME under the proposed default settings (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://meme.sdsc.edu/meme/website/intro.html">http://meme.sdsc.edu/meme/website/intro.html</ext-link>) (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Bailey1" ref-type="bibr">Bailey and Elkan 1994</xref>) (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="st009">Tables S9&#x02013;S11</xref>). The number and location of consensus motifs in the <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. cerevisiae</named-content> genome was obtained by searching &#x0201c;Pattern Match&#x0201d; in the SGD (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Issel-Tarver1" ref-type="bibr">Issel-Tarver et al. 2002</xref>). Thereby, nucleotides that were at least 19% conserved among the MEME selected sequences were used to compile the Consensus Motif that was searched for.</p></sec><sec id="s4a7"><title>Three-hybrid assays</title><p>Three-hybrid assays were performed as described elsewhere (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Bernstein1" ref-type="bibr">Bernstein et al. 2002</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4a8"><title>Immunofluorescence</title><p>Immunofluorescence was performed as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.med.unc.edu/%7Ehdohlman/IF.html">http://www.med.unc.edu/%7Ehdohlman/IF.html</ext-link>. Fixed and permeabilized cells were treated with 5 &#x003bc;g/ml purified rabbit immunoglobulin (Sigma) for 1 h at room temperature. After washing, cells were incubated with Cy3 goat anti-rabbit antibodies (1:400). Images were obtained on a Zeiss (Oberkochen, Germany) Axioplan-2 microscope using an Axiocam HRC camera.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><p>Full microarray results and other supporting information can be viewed at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://microarray-pubs.stanford.edu/yeast_puf/">http://microarray-pubs.stanford.edu/yeast_puf/</ext-link> and at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genome-www5.stanford.MicroArray/SMD/">http://genome-www5.stanford.MicroArray/SMD/</ext-link>.</p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sg001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><title>Distribution of Average Cy5/Cy3 Fluorescence Ratios from Quadruplicate Microarray Hybridizations Analyzing mRNA Targets for Puf1p, Puf2p, Puf4p, and Puf5p</title><p>See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020079-g003">Figure 3</xref>A for Puf3p.</p><p>(167 KB EPS).</p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0020079.sg001.eps"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sg002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><title>Examples of Groups of mRNAs Associated with the Same Puf Protein and Encoding Related Proteins</title><p>(A) Puf2p-bound mRNAs encode diverse proteins involved in regulation of ATP-dependent proton transport. <italic>PMA1</italic> and <italic>PMA2</italic> encode plasma membrane proteins that comprise the major ATP-dependent proton transporters and regulate cellular pH levels. Pmp1p, Pmp2p, and Pmp3p are small isoproteolipids, which are present in a physical complex with Pma1p and act as regulators of its activity upon stress conditions (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Navarre1" ref-type="bibr">Navarre et al. 1994</xref>). Hrk1p is a protein histidine kinase, which activates Pma1p in response to glucose (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Goossens1" ref-type="bibr">Goossens et al. 2000</xref>). Ast1p is implicated in proper delivery of Pma1p to plasma membranes (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Bagnat1" ref-type="bibr">Bagnat et al. 2001</xref>).</p><p>(B) Puf4p-bound mRNAs encode the nucleolar GAR proteins (blue), members of the H/ACA core complex (boxed), and Hmt1p, a dimethylase acting on GAR proteins. Nop1p performs 2&#x02032;-<italic>O</italic>-ribose methylation of pre-rRNA, a process guided by small nucleolar RNAs (snoRNAs) of the box C/D family. Cbf5p catalyzes pseudouridine formation with box H/ACA snoRNAs, and three of the four components of the H/ACA core complex were Puf4p-associated (Cbf5, Gar1, and Nhp2 [<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Henras1" ref-type="bibr">Henras et al. 1998</xref>]; no data were obtained for the fourth component, Nop10, shown in gray). All transcripts encoding nucleolar proteins of the GAR repeats family (Gar1p, Sbp1p, Nop1p, Nsr1p) were Puf4p-bound. The GAR domain is dimethylated at arginine residues. Remarkably, several mRNAs coding for S-adenosylmethionine-dependent methyltransferases were Puf4p-bound including Hmt1p, the major protein arginine-methyltransferase in yeast (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Gary1" ref-type="bibr">Gary et al. 1996</xref>). Hmt1p has recently been shown to dimethylate arginines of the proteins Gar1p, Nop1p, and Nsr1p (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Xu1" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al. 2003</xref>).</p><p>(38 KB EPS).</p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0020079.sg002.eps"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sg003"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><title>Phenotypic Analysis of <italic>puf3</italic>&#x00394; Cells</title><p>Serial dilutions (1:10) of cells were spotted on plates supplemented with the indicated media. Plates were incubated for 3 d at 30&#x000b0;C. Abbreviations: YPD, yeast&#x02013;peptone&#x02013;dextrose; YPGE, yeast&#x02013;peptone&#x02013;3% glycerol&#x02013;2% ethanol; SC, synthetic complete.</p><p>(264 KB PDF).</p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0020079.sg003.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="st001"><label>Table S1</label><caption><title>Number of mRNA Targets Shared between Puf Proteins</title><p>(15 KB XLS).</p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0020079.st001.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="st002"><label>Table S2</label><caption><title>Protein Copy Number Determination of Puf Proteins</title><p>Cells were grown to mid-log phase in YPAD medium and the number of cells was counted. Whole-cell extracts were prepared as described previously (Hoffman et al. 2002). In brief, cells were resuspended in 1&#x000d7; SDS-PAGE sample buffer, incubated at 100&#x000b0;C for 10 min, and vortexed for 2 min with glass beads. After a short centrifugation, eight dilutions of cell extracts and protein A (Amersham, Little Chalfont, United Kingdom), which served as a reference standard, were spotted on a nitrocellulose filter. Expression of IgG-binding domains was monitored with rabbit peroxidase&#x02013;anti-peroxidase soluble complex at 1:5,000 (Sigma). Chemiluminescence was measured with a Typhoon 8600 Imager (Molecular Dynamics, Sunnyvale, California, United States) and quantified with the ImageQuant 5.2 software. Averaged numbers from two independent measurements were used for calculations. The total number of mRNA copies in the pool associated with each Puf protein was estimated as follows: copy numbers for individual mRNAs were retrieved from two independent genome-wide measurements (<xref rid="pbio-0020079-Holstege1" ref-type="bibr">Holstege et al. 1998</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020079-Wang2" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al. 2002b</xref>). For genes with no data, we added the median value for copy numbers of all mRNAs in the respective pool.</p><p>(30 KB XLS).</p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0020079.st002.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="st003"><label>Table S3</label><caption><title>List of Puf1p Target mRNAs</title><p>Columns indicate the following (from left to right): ORF; gene name; GO annotations; classification of gene products (soluble/membrane-associated); average log<sub>2</sub> ratios of enrichment across four independent Puf affinity isolations; standard deviations; association of mRNA with other Puf proteins; mRNA copy numbers.</p><p>(28 KB XLS).</p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0020079.st003.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="st004"><label>Table S4</label><caption><title>List of Puf2p Target mRNAs</title><p>Notations are as in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="st003">Table S3</xref>.</p><p>(52 KB XLS).</p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0020079.st004.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="st005"><label>Table S5</label><caption><title>List of Puf3p Target RNAs</title><p>Columns indicate the following (from left to right): ORF; gene name; GO annotations; classification of gene products (soluble/membrane-associated); average log<sub>2</sub> ratios of enrichment across four independent Puf affinity isolations; standard deviations; association of mRNA with other Puf proteins; location of consensus motif identified by MEME; mRNA copy numbers.</p><p>(70 KB XLS).</p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0020079.st005.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="st006"><label>Table S6</label><caption><title>List of Puf4p Target mRNAs</title><p>Notations are as in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="st005">Table S5</xref>.</p><p>(61 KB XLS).</p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0020079.st006.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="st007"><label>Table S7</label><caption><title>List of Puf5p Target mRNAs</title><p>Notations are as in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="st005">Table S5</xref>.</p><p>(64 KB XLS).</p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0020079.st007.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="st008"><label>Table S8</label><caption><title>Significant Shared GO Annotations among Puf mRNA Targets</title><p>Only annotations with <italic>p</italic> values of less than 0.001 are indicated. GO annotations were retrieved from the SGD with GO Finder (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://db.yeastgenome.org/cgi-bin/SGD/GO/goTermFinder">http://db.yeastgenome.org/cgi-bin/SGD/GO/goTermFinder</ext-link>) on May 21, 2003. Respective <italic>p</italic> values are indicated in a column next to the names of the GO term.</p><p>(30 KB XLS).</p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0020079.st008.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="st009"><label>Table S9</label><caption><title>Results of MEME Motif Searches: Motifs among Puf3p mRNA Targets</title><p>(63 KB XLS).</p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0020079.st009.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="st010"><label>Table S10</label><caption><title>Results of MEME Motif Searches: Motifs among Puf4p mRNA Targets</title><p>(55 KB XLS).</p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0020079.st010.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="st011"><label>Table S11</label><caption><title>Results of MEME Motif Searches: Motifs among Puf5p mRNA Targets</title><p>(34 KB XLS).</p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0020079.st011.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><sec id="s5a"><title>Accession Numbers</title><p>All accession numbers for human, <italic>Drosophila</italic>, or <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. elegans</named-content> proteins are from the SwissProt database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/swissprot/">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/swissprot/</ext-link>): CPEB (Q18317), GLD1 (Q17339), DAZL (Q92904), FBF-1 (Q9N5M6), FEM3 (P34691), IRP (P21399), NANOS (P25724), <italic>Drosophila</italic> PUMILIO (P25822), human PUMILIO-1 (Q14671), human PUMILIO-2 (Q9HAN2), and SLBP (P97330).</p><p>The accession numbers for <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. cerevisiae</named-content> genes are from SGD (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genome-www.stanford.edu/Saccharomyces/">http://genome-www.stanford.edu/Saccharomyces/</ext-link>) (ORF/SGD identification number): <italic>ADA2</italic> (YDR448W/S0002856), <italic>AME1</italic> (YBR211C/S0000415), <italic>APS3</italic> YJL024C/S0003561), <italic>AST1</italic> (YBL069W/S0000165), <italic>BBP1</italic> (YPL255W/S0006176), <italic>BDF1</italic> (YLR399C/S0004391), <italic>BDF2</italic> (YDL070W/S0002228), <italic>BOI2</italic> (YER114C/S0000916), <italic>BSP1</italic> (YPR171W/S0006375), <italic>BUB1</italic> (YGR188C/S0003420), <italic>BUD9</italic> (YGR041W/S0003273), <italic>CBF5</italic> (YLR175W/S0004165), <italic>CDC31</italic> (YOR257W/S0005783), <italic>CNM67</italic> (YNL225C/S0005169), <italic>COX17</italic> (YLL009C/S0003932), <italic>DAD2</italic> (YKR083C/S0001791), <italic>DHH1</italic> (YDL160C/S0002319), <italic>ELM1</italic> (YKL048C/S0001531), <italic>FPS1</italic> (YLL043W/S0003966), <italic>GAR1</italic> (YHR089C/S0001131), <italic>GIC1</italic> (YHR061C/S0001103), <italic>HDA1</italic> (YNL021W/S0004966), <italic>HFI1</italic> (YPL254W/S0006175), <italic>HMT1</italic> (YBR034C/S0000238), <italic>HOS1</italic> (YPR068C/S0006272), <italic>HOS3</italic> (YPL116W/S0006037), <italic>HST1</italic> (YOL068C/S0005429), <italic>HTA1</italic> (YDR225W/S0002633), <italic>IFM1</italic> (YOL023W/S0005383), <italic>KAR1</italic> (YNL188W/S0005132), <italic>KAR9</italic> (YPL269W/S0006190), <italic>KHD1</italic> (YBL032W/S0000128), <italic>MAS6</italic> (YNR017W/S0005300), <italic>MEX67</italic> (YPL169C/S0006090), <italic>MUP3</italic> (YHL036W/S0001028), <italic>NCE101</italic> (YJL205C/S0003742), <italic>NCE102</italic> (YPR149W/S0006353), <italic>NHP2</italic> (YDL208W/S0002367), <italic>NOP1</italic> (YDL014W/S0002172), <italic>NSR1</italic> (YGR159C/S0003391), <italic>NUF2</italic> (YOL069W/S0005430), <italic>PDR16</italic> (YNL231C/S0005175), <italic>PMA1</italic> (YGL008C/S0002976), <italic>PUF1</italic> (YJR091C/S0003851), <italic>PUF2</italic> (YPR042C/S0006246), <italic>PUF3</italic> (YLL013C/S0003936), <italic>PUF4</italic> (YGL014W/S0002982), <italic>PUF5</italic> (YGL178W/S0003146), <italic>RAX2</italic> (YLR084C/S0004074), <italic>RSC1</italic> (YGR056W/S0003288), <italic>RSC2</italic> (YLR357W/S0004349), <italic>RSC4</italic> (YKR008W/S0001716), <italic>SBP1</italic> (YHL034C/S0001026), <italic>SCP160</italic> (YJL080C/S0003616), <italic>SFK1</italic> (YKL051W/S0001534), <italic>SFL1</italic> (YOR140W/S0005666), <italic>SHE2</italic> (YKL130C/S0001613), <italic>SIN3</italic> (YOL004W/S0005364), <italic>SNC2</italic> (YOR327C/S0005854), <italic>SNT1</italic> (YCR033W/S0000629), <italic>SPC19</italic> (YDR201W/S0002609), <italic>SPC42</italic> (YKL042W/S0001525), <italic>SPT7</italic> (YBR081C/S0000285), <italic>SPT8</italic> (YLR055C/S0004045), <italic>SSO2</italic> (YMR183C/S0004795), <italic>STE7</italic> (YDL159W/S0002318), <italic>SUR7</italic> (YML052W/S0004516), <italic>TPO1</italic> (YLL028W/S0003951), <italic>TPO2</italic> (YGR138C/S0003370), <italic>TPO3</italic> (YPR156C/S0006360), <italic>VPS72</italic> (YDR485C/S0002893), <italic>YIP1</italic> (YGR172C/S0003404), <italic>YKL091c</italic> (YKL091C/S0001574), <italic>YPR157w</italic> (YPR157W/S0006361), and <italic>YRA1</italic> (YDR381W/S0002789).</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We are grateful to Dr. Erin O'Shea for generously providing TAP-tagged Puf strains in advance of publication, Dr. Marvin Wickens for the yeast three-hybrid assay reagents, and Dr. Kenji Irie for plasmids. We thank Drs. Stefan Luschnig, Yoav Arava, Kevin Travers, and Dan Hogan for critical reading of the manuscript. APG was supported by a long-term fellowship from the Human Frontier Science Organization. This work was supported by the Howard Hughes Medical Institute, by a grant from the National Cancer Institute to POB, and by a grant from the National Institutes of Health (GM49243) to DH. POB is an investigator of the Howard Hughes Medical Institute.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="n1" fn-type="COI-statement"><p>
<bold>Conflicts of interest.</bold> The authors have declared that no conflicts of interest exist.</p></fn><fn id="n2" fn-type="con"><p>
<bold>Author contributions.</bold> APG, DH, and POB conceived and designed the experiments. APG performed the experiments. APG, DH, and POB analyzed the data. APG, DH, and POB contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools. APG, DH, and POB wrote the paper.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="n3" fn-type="edited-by"><p>Academic Editor: Sean Eddy, Washington University</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pbio-0020079-Albertsen1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albertsen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellahn</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Waffenschmidt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Localization and function of the yeast multidrug transporter Tpo1p</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>12820</fpage><lpage>12825</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12562762</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Andersen1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kedersha</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stressful initiations</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>2002</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>3227</fpage><lpage>3234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12140254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Bagnat1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bagnat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plasma membrane proton ATPase Pma1p requires raft association for surface delivery in yeast</article-title><source>Mol Biol Cell</source><year>2001</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>4129</fpage><lpage>4138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11739806</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Bailey1"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Elkan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fitting a mixture model by expectation maximization to discover motifs in biopolymers. Proceedings of the Second International Conference on Intelligent Systems for Molecular Biology; August</article-title><year>1994</year><publisher-loc>Stanford, California; Menlo Park, California</publisher-loc><publisher-name>AAAI Press</publisher-name><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>36</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Bernstein1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Buter</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Stumpf</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wickens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analyzing mRNA&#x02013;protein complexes using a yeast three-hybrid system</article-title><source>Methods</source><year>2002</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12054889</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Brown1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ceman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Darnell</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Donnell</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Microarray identification of FMRP-associated brain mRNAs and altered mRNA translational profiles in fragile X syndrome</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2001</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>487</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11719188</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Cleves1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cleves</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Barondes</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new pathway for protein export in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</named-content>
</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>1017</fpage><lpage>1026</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8655575</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Cliften1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cliften</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sudarsanam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Desikan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Finding functional features in <italic>Saccharomyces</italic> genomes by phylogenetic footprinting</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2003</year><volume>301</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12775844</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Costanzo1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costanzo</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirschman</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kranz</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>YPD, PombePD and WormPD: Model organism volumes of the BioKnowledge library, an integrated resource for protein information</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11125054</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Crittenden1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crittenden</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachorik</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallegos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A conserved RNA-binding protein controls germline stem cells in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Caenorhabditis elegans</named-content>
</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2002</year><volume>417</volume><fpage>660</fpage><lpage>663</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12050669</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Dominski1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dominski</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Marzluff</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Formation of the 3&#x02032; end of histone mRNA</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>1999</year><volume>239</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10571029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Dreyfuss1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dreyfuss</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kataoka</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Messenger-RNA-binding proteins and the messages they carry</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11994740</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Eisen1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Spellman</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name><surname>Botstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cluster analysis and display of genome-wide expression patterns</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1998</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>14863</fpage><lpage>14868</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9843981</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Eisenstein1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eisenstein</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel roles for iron regulatory proteins in the adaptive response to iron deficiency</article-title><source>J Nutr</source><year>2003</year><volume>133</volume><issue>5 Suppl 1</issue><fpage>1510S</fpage><lpage>1516S</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12730455</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Eystathioy1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eystathioy</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tenenbaum</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Keene</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A phosphorylated cytoplasmic autoantigen, GW182, associates with a unique population of human mRNAs within novel cytoplasmic speckles</article-title><source>Mol Biol Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1338</fpage><lpage>1351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11950943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Farina1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farina</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Huttelmaier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Musunuru</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Darnell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two ZBP1 KH domains facilitate beta-actin mRNA localization, granule formation, and cytoskeletal attachment</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>160</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12507992</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Fatica1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fatica</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tollervey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Making ribosomes</article-title><source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12067653</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Futcher1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Futcher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Latter</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name><name><surname>Monardo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrels</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A sampling of the yeast proteome</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1999</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>7357</fpage><lpage>7368</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10523624</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Gan1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitakawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshino</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Oshiro</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yonezawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tag-mediated isolation of yeast mitochondrial ribosome and mass spectrometric identification of its new components</article-title><source>Eur J Biochem</source><year>2002</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>5203</fpage><lpage>5214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12392552</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Gary1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gary</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Herschman</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The predominant protein&#x02013;arginine methyltransferase from <named-content content-type="genus-species">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</named-content>
</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1996</year><volume>271</volume><fpage>12585</fpage><lpage>12594</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8647869</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Gavin1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gavin</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosche</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Grandi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Marzioch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Functional organization of the yeast proteome by systematic analysis of protein complexes</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2002</year><volume>415</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11805826</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Gerbi1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerbi</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Borovjagin</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The nucleolus: A site of ribonucleoprotein maturation</article-title><source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>318</fpage><lpage>325</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12787774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Ghaemmaghami1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghaemmaghami</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Huh</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bower</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Howson</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Belle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global analysis of protein expression in yeast</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2003</year><volume>424</volume><fpage>727</fpage><lpage>741</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Gollub1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gollub</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Binkley</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Demeter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Finkelstein</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Stanford Microarray Database: Data access and quality assessment tools</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12519956</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Goossens1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goossens</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>de La Fuente</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Forment</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Serrano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Portillo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of yeast H(+)-ATPase by protein kinases belonging to a family dedicated to activation of plasma membrane transporters</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2000</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>7654</fpage><lpage>7661</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11003661</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Hastie1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hastie</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The expression of three abundance classes of messenger RNA in mouse tissues</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1976</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>761</fpage><lpage>774</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1017013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Henras1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henras</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bousquet-Antonelli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Noaillac-Depeyre</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelugne</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nhp2p and Nop10p are essential for the function of H/ACA snoRNPs</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1998</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>7078</fpage><lpage>7090</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9843512</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Hereford1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hereford</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosbash</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Number and distribution of polyadenylated RNA sequences in yeast</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1977</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>453</fpage><lpage>462</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">321129</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Hieronymus1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hieronymus</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide analysis of RNA&#x02013;protein interactions illustrates specificity of the mRNA export machinery</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2003</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>156</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Hoffman1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrison</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dohlman</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of RGS proteins in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</named-content>
</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol</source><year>2002</year><volume>344</volume><fpage>617</fpage><lpage>631</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11771415</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Holstege1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holstege</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyrick</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>TI</given-names></name><name><surname>Hengartner</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dissecting the regulatory circuitry of a eukaryotic genome</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1998</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>717</fpage><lpage>728</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9845373</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Huh1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huh</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name><surname>Falvo</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerke</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Howson</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global analysis of protein localization in budding yeast</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2003</year><volume>425</volume><fpage>671</fpage><lpage>672</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14562083</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Issel-Tarver1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Issel-Tarver</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Christie</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolinski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrada</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Balakrishnan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>
<italic>Saccharomyces</italic> Genome Database</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol</source><year>2002</year><volume>350</volume><fpage>329</fpage><lpage>346</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12073322</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Jacobs1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacobs Anderson</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computational identification of <italic>cis</italic>-acting elements affecting post-transcriptional control of gene expression in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</named-content>
</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1604</fpage><lpage>1617</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10710427</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Keene1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keene</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Organizing mRNA export</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2003</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12560814</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Keene2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keene</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tenenbaum</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Eukaryotic mRNPs may represent posttranscriptional operons</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1161</fpage><lpage>1167</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12086614</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Kennedy1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gotta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>McNabb</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Redistribution of silencing proteins from telomeres to the nucleolus is associated with extension of life span in S. cerevisiae</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1997</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>391</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9150138</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Kurdistani1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurdistani</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Grunstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Histone acetylation and deacetylation in yeast</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>276</fpage><lpage>284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12671650</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Lasko1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lasko</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene regulation at the RNA layer: RNA binding proteins in intercellular signaling networks</article-title><source>Sci STKE</source><year>2003</year><volume>179</volume><fpage>RE6</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Lehmann1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>N&#x000fc;sslein-Volhard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The maternal gene <italic>nanos</italic> has a central role in posterior pattern formation of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> embryo</article-title><source>Development</source><year>1991</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>679</fpage><lpage>691</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1935684</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Li1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fridovich-Keil</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scp160p associates with specific mRNAs in yeast</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1830</fpage><lpage>1837</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12654998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Lieb1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lieb</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Botstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Promoter-specific binding of Rap1 revealed by genome-wide maps of protein&#x02013;DNA association</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2001</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>327</fpage><lpage>334</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11455386</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Machin1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Machin</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microtubule stability in budding yeast: Characterization and dosage suppression of a benomyl-dependent tubulin mutant</article-title><source>Mol Biol Cell</source><year>1995</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1241</fpage><lpage>1259</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8534919</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Maniatis1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maniatis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An extensive network of coupling among gene expression machines</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2002</year><volume>416</volume><fpage>499</fpage><lpage>506</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11932736</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Mazumder1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazumder</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Seshadri</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Translational control by the 3&#x02032;-UTR: The ends specify the means</article-title><source>Trends Biochem Sci</source><year>2003</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12575997</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Mendez1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mendez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Translational control by CPEB: A means to the end</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>529</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11433366</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Michelitsch1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michelitsch</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A census of glutamine/asparagine-rich regions: Implications for their conserved function and the prediction of novel prions</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>11910</fpage><lpage>11915</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11050225</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Mignone1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mignone</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gissi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Liuni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pesole</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Untranslated regions of mRNAs</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>REVIEWS0004</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11897027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Moore1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaruzelska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Urano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Firpo</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Human Pumilio-2 is expressed in embryonic stem cells and germ cells and interacts with DAZ (Deleted in AZoospermia) and DAZ-like proteins</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>538</fpage><lpage>543</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12511597</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Navarre1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Navarre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Catty</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Leterme</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Goffeau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two distinct genes encode small isoproteolipids affecting plasma membrane H(+)-ATPase activity of <named-content content-type="genus-species">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</named-content>
</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1994</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>21262</fpage><lpage>21268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8063750</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Olivas1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olivas</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Puf3 protein is a transcript-specific regulator of mRNA degradation in yeast</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2000</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>6602</fpage><lpage>6611</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11101532</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Orphanides1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orphanides</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A unified theory of gene expression</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>451</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11909516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Rigaut1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rigaut</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Shevchenko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A generic protein purification method for protein complex characterization and proteome exploration</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>1999</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1030</fpage><lpage>1032</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10504710</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Shepard1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shepard</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Jambhekar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Takizawa</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Widespread cytoplasmic mRNA transport in yeast: Identification of 22 bud-localized transcripts using DNA microarray analysis</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>11429</fpage><lpage>11434</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13679573</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Sheth1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheth</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decapping and decay of messenger RNA occur in cytoplasmic processing bodies</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2003</year><volume>300</volume><fpage>805</fpage><lpage>808</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12730603</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Sonoda1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sonoda</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wharton</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>
<italic>Drosophila</italic> brain tumor is a translational repressor</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2001</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>762</fpage><lpage>773</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11274060</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Tadauchi1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tadauchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Herskowitz</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Irie</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Post-transcriptional regulation through the HO 3&#x02032;-UTR by Mpt5, a yeast homolog of Pumilio and FBF</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2001</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>552</fpage><lpage>561</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11157761</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Takizawa1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takizawa</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>DeRisi</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilhelm</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Vale</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plasma membrane compartmentalization in yeast by messenger RNA transport and a septin diffusion barrier</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2000</year><volume>290</volume><fpage>341</fpage><lpage>344</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11030653</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Tenenbaum1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tenenbaum</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Carson</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lager</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Keene</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identifying mRNA subsets in messenger ribonucleoprotein complexes by using cDNA arrays</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>14085</fpage><lpage>14090</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11121017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Waggoner1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waggoner</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Liebhaber</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of mRNAs associated with &#x003b1;CP2-containing RNP complexes</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>7055</fpage><lpage>7067</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12972621</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Wang1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>McLachlan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamore</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modular recognition of RNA by a human pumilio-homology domain</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2002a</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>501</fpage><lpage>512</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12202039</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Wang2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Storey</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tibshirani</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Herschlag</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Precision and functional specificity in mRNA decay</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2002b</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>5860</fpage><lpage>5865</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11972065</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Waskiewicz-Staniorowska1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waskiewicz-Staniorowska</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Skala</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jasinski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grenson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goffeau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Functional analysis of three adjacent open reading frames from the right arm of yeast chromosome XVI</article-title><source>Yeast</source><year>1998</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1027</fpage><lpage>1039</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9730282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Wickens1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wickens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimble</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A PUF family portrait: 3&#x02032; UTR regulation as a way of life</article-title><source>Trends Genet</source><year>2002</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>150</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11858839</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Wigge1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wigge</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>ON</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Soues</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analysis of the <italic>Saccharomyces</italic> spindle pole by matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization (MALDI) mass spectrometry</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1998</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>967</fpage><lpage>977</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9585415</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Winzeler1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winzeler</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoemaker</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Astromoff</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional characterization of the <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. cerevisiae</named-content> genome by gene deletion and parallel analysis</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1999</year><volume>285</volume><fpage>901</fpage><lpage>906</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10436161</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Xu1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Setya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>
<named-content content-type="genus-species">In vivo</named-content> analysis of nucleolar proteins modified by the yeast arginine methyltransferase Hmt1/Rmt1p</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2003</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>746</fpage><lpage>759</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12756332</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Zamore1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zamore</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Pumilio protein binds RNA through a conserved domain that defines a new class of RNA-binding proteins</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>1997</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1421</fpage><lpage>1433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9404893</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020079-Zhang1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallegos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Puoti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Durkin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A conserved RNA-binding protein that regulates sexual fates in the <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. elegans</named-content> hermaphrodite germ line</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1997</year><volume>390</volume><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>484</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9393998</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>DAZ</term><def><p>deleted in azoospermia</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DTT</term><def><p>dithiothreitol</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FBF</term><def><p>Fem-3-binding factor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GAR</term><def><p>glycine/arginine-rich</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GO</term><def><p>Gene Ontology</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HDAC</term><def><p>histone deacetylase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ORF</term><def><p>open reading frame</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IRP</term><def><p>iron regulatory protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MEME</term><def><p>multiple expectation maximization for motif elicitation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NP-40</term><def><p>Nonidet P-40</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Puf</term><def><p>Pumilio-FBF</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Pum-HD</term><def><p>Pumilio homology domain</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RBP</term><def><p>RNA-binding protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>rRNA</term><def><p>ribosomal RNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SAGA</term><def><p>Spt&#x02013;Ada&#x02013;Gcn5&#x02013;acetyltransferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SGD</term><def><p>
<italic>Saccharomyces</italic> Genome Database</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SLBP</term><def><p>stem&#x02013;loop binding protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SMD</term><def><p>Stanford Microarray Database</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>snoRNA</term><def><p>small nucleolar RNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>STAR</term><def><p>signal transduction and activation of RNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TAP</term><def><p>tandem-affinity purification</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TEV</term><def><p>tobacco etch virus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UTR</term><def><p>untranslated region</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>YPD</term><def><p>Yeast Proteome Database</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>YPD</term><def><p>yeast&#x02013;peptone&#x02013;dextrose</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>YPGE</term><def><p>yeast&#x02013;peptone&#x02013;3% glycerol&#x02013;2% ethanol</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></back></article>