<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">pbio</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosbiol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1544-9173</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1545-7885</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15024413</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">368157</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0020050</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Biophysics</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="System Taxonomy"><subject>Mus (Mouse)</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A Spontaneous, Recurrent Mutation in Divalent Metal Transporter-1 Exposes a Calcium Entry Pathway</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">G185R DMT1 Is an Ion Channel</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Haoxing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Jie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>DeFelice</surname><given-names>Louis J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>Nancy C</given-names></name><email>nandrews@enders.tch.harvard.edu</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Clapham</surname><given-names>David E</given-names></name><email>dclapham@enders.tch.harvard.edu</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><bold>1</bold><institution>Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Children's Hospital</institution><addr-line>Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts</addr-line><country>United States of America</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><bold>2</bold><institution>Department of Pharmacology, Vanderbilt University Medical Center</institution><addr-line>Nashville, Tennessee</addr-line><country>United States of America</country></aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>3</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>3</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>16</day><month>3</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>2</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e50</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>4</day><month>11</month><year>2003</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2003</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9;2004 Xu et al. </copyright-statement><copyright-year>2004</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="d35e156" related-article-type="companion" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pbio.0020070" xlink:title="synopsis" vol="2" page="e70">
<article-title>A Single Mutation Transforms an Iron Transporter into an Ion Channel</article-title>
</related-article><abstract><p>Divalent metal transporter-1 (DMT1/DCT1/Nramp2) is the major Fe<sup>2+</sup> transporter mediating cellular iron uptake in mammals. Phenotypic analyses of animals with spontaneous mutations in <italic>DMT1</italic> indicate that it functions at two distinct sites, transporting dietary iron across the apical membrane of intestinal absorptive cells, and transporting endosomal iron released from transferrin into the cytoplasm of erythroid precursors. DMT1 also acts as a proton-dependent transporter for other heavy metal ions including Mn<sup>2+</sup>, Co<sup>2+</sup>, and Cu<sup>2</sup>, but not for Mg<sup>2+</sup> or Ca<sup>2+</sup>. A unique mutation in <italic>DMT1,</italic> G185R, has occurred spontaneously on two occasions in microcytic <italic>(mk)</italic> mice and once in Belgrade <italic>(b)</italic> rats. This mutation severely impairs the iron transport capability of DMT1, leading to systemic iron deficiency and anemia. The repeated occurrence of the G185R mutation cannot readily be explained by hypermutability of the gene. Here we show that G185R mutant DMT1 exhibits a new, constitutive Ca<sup>2+</sup> permeability, suggesting a gain of function that contributes to remutation and the <italic>mk</italic> and <italic>b</italic> phenotypes.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="toc"><p>David Clapham and colleagues offer new evidence that blurs the line between ion transporters and channels</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Spontaneous mutations in mice and rats have provided important information about mammalian iron homeostasis (reviewed in <xref rid="pbio-0020050-Andrews1" ref-type="bibr">Andrews 2000</xref>). Interestingly, three independent, autosomal recessive mutants have been shown to have the same amino acid substitution in a key iron transport molecule. Two strains of mutant microcytic <italic>(mk)</italic> mice (MK/ReJ-<italic>mk</italic>, SEC/1ReJ-<italic>mk</italic>) and Belgrade (<italic>b</italic>) rats have severe iron deficiency attributable to a G185R mutation in divalent metal transporter-1 (DMT1) (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Fleming1" ref-type="bibr">Fleming et al. 1997</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020050-Andrews1" ref-type="bibr">Andrews 2000</xref>). Based on the phenotypes of these animals and the properties of DMT1 detailed below, we and others concluded that DMT1 is essential for intestinal absorption of Fe<sup>2+</sup> and for unloading of transferrin-derived iron from transferrin cycle endosomes (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Fleming1" ref-type="bibr">Fleming et al. 1997</xref>, <xref rid="pbio-0020050-Fleming2" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020050-Gunshin1" ref-type="bibr">Gunshin et al. 1997</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020050-Picard1" ref-type="bibr">Picard et al. 2000</xref>). It is intriguing that no other <italic>DMT1</italic> mutations have been described in mammals, and no features of the DNA sequence suggest that the G185 codon would be hypermutable in two species. We speculated that a novel characteristic of the G185R DMT1 protein might account for this remarkable pattern of remutation.</p><p>Trace metal ions including Fe<sup>2+</sup>, Mn<sup>2+</sup>, Cu<sup>2+</sup>, Zn<sup>2+</sup>, and Co<sup>2+</sup> are required cofactors for many essential cellular enzymes. They cannot cross the plasma membrane through simple diffusion, and active uptake requires specific transporters. DMT1 is the only molecule known to mediate cellular iron uptake in higher eukaryotes. It is structurally unrelated to known Zn<sup>2+</sup> and Cu<sup>2+</sup> transporters, but DMT1 can transport those and other divalent metal ions (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Gunshin1" ref-type="bibr">Gunshin et al. 1997</xref>), and it appears to be the major mammalian Mn<sup>2+</sup> transporter (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Chua1" ref-type="bibr">Chua and Morgan 1997</xref>). DMT1 is predicted to have 12 transmembrane (TM) segments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g001">Figure 1</xref>A). It is expressed on the apical brush border of the proximal duodenum (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Canonne-Hergaux1" ref-type="bibr">Canonne-Hergaux et al. 1999</xref>) and in transferrin cycle endosomes (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Su1" ref-type="bibr">Su et al. 1998</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020050-Gruenheid1" ref-type="bibr">Gruenheid et al. 1999</xref>). It appears to function by coupling a metal entry pathway to a downhill proton gradient, taking advantage of the acidic pH in both of those sites. An earlier study proposed a 1:1 stoichiometry of metal ion and proton cotransport (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Gunshin1" ref-type="bibr">Gunshin et al. 1997</xref>).</p><fig id="pbio-0020050-g001" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Wild-Type DMT1-Expressing Cells Exhibit a Proton Current and a Proton-Dependent Mn<sup>2+</sup>-Induced Current</title><p>(A) The G185R mutation is in the fourth of 12 putative TM domains in both mouse (shown) and rat DMT1 proteins.</p><p>(B) <sup>55</sup>Fe<sup>2+</sup> uptake was greatly reduced for G185R in comparison to wild-type DMT1, although the protein expression levels were comparable (inset).</p><p>(C&#x02013;E) Representative currents induced by protons (pH 4.2) and Mn<sup>2+</sup> (100 &#x003bc;M) at +50 mV (open triangles; some of the datapoints have been removed for clarity) and &#x02212;130 mV (open circles) in a wild-type DMT1-transfected CHO-K1 cell. Whole-cell currents were elicited by repeated voltage ramps (&#x02212;140 to +60 mV, 1,000 ms), shown in (E), with a 4 s interval between ramps. Holding potential (HP) was +20 mV. Neither control solution (10mM Ca<sup>2+</sup>/140 mM Na<sup>+</sup>/[pH7.4]) nor isotonic Ca<sup>2+</sup> (105 mM) solution induced significant current. Representative I-V relations are shown in (E). Current responses from a vector (pTracer)-transfected cell are shown in (D).</p><p>(F) pH-dependence of the E<sub>rev</sub> of the wild-type DMT1 current in the presence or absence of 300 &#x003bc;M [Mn<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>o</sub>. In the absence of Mn<sup>2+</sup>, the pH dependence of the E<sub>rev</sub> can be fitted by a line with a slope 58 mV/pH unit. In the presence of 300 &#x003bc;M Mn<sup>2+</sup>, the relationship was nonlinear, especially at higher pH. E<sub>H</sub>, H<sup>+</sup> equilibrium potential. Note that the currents were not leak-subtracted.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020050.g001"/></fig><p>Ca<sup>2+</sup> is not a measurable substrate for wild-type DMT1 (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Gunshin1" ref-type="bibr">Gunshin et al. 1997</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020050-Tandy1" ref-type="bibr">Tandy et al. 2000</xref>), even though it is at least 1,000 times more abundant in plasma than trace metals. Surprisingly, we found that the G185R mutation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g001">Figure 1</xref>A) dramatically increases the Ca<sup>2+</sup>-permeability of DMT1, functionally converting DMT1 into a Ca<sup>2+</sup> channel. In light of the important and ubiquitous role of Ca<sup>2+</sup> in cell signaling (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Berridge1" ref-type="bibr">Berridge et al. 2003</xref>), this gain of function offers a likely explanation for the remutation.</p><p>Interpretations of recent structural data have already suggested that permeation pathways exist within some transporters (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Hirai1" ref-type="bibr">Hirai et al. 2002</xref>), blurring the distinction between transporters and ion channels (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-DeFelice1" ref-type="bibr">DeFelice and Blakely 1996</xref>). Our finding, that a single amino acid substitution in a presumed transporter can expose a channel pathway, strongly supports this notion and provides new insight into what must be viewed as a continuum between transporter and channel activities.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><p>We studied wild-type DMT1 and the G185R mutant proteins by whole-cell patch&#x02013;clamp in transiently expressing CHO-K1 and HEK-293T cells and in doxycycline-inducible DMT1-HEK-On and G185R-HEK-On cells. Consistent with previous studies, DMT1 expression significantly increased cellular <sup>55</sup>Fe<sup>2+</sup> uptake at low pH (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g001">Figure 1</xref>B). As reported in <italic>Xenopu</italic>s oocytes (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Gunshin1" ref-type="bibr">Gunshin et al. 1997</xref>), reduction of extra-cellular pH in the absence of metal (nominal free [Fe<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>o</sub> of approximately 0.05 &#x003bc;M) induced large inward currents in DMT1-expressing cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g001">Figure 1</xref>C and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g001">1</xref>D). This current is referred to as a substrate-free &#x0201c;leak&#x0201d; pathway and is representative of &#x0201c;drive-slip&#x0201d; phenomena seen in DMT1 and a related yeast metal transporter, SMF1p (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Sacher1" ref-type="bibr">Sacher et al. 2001</xref>), as well as many other transporters (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Nelson1" ref-type="bibr">Nelson et al. 2002</xref>). Because we found that protons also activated an endogenous diisothiocyanostilbene 2,2-disolphonic acid (DIDS)-sensitive anion conductance (unpublished data) that was strongly outwardly rectifying (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sg001">Figure S1</xref>), we used SO<sub>4</sub>
<sup>2&#x02013;</sup> to replace most of the Cl<sup>&#x02013;</sup> ([Cl<sup>&#x02013;</sup>]<sub>o </sub>= 5 mM) in low-pH bath solutions. With elimination of the background Cl<sup>&#x02013;</sup> current, the proton-evoked current was inwardly rectifying (hyperbolic) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g001">Figure 1</xref>E).</p><p>The large proton-induced current caused significant DMT1-specific intracellular acidification (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Gunshin1" ref-type="bibr">Gunshin et al. 1997</xref>). In whole-cell recordings of DMT1 currents, we routinely observed slow inactivation (or decay) after a proton-induced current reached its peak (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g001">Figure 1</xref>C). While the extent of the slow inactivation varied from cell to cell, it usually reached a relative steady state within 100 s. Addition of 100 &#x003bc;M Fe<sup>2+</sup> (data not shown) or Mn<sup>2+</sup> induced an additional current with less pronounced slow inactivation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g001">Figure 1</xref>C). Because Fe<sup>2+</sup> is readily oxidized to Fe<sup>3+</sup> in the absence of substantial concentrations of reducing agents (e.g., ascorbate), and Fe<sup>3+</sup> is not transported by DMT1 (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Gunshin1" ref-type="bibr">Gunshin et al. 1997</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020050-Picard1" ref-type="bibr">Picard et al. 2000</xref>), we have used Mn<sup>2+</sup> as an Fe<sup>2+</sup> surrogate since both metals induced similar currents (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Gunshin1" ref-type="bibr">Gunshin et al. 1997</xref>; unpublished data). The observed Mn<sup>2+</sup> deficiency of <italic>b</italic> rats in vivo (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Chua1" ref-type="bibr">Chua and Morgan 1997</xref>) also supports its use in this role.</p><p>H<sup>+</sup> alone or H<sup>+</sup>/Mn<sup>2+</sup> induce distinct currents in DMT1. No significant voltage- or time-dependent fast inactivation was seen when the DMT1-mediated H<sup>+</sup>/Mn<sup>2+</sup> current (I<sub>DMT1</sub>) was recorded (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sg002">Figure S2</xref>). The amplitude of additional Mn<sup>2+</sup>-induced current was dependent on [Mn<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>o</sub>, with a measurable response at [Mn<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>o</sub> &#x0003c; 1 &#x003bc;M (pH 4.2). In the presence of 100 &#x003bc;M Mn<sup>2+</sup> (pH 4.2), the additional Mn<sup>2+</sup>-induced current was typically half the amplitude of the proton-induced current. Addition of Mn<sup>2+</sup> alone (100 &#x003bc;M) at pH 7.4 did not induce any additional current. Since H<sup>+</sup> or H<sup>+</sup>/Mn<sup>2+</sup> induced two currents with distinct kinetics in DMT1-expressing cells, the underlying charge-carrying ion species and their relative contributions to the macroscopic currents were investigated. We monitored the reversal potential (E<sub>rev</sub>) and the current amplitude in ion-substitution experiments. Replacement of Na<sup>+</sup> with <italic>N</italic>-methyl-D-glucamine (NMDG<sup>+</sup>) did not significantly change the E<sub>rev</sub> of H<sup>+</sup> or H<sup>+</sup>/Mn<sup>2+</sup>-induced currents, although the net current amplitude was slightly increased (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sg003">Figure S3</xref>). On the other hand, the current amplitude (data not shown) and E<sub>rev</sub> of the proton current were strongly affected by [H<sup>+</sup>]<sub>o</sub> (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g001">Figure 1</xref>F). The slope of E<sub>rev</sub> versus pH was 58 mV/decade, is consistent with an H<sup>+</sup>-permeable pore. The large positive displacement in E<sub>rev</sub> from E<sub>H</sub> (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g001">Figure 1</xref>F) may result in part from leak and capacitance-charging, but the carrier mechanism is not well understood.</p><p>In contrast, when Mn<sup>2+</sup> was introduced, the slope of the curve fitted to E<sub>rev</sub> versus pH deviated considerably from the theoretical slope for a H<sup>+</sup>-permeable electrode (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g001">Figure 1</xref>F). Replacement of Na<sup>+</sup> by NMDG<sup>+</sup> did not significantly affect the Mn<sup>2+</sup>-induced response (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sg003">Figure S3</xref>). Our interpretation of this deviation is that DMT1 transport stoichiometry is variable (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Chen1" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al. 1999</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020050-Sacher1" ref-type="bibr">Sacher et al. 2001</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020050-Adams1" ref-type="bibr">Adams and DeFelice 2002</xref>) or has a fixed but very low permeation ratio (P<sub>Mn</sub>/P<sub>H</sub>) (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Hodgkin1" ref-type="bibr">Hodgkin and Horowicz 1959</xref>). P<sub>Mn</sub>/P<sub>H</sub> can be estimated from the slope of E<sub>rev</sub> versus pH based on an extended Goldman&#x02013;Hodgkin&#x02013;Katz equation (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Lewis1" ref-type="bibr">Lewis 1979</xref>) with two permeable ions (H<sup>+</sup> and Mn<sup>2+</sup>). At pH 4.2, the slope of E<sub>rev</sub> versus pH did not differ significantly with or without Mn<sup>2+</sup>(see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g001">Figure 1</xref>F). Therefore, we estimate that at pH 4.2 the contribution of H<sup>+</sup> to I<sub>DMT1</sub> is much larger than that of Fe<sup>2+</sup>/Mn<sup>2+</sup> (P<sub>Mn</sub>/P<sub>H </sub>&#x0003c; 0.01), in contrast to the 1:1 stoichiometry proposed previously (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Gunshin1" ref-type="bibr">Gunshin et al. 1997</xref>). Importantly, no Ca<sup>2+</sup> permeability was observed, even in isotonic (105 mM) Ca<sup>2+</sup> solution (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g001">Figure 1</xref>C).</p><p>In G185R-expressing cells, we observed a large inward current in control bath solution (10 mM Ca<sup>2+</sup> and 140 mM Na<sup>+</sup>) at pH 7.4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g002">Figure 2</xref>A), though no significant current was detected with wild-type DMT1 under similar conditions (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g001">Figure 1</xref>E). This inward current mediated by G185R mutant DMT1 (I<sub>G185R</sub>) was stable over minutes with no slow inactivation (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g002">Figure 2</xref>A), in contrast to the DMT1-mediated proton current (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g001">Figure 1</xref>C). We observed I<sub>G185R</sub> in more than 85% of enhanced green fluorescent protein (EGFP)-positive cells transfected with the pTracer-G185R construct and in stable, doxycycline-induced G185R-HEK-On cells, but never in cells transfected with wild-type <italic>DMT1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g001">Figure 1</xref>C) or with 30 <italic>DMT1</italic> mutations at other positions (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003e; 300 cells; unpublished data). The inwardly rectifying current was cationic, since Ca<sup>2+</sup> and Na<sup>+</sup> substitution by NMDG<sup>+</sup> completely abrogated the current (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g002">Figure 2</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g002">2</xref>B). The current and rectification profiles were not significantly changed when ATP and Mg<sup>2+</sup> were omitted from the intracellular solution, or when Na<sup>+</sup> or K<sup>+</sup> replaced Cs<sup>+</sup> as the primary intracellular cation.</p><fig id="pbio-0020050-g002" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>G185R-Expressing Cells Display a Constitutive [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>o</sub>-Dependent Cationic Current</title><p>(A&#x02013;B) Large inward currents were evoked by control solution (10mM Ca<sup>2+</sup>/140 mM Na<sup>+</sup> [pH 7.4]) in G185R-transfected cells. The current was inhibited by lowering the solution pH to 5.8 without altering other ions. Further reducing the pH to 4.2 induced I<sub>DMT1</sub>-like current (enhanced by adding 100 &#x003bc;M Mn<sup>2+</sup>). No significant inward current was seen in NMDG<sup>+</sup> (Na<sup>+</sup>-free, Ca<sup>2+</sup>-free) solution.</p><p>(C) Time- and voltage-dependent kinetics of I<sub>G185R</sub> recorded in control solution in response to voltage steps.</p><p>(D) Current densities (mean &#x000b1; SEM, <italic>n</italic> = 15) of I<sub>G185R</sub> in control solution mea-sured at various voltages and normalized by cell capacitance.</p><p>(E) Time- and voltage-dependent kinetics of I<sub>G185R</sub> in the presence of 105 mM Ca<sup>2+</sup>.</p><p>(F) Ca<sup>2+</sup> is more permeant than Na<sup>+</sup> in G185R-expressing cells.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020050.g002"/></fig><p>We found that low pH strongly inhibited I<sub>G185R</sub> (by approximately 90% at pH 5.8; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g002">Figure 2</xref>A), in contrast to both wild-type DMT1 currents, which were activated at low pH. However, further reduction to pH 4.2 revealed a current (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g002">Figure 2</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g002">2</xref>B) that was similar to the proton current of wild-type DMT1. Addition of Mn<sup>2+</sup> at pH 4.2 enhanced the inward current, as with wild-type DMT1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g002">Figure 2</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g002">2</xref>B). The proton current and Mn<sup>2+</sup>-induced response displayed similar patterns of inactivation and further activation as in wild-type DMT1-transfected cells, but both currents were much smaller than their wild-type counterparts. Consistent with this result and our previous uptake studies (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Su1" ref-type="bibr">Su et al. 1998</xref>), we found that G185R cells had much lower Fe<sup>2+</sup> uptake (approximately 10% measured at 16 min) compared to wild-type DMT1 at similar protein expression levels (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g001">Figure 1</xref>B).</p><p>I<sub>G185R</sub> rectified more steeply with voltage than I<sub>DMT1</sub>, probably due to pronounced time- and voltage-dependent fast inactivation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g002">Figure 2</xref>C; see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sg002">Figure S2</xref> for comparison). Fast inactivation was enhanced when [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>o </sub>was increased to 105 mM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g002">Figure 2</xref>E), strengthening the notion that I<sub>G185R</sub> was fundamentally distinct from the currents mediated by wild-type DMT1. In control bath solution (10 mM Ca<sup>2+</sup>, 140 mM Na<sup>+</sup> [pH 7.4]), I<sub>G185R </sub>was 64 &#x000b1; 7 pA/pF at &#x02212;140 mV (mean &#x000b1; SEM, <italic>n</italic> = 15; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g002">Figure 2</xref>D) compared to less than 2 pA/pF in mock and DMT1-transfected cells. I<sub>G185R</sub> reversed at approximately +20 mV with very little current above 0 mV (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g002">Figure 2</xref>D), whereas the E<sub>rev</sub> of I<sub>DMT1</sub> was approximately +50 mV at pH 4.2. The dependence of I<sub>G185R</sub> on holding potential was also distinct from I<sub>DMT1</sub> (see below).</p><p>We next investigated the cation selectivity of I<sub>G185R</sub>. The amplitude of I<sub>G185R</sub> was strongly dependent on [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>o</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g002">Figure 2</xref>F). With 10 mM Ca<sup>2+</sup> in the bath, replacement of 140 mM NMDG<sup>+</sup> by 140 mM Na<sup>+</sup> only slightly (by approximately 15%) increased the current, indicating that Ca<sup>2+</sup> permeated the plasma membrane of G185R-transfected cells much more readily than Na<sup>+</sup>. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g003">Figure 3</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g003">3</xref>B, increasing [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>o</sub> not only augmented the current amplitude but also shifted E<sub>rev</sub> toward depolarized potentials. The slope of this shift (25 mV per decade) was close to the slope of 29 mV per decade predicted by the Nernst equation for a Ca<sup>2+</sup>-selective electrode (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g003">Figure 3</xref>C). The relative permeability of various divalent cations was studied under bi-ionic conditions (pipette solution containing Na<sup>+</sup> and Glutamate; see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>). After adding 10 mM test divalent cations to the NMDG<sup>+</sup> solution, we recorded currents using step voltages from two holding potentials (-60 mV and +40 mV). We determined G185R-specific currents by measuring the reversal potentials of the currents subtracted from two holding potentials (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g004">Figure 4</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g004">4</xref>B) and corrected for the junction potential. The permeability sequence was Ca<sup>2+</sup> &#x0003e; Sr<sup>2+</sup> &#x0003e; Ba<sup>2+</sup> as calculated (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pbio-0020050-e001">Equation 2</xref>; see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>) and illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g003">Figure 3</xref>E. For divalent cations, we found that the highest conductance was to Ca<sup>2+</sup>, followed by Sr<sup>2+</sup> and Ba<sup>2+</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g003">Figure 3</xref>D). While Ca<sup>2+</sup>, Sr<sup>2+</sup>, and Ba<sup>2+</sup> currents were relatively stable over time, currents mediated by Mn<sup>2+</sup> and Mg<sup>2+</sup> were transient (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g003">Figure 3</xref>D), the simplest explanation for this behavior being a block by these two weakly permeant ions. The monovalent permeability was calculated using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pbio-0020050-e001">Equation 1</xref> (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">see Materials and Methods</xref>), yielding a selectivity sequence Li<sup>+</sup> &#x0003e; Na<sup>+</sup> &#x0003e; K<sup>+</sup> &#x0003e; Cs<sup>+</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g003">Figure 3</xref>E). Under these conditions, P<sub>Mn </sub>was insignificant. The cationic permeability sequence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g003">Figure 3</xref>E) of I<sub>G185R</sub> was similar to L-type voltage-gated Ca<sup>2+</sup> channels (VGCCs) (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Sather1" ref-type="bibr">Sather and McCleskey 2003</xref>), but I<sub>G185R</sub> was less Ca<sup>2+</sup>-selective (P<sub>Ca</sub>/P<sub>Na </sub>of approximately 10) than VGCCs (P<sub>Ca</sub>/P<sub>Na </sub>of approximately 1,000). Single <italic>i</italic>
<sub>G185R</sub> channels were not observed in cell-attached patches. Analysis of membrane current noise at &#x02212;100 mV predicted a single-channel chord conductance of 0.4 &#x000b1; 0.1 pS (<italic>n</italic> = 5; unpublished data), too small to be observed under most patch&#x02013;clamp conditions.</p><fig id="pbio-0020050-g003" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Ca<sup>2+</sup> Permeability of I<sub>G185R</sub>
</title><p>(A) Whole-cell I-V relations in the presence of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>o</sub> are indicated.</p><p>(B) Enlarged view of (A) to show the E<sub>rev</sub> measurement.</p><p>(C) [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>o</sub> dependence of E<sub>rev</sub>. The slope was fit by linear regression to 25 mV per decade, close to the 29 mV per decade predicted for a Ca<sup>2+</sup>-selective electrode (dotted line).</p><p>(D) Currents through G185R in various isotonic divalent solutions. I-Vs are shown in the inset. Note that currents induced by isotonic Mg<sup>2+</sup> and Mn<sup>2+</sup> were transient.</p><p>(E) Relative permeability of various divalent and monovalent cations<bold>.</bold> The reversal potentials of I<sub>G185R</sub> in 10 mM test divalent cations were measured under bi-ionic conditions as described in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>. The permeability was calculated using Equations 1 and 2.</p><p>(F) [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> changes estimated by Fura-2 fluorescence in response to an elevation of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>o</sub> from 1 to 30 mM. The results were averaged from five (HEK-On) and seven (G185R) independent experiments (<italic>n</italic> = 3&#x02013;13 cells each). To minimize potential endogenous depletion-activated and/or TRP-mediated Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx, cells were bathed in the presence of 50 &#x003bc;M SKF96365 and 50 &#x003bc;M 2-APB. The F340/F380 ratio was recorded and converted into estimated [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> based on an ionomycin-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> calibration.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020050.g003"/></fig><fig id="pbio-0020050-g004" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Voltage Dependence and Pharmacological Properties of I<sub>G185R</sub>
</title><p>(A) Whole-cell currents recorded in 105 mM [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>o</sub> were dependent on holding potential before the voltage ramps (&#x02212;140 to &#x02212;120 mV shown). For clarity, only the first 20 ms of the 4 s-long holding potential is shown.</p><p>(B) Voltage dependence of I<sub>G185R </sub>in control solution and 105 mM [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>o</sub>. I<sub>DMT1</sub> (dotted line) exhibited no depen-dence on the holding potential. Abbreviations: V<sub>1/2</sub> , half activation voltage. &#x003ba;, slope factor.</p><p>(C and D) Sensitivity of I<sub>G185R </sub>to various pharmacological agents and cation channel blockers. I<sub>G185R</sub> was relatively insensitive to RR, 2-APB, or SKF96365, but was blocked by 1mM La<sup>3+</sup> or Cd<sup>2+</sup> (D).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020050.g004"/></fig><p>Using the Ca<sup>2+</sup> indicator dye Fura-2, we demonstrated G185R-mediated Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx by monitoring intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> levels in response to an elevation of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>o</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g003">Figure 3</xref>F). To minimize the contributions of endogenous Ca<sup>2+</sup>-influx and/or store release, we bathed cells in the presence of 50 &#x003bc;M SKF96365 and 50 &#x003bc;M 2-APB. Upon raising [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>o</sub>, [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> rose from 105 nM to 240 nM in doxycycline-induced G185R-HEK-On cells, significantly higher than in control HEK-On cells treated with doxycycline. Thus, the permeability of G185R to Ca<sup>2+</sup> is capable of increasing [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>.</p><p>I<sub>G185R</sub> displayed hyperpolarization-induced inhibition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g004">Figure 4</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g004">4</xref>B) (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Bakowski1" ref-type="bibr">Bakowski and Parekh 2000</xref>). The half-maximal activation voltages (V<sub>1/2</sub>) were &#x02212;33 mV and &#x02212;10 mV for control and isotonic Ca<sup>2+</sup> solutions, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g004">Figure 4</xref>B). The voltage-dependence of I<sub>G185R</sub> was Ca<sup>2+</sup>-independent, since the Na<sup>+</sup> and Li<sup>+</sup> currents in nominal [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>o</sub> also exhibited a similar voltage dependence. By contrast, I<sub>DMT1</sub> lacked this voltage dependence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g004">Figure 4</xref>B). I<sub>G185R</sub> was not enhanced under low-divalent conditions (less than 10 nM), nor was it blocked by antagonists of known Ca<sup>2+</sup>-permeant channels. In particular, the current was not blocked by ruthenium red (RR), Ca<sup>2+</sup>-release activated Ca<sup>2+</sup> channel (CRAC) blockers SKF96365 and 2-APB (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Kozak1" ref-type="bibr">Kozak et al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020050-Prakriya1" ref-type="bibr">Prakriya and Lewis 2002</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g004">Figure 4</xref>C), or the L-type VGCC blocker nifedepine (10 &#x003bc;M). Divalent cations, including DMT1 substrates (Cd<sup>2+</sup>, Ni<sup>2+</sup>, Co<sup>2+</sup>), inhibited I<sub>G185R</sub>. La<sup>3+</sup> (1 mM; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g004">Figure 4</xref>C) and Cd<sup>2+</sup> (1 mM) blocked I<sub>G185R</sub> in a similar voltage-dependent manner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g004">Figure 4</xref>D). Thus, I<sub>G185R</sub> is distinct from known Ca<sup>2+</sup>-permeant channels such as VGCCs, transient receptor potentials (TRPs), and CRAC currents, based on its current&#x02013;voltage (I-V) relation, kinetics, permeation properties, and pharmacological sensitivity.</p><p>To investigate whether G185R-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> permeability might play a physiological role in the mutant animals, we recorded from intestinal enterocytes isolated from both wild-type and homozygous <italic>mk</italic> mice. We studied cells from the proximal 1 cm of the mouse duodenum, where DMT1 expression is highest and iron absorption is maximal (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Gunshin1" ref-type="bibr">Gunshin et al. 1997</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020050-Canonne-Hergaux1" ref-type="bibr">Canonne-Hergaux et al. 1999</xref>). Because DMT1 expression is very low in iron-replete, wild-type mice, but induced in iron-deficient mice (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Canonne-Hergaux1" ref-type="bibr">Canonne-Hergaux et al. 1999</xref>), we isolated enterocytes from mice that had been made iron-deficient by prolonged feeding of an iron-deficient diet, and confirmed DMT1 induction by Western blotting using a DMT1-specific antibody (unpublished data). We were able to record I<sub>DMT1</sub>-like currents in mature enterocytes that stained positive for alkaline phosphatase (I &#x0003e; 80 pA at &#x02212;130mV, <italic>n</italic> = 7 out of 20 cells; representative data shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g005">Figure 5</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g005">5</xref>B).</p><fig id="pbio-0020050-g005" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>DMT1-Like and G185R-Like Currents in Enterocytes Isolated from Wild-Type and <italic>mk</italic>/<italic>mk</italic> Mice, Respectively</title><p>(A) Enterocyte currents isolated from an iron-deficient wild-type mouse (&#x02212;Fe). Reducing bath pH (140 mM NaCl) induced a slowly desensitizing inward current that was further enhanced by addition of Mn<sup>2+</sup>.</p><p>(B) Both proton and H<sup>+</sup>/Mn<sup>2+</sup>currents were inwardly rectifying.</p><p>(C and D) An <italic>mk</italic> enterocyte expressed a large constitutive inward current in control bath solution. Reducing the bath pH (140 mM NaCl) first inhibited and then activated another inward current insensitive to the holding potential. This slowly-desensitizing current displayed a less steeply rectifying I-V as shown in (D).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020050.g005"/></fig><p>Mice homozygous for the <italic>mk</italic> mutation express large amounts of G185R DMT1 protein in the duodenum. Although much of it is mislocalized to the cytoplasm (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Canonne-Hergaux2" ref-type="bibr">Canonne-Hergaux et al. 2000</xref>), we expected that some would be present in the plasma membrane. Accordingly, and in contrast with wild-type enterocytes, we recorded a large, constitutive inward current in most mature <italic>mk</italic> enterocytes (<italic>n</italic>= 6 out of 8 cells; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g005">Figure 5</xref>C and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g005">5</xref>D), which displayed the same conductance as seen in G185R-transfected cells. The I-V relationship, step current response, dependence on holding potential, ion selectivity and insensitivity to RR, and SKF96365 or 2-APB were indistinguishable from those of transfected I<sub>G185R</sub>. Furthermore, H<sup>+</sup> inhibited the I<sub>G185R</sub>-like current in <italic>mk</italic> enterocytes, and the H<sup>+</sup>/Mn<sup>2+</sup>-induced DMT1-like current at pH 4.2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g005">Figure 5</xref>C and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020050-g005">5</xref>D) was insensitive to holding potential, as observed in transfected cells. Based on these observations, we conclude that the major current observed in <italic>mk</italic> enterocytes was I<sub>G185R</sub>. Although our preparation did not allow us to distinguish apical versus basolateral localization, the large size of the current in <italic>mk</italic> cells was consistent with plasma membrane localization of G185R protein.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>We conclude that expression of G185R in transfected cells and in vivo in <italic>mk</italic> mice is associated with the appearance of a novel Ca<sup>2+</sup> permeation pathway that has the properties of a Ca<sup>2+</sup> channel. One interpretation is that a Ca<sup>2+</sup> channel pathway through the DMT1 protein is exposed or augmented by the G185R mutation. Another possibility is that Ca<sup>2+</sup> conduction occurs through an associated Ca<sup>2+</sup>-permeable protein. We favor the first possibility because the Ca<sup>2+</sup> conductance has been observed in diverse cell lines expressing G185R DMT1 (CHO-K1, HEK293T, and HEK-On cell lines) and in <italic>mk</italic> enterocytes. A putative associated protein, if present in these different cell types, would have to be activated in a G185R-dependent manner. We did not find evidence of an associated protein when we immunoprecipitated wild-type or G185R DMT1 from transfected CHO-K1 cells (unpublished data). Furthermore, a distinct DMT1 mutant, G185K, also displayed Ca<sup>2+</sup> permeability, but this mutant was less selective for Ca<sup>2+</sup> over Na<sup>+</sup> (unpublished data).</p><p>G185R mutations have occurred at least three times in rodents, which suggests that G185R not only inactivates DMT1, but may confer an unknown selective advantage. Because it has arisen in inbred colonies, the postulated selective advantage must either make the animals more viable than other <italic>DMT1</italic> mutants with impaired iron transport or more likely to be noticed by those managing the animal colonies. In parallel with these studies, we have generated knockout mice homozygous for a null <italic>DMT1</italic> allele (<italic>Dmt1<sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup></italic>; H. Gunshin and N. C. Andrews, personal communication). Although detailed phenotypic characterization has not yet been completed, we have noted that <italic>Dmt1<sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup></italic> mice invariably die by the end of the first week of life, in contrast to <italic>mk/mk</italic> mice, which are poorly viable but can survive for more than a year (H. Gunshin and N. C. Andrews, personal communication). This suggests that the small amount of residual function of G185R DMT1, perhaps in combination with its gain-of-function Ca<sup>2+</sup> conductance, contributes to viability.</p><p>Two previous studies support the notion that the gain-of-function reported here is an advantage. Elevated intracellular [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] has been reported to increase nontransferrin-bound iron uptake through an undefined transport system that has characteristics distinct from DMT1 (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Kaplan1" ref-type="bibr">Kaplan et al. 1991</xref>). This might ameliorate the iron-transport defect caused by inactivation of DMT1, either in the intestine or in erythroid precursors. The transferrin cycle is essential for iron uptake by erythroid precursor cells (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Levy1" ref-type="bibr">Levy et al. 1999</xref>), and DMT1 mediates at least some of the transfer of iron from transferrin cycle endosomes to the cytoplasm (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Fleming2" ref-type="bibr">Fleming et al. 1998</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020050-Gruenheid1" ref-type="bibr">Gruenheid et al. 1999</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020050-Touret1" ref-type="bibr">Touret et al. 2003</xref>). Elevated [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> has been reported to accelerate iron uptake through the transferrin cycle, apparently through activation of protein kinase C (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Ci1" ref-type="bibr">Ci et al. 2003</xref>). Thus, the influx of Ca<sup>2+</sup> might potentiate the residual DMT1 iron-transport activity. Accordingly, <sup>55</sup>Fe uptake by <italic>mk/mk</italic> reticulocytes has been reported to be approximately 45% of the level observed in wild-type reticulocytes (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Canonne-Hergaux3" ref-type="bibr">Canonne-Hergaux et al. 2001</xref>), higher than expected for a severe loss-of-function mutation.</p><p>In summary, we have found that a single point mutation (G185R) in a 12-TM transporter protein conferred new Ca<sup>2+</sup>-selective permeability. Previous studies have suggested that channels, pumps, and transporters may share some common mechanisms for ion translocation (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Gadsby1" ref-type="bibr">Gadsby et al. 1993</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020050-Fairman1" ref-type="bibr">Fairman et al. 1995</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020050-Cammack1" ref-type="bibr">Cammack and Schwartz 1996</xref>; for review see references in <xref rid="pbio-0020050-Lester1" ref-type="bibr">Lester and Dougherty 1998</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020050-Nelson1" ref-type="bibr">Nelson et al. 2002</xref>). The &#x0201c;channel mode&#x0201d; has been proposed to explain the &#x0201c;drive-slip&#x0201d; mechanism as part of the transport cycle. In this sense, wild-type DMT1 may simply be a proton channel with limited permeability for certain divalent metal ions. By mutating a single residue, G185R, it becomes an unambiguously Ca<sup>2+</sup>-permeant ion channel. Our findings may add new insight into mechanisms of Ca<sup>2+</sup> entry and transporter function. The notion that the 12-TM proteins can be ion channels may inform the search for candidate Ca<sup>2+</sup> and/or cationic channels and facilitate the molecular characterization of many unidentified native conductances.</p><p>We initiated these studies to investigate why a unique DMT1 mutation, G185R, has occurred independently at least twice in mice and once in rats (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Fleming1" ref-type="bibr">Fleming et al. 1997</xref>,<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Fleming2" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>). The multiple occurrences of this spontaneous mutation suggested that it might confer some type of selective advantage. We speculate that the proposed Ca<sup>2+</sup> entry gain of function helps to account for this remarkable pattern of remutation. Further investigation of this hypothesis will require direct and detailed comparison of <italic>DMT1</italic>-null and <italic>mk</italic> mice.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title/><sec id="s4a1"><title>Molecular biology</title><p>The <italic>DMT1</italic> cDNA used in this study was derived from one of four alternatively-spliced <italic>DMT1</italic> gene transcripts. The G185R mutation was generated by using M13 phage and the oligonucleotide GTCCCCCTGTGGGGC<italic>C</italic>GAGTCCTCATCACCA. Wild-type DMT1 and the G185R mutant were tagged with a C-terminal FLAG epitope and subcloned into pTracer-CMV2 (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, California, United States). CHO-K1 or HEK293T cells transiently transfected with DMT1 and G185R were used for the <sup>55</sup>Fe uptake assay and Western blot analysis. To obtain a stable G185R-expressing cell line, the G185R-encoding <italic>DMT1</italic> gene was subcloned into pRevTRE (Clontech, Palo Alto, California, United States), a retroviral vector that drives expression from a Tet-responsive element. All constructs were confirmed by sequencing. DMT1 Western blot analyses were performed with an anti-FLAG M2 monoclonal antibody (Sigma, St. Louis, Missouri, United States) and, in some cases, with a goat polyclonal antibody raised against human DMT1 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Santa Cruz, California, United States).</p></sec><sec id="s4a2"><title>Mammalian cell electrophysiology</title><p>Wild-type and G185R mutant DMT1 were subcloned into an EGFP-containing vector (pTracer-CMV2, Invitrogen) for transient expression in CHO-K1 and HEK293T cells. Cells were transfected using Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen). Transfected cells, cultured at 37&#x000b0;C, were plated onto glass coverslips and recorded 24 (DMT1) or 30 (G185R) hrs after transfection. A stable cell line (HEK293 Tet-On<sup>TM</sup>, or HEK-On) was generated, and expression was induced by adding 1&#x02013;10 &#x003bc;g/ml doxycycline into the culture medium. Unless otherwise stated, the pipette solution contained 147 mM cesium, 120 mM methane-sulfonate, 8 mM NaCl, 10 mM EGTA, 2 mM Mg-ATP, 20 mM HEPES (pH 7.4). Bath solution contained 140 mM NaCl, 10 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 mM HEPES, 10 mM MES, 10 mM glucose (pH 7.4). Unless otherwise stated, the low pH solutions contained only nominal free Ca<sup>2+</sup> (1&#x02013;10 &#x003bc;M). Data were collected using an Axopatch 2A patch&#x02013;clamp amplifier, Digidata 1320, and pClamp 8.0 software (Axon Instruments, Union City, California, United States). Whole-cell currents were digitized at 10 kHz and filtered at 2 kHz.</p><p>The permeability to monovalent cations (relative to P<sub>Na</sub>) was estimated according to <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pbio-0020050-e001">Equation 1</xref> from the shift in E<sub>rev</sub> upon replacing [Na<sup>+</sup>]<sub>o</sub> in nominally Ca<sup>2+</sup>-free bath solution (150 mM XCl, 20 mM HEPES, 10 mM glucose [pH 7.4]]), where X<sup>+</sup> was Na<sup>+</sup>, K<sup>+</sup>, Cs<sup>+</sup>, or Li<sup>+</sup>. For the permeability to divalent cations (relative to P<sub>Na</sub>), bi-ionic conditions were used; Y<sup>2+</sup> was Ca<sup>2+</sup>, Ba<sup>2+</sup>, or Sr<sup>2+</sup> (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pbio-0020050-e001">Equation 2</xref>). The internal pipette solution contained 100 mM Na-gluconate, 10 mM NaCl, 10 mM EGTA, 20 mM HEPES-Na (pH 7.4 adjusted with NaOH, [Na<sup>+</sup>]<sub>total</sub> = 140). The external solution was 140 mM NMDG-Cl, 10 mM Y<sup>2+</sup>Cl<sub>2</sub>, 20 mM HEPES (pH 7.4 adjusted with HCl). The permeability ratios of cations were estimated from the following equations (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Lewis1" ref-type="bibr">Lewis 1979</xref>):</p><p>
<disp-formula id="pbio-0020050-e001"><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020050.e001.jpg" mimetype="image" position="float"/></disp-formula>
</p><p>where R, T, F, V, and &#x003b3; are, respectively, the gas constant, absolute temperature, Faraday constant, E<sub>rev</sub>, and activity coefficient. The liquid junction potentials were measured and corrected as described by <xref rid="pbio-0020050-Neher1" ref-type="bibr">Neher (1992</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4a3"><title>Uptake assay</title><p>The assay buffer contained 25 mM Tris, 25 mM MES, 140 mM NaCl, 5.4 mM KCl, 5 mM glucose, 1.8 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.8 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>. Ascorbic acid was adjusted to 1 mM and the pH was adjusted to 5.8. Most assays were performed with 20 &#x003bc;M Fe<sup>2+</sup> at pH 5.8 unless otherwise indicated. A 50-fold <sup>55</sup>Fe stock was made immediately before the assay with 1 mM <sup>55</sup>Fe (with a 1:20 molar ratio for <sup>55</sup>FeCl<sub>3</sub> and FeSO<sub>4</sub>) and 50 mM nitrilotriacetic acid. About 30 h after transient transfection, CHO-K1 or HEK293T cells were washed and harvested with PBS (for CHO-K1 cells, trypsin treatment was required). Cells were resuspended in glass test tubes at 0.5&#x02013;1 million/ml in 490 &#x003bc;l assay buffer at 30&#x000b0;C. The reaction was started by adding 10 &#x003bc;l of <sup>55</sup>Fe stock and stopped at 4, 8, and 16 min by quickly filtering the reaction mix on a nitrocellulose filter (HAWP02500; Millipore, Billerica, Massachusetts, United States). Filters were washed twice with 2 ml of assay buffer, dried, and radioactivity counted by liquid scintillation spectrometry.</p></sec><sec id="s4a4"><title>Calcium imaging</title><p>Cells were loaded with 2 &#x003bc;M Fura-2 AM in culture medium at 37&#x000b0;C for 30 min. Low levels of G185R protein were expressed in the absence of doxycycline in G185R HEK-On cells (Western blotting; unpublished data). Therefore, doxycycline-treated HEK-On cells not expressing DMT1 were used as controls in imaging experiments. We recorded Fura-2 ratios (F340/F380) on an UltraVIEW imaging system (Olympus, Tokyo, Japan). A standard curve for Fura-2 ratio versus [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] was constructed according to <xref rid="pbio-0020050-Grynkiewicz1" ref-type="bibr">Grynkiewicz et al. (1985</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4a5"><title>Isolation of enterocytes</title><p>Homozygous <italic>mk</italic> mice (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Fleming1" ref-type="bibr">Fleming et al. 1997</xref>) were housed in the barrier facility at Children's Hospital (Boston, Massachusetts, United States). Husbandry and use were according to protocols approved by the Animal Care and Use Committee. Wild-type iron-deficient mice were provided by J.-J. Chen (Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, Massachusetts, United States). Mouse enterocytes were isolated using a modified protocol provided by Dr. F. Sepulveda (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Monaghan1" ref-type="bibr">Monaghan et al. 1997</xref>). In brief, 1 cm of the proximal duodenum was excised, rinsed with cold PBS, and soaked for 5 min at 37&#x000b0;C in a solution containing 7 mM K<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>, 44 mM K<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, 9 mM NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, 15 mM Na<sub>3</sub>Citrate, 10 mM HEPES, and 180 mM glucose (pH 7.4). The tissue was then incubated with gentle shaking for 3 min in a similar solution containing 7 mM K<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>, 44 mM K<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, 9 mM NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, 10 mM HEPES, 180 mM glucose, 1 mM DTT, and 0.2 mM EDTA (pH 7.4). The mucosal cells were gently squeezed from the duodenum with forceps into 5 ml of ice-cold DMEM/F12 medium, pelleted at 800 &#x000d7; <italic>g</italic> for 4 min, resuspended in 5 ml of prewarmed DMEM/F12 with 0.5 mg/ml collagenase type 1A, and incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 10 min. Cells isolated by this procedure have been shown previously to be primarily of villus origin and hence are mature enterocytes. We confirmed this by alkaline phosphatase staining. Diluted cells were filtered through a 40-&#x003bc;m nylon cell mesh (BD Biosciences, Palo Alto, California, United States). The cells were then washed with DMEM/F12, resuspended in 20 ml of ice-cold DMEM and kept at 4&#x000b0;C. They were plated on coverslips coated with Cell-Tak<sup>TM</sup> (BD Biosciences) and maintained on ice before patch&#x02013;clamp recording at room temperature.</p></sec><sec id="s4a6"><title>Data analysis</title><p>Group data are presented as mean &#x000b1; SEM. Statistical comparisons were made using analysis of variance and the <italic>t</italic>-test with Bonferroni correction. A two-tailed value of <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 was taken to be statistically significant.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sg001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><title>CHO-K1 Cells Express an Endogenous Proton-Activated Chloride Channel</title><p>(A) Anion dependence of pH-induced response in a DMT1-expressing cell. Outward current usually appears later than the inward current.</p><p>(B) Currents generated in response to a voltage ramp.</p><p>(C) pH-induced outwardly rectifying current in a nontransfected CHO-K1 cell. A similar current was seen also in HEK293T and HEK-On cells, with properties similar to the cloned ClC-7 channel (<xref rid="pbio-0020050-Diewald1" ref-type="bibr">Diewald et al. 2002</xref>). This current exhibits the same anion depen-dence as in (A) (data not shown)<bold>. </bold>We attributed the outward currents shown in (A) and (B) to this endogenous Cl<sup>&#x02013;</sup> current. Therefore, for our recordings on DMT1, SO<sub>4</sub>
<sup>2\&#x02013;</sup> was usually used to replace most of the Cl<sup>&#x02013;</sup> ([Cl<sup>&#x02013;</sup>]<sub>o</sub> = 5 mM) for all low-pH bath solutions. </p><p>(718 KB PDF).</p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0020050.sg001.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sg002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><title>Time- and Voltage-Dependent Kinetics of H<sup>+</sup>/Mn<sup>2+</sup> Current of DMT1</title><p>Whole-cell currents were generated by voltage steps from &#x02212;140 to +80 mV in 20 mV steps, 400 ms. The interval between steps was 1,000 ms. (1 MB PDF).</p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0020050.sg002.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sg003"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><title>Na<sup>+</sup>-Dependence of DMT1 H<sup>+</sup> and H<sup>+</sup>/Mn<sup>2+</sup> Currents</title><p>Replacement of extracellular Na<sup>+</sup> by NMDG<sup>+</sup> slightly increased the proton current (approximately 20%) and this was further augmented by adding 300 &#x003bc;M Mn<sup>2+</sup>. The concentrations used were Na<sup>+</sup> and NMDG<sup>+</sup>, 140 mM, (pH 4.2); Mn<sup>2+</sup>, 300 &#x003bc;M. (141 KB PDF).</p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0020050.sg003.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><sec id="s5a"><title/><sec id="s5a1"><title>Accession Numbers</title><p>The GenBank (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/GenBank/">www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/GenBank/</ext-link>) accession number for <italic>DMT1</italic> is AF029758.</p></sec></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>This work resulted from a balanced collaboration between the Andrews and Clapham laboratories, supported by the Howard Hughes Medical Institute. NCA is also supported by a research grant from the National Institutes of Health (RO1 DK53813). Mark D. Fleming contributed to the care and dissection of <italic>mk</italic> mice. We thank Jane-Jane Chen for providing the mice on low-iron diet and Francisco Sepulveda for the protocol used to isolate enterocytes. We are grateful to I. Scott Ramsey, Renee M. Ned, Elena Oancea, and Svetlana Gapon for assistance and to Thomas E. DeCoursey, Jian Yang, Lixia Yue, and Richard Aldrich for comments. We appreciate encouragement and helpful comments from other members of the Clapham and Andrews laboratories.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="n1" fn-type="COI-statement"><p>
<bold>Conflicts of interest.</bold> The authors have declared that no conflicts of interest exist.</p></fn><fn id="n2" fn-type="con"><p>
<bold>Author contributions.</bold> HX, JJ, LJD, NCA, and DEC conceived and designed the experiments. HX and JJ performed the experiments. HX and JJ analyzed the data. HX, NCA, and DEC wrote the paper.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="n3" fn-type="edited-by"><p>Academic Editor: Chris Miller, Brandeis University</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pbio-0020050-Adams1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>DeFelice</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flux coupling in the human serotonin transporter</article-title><source>Biophys J</source><year>2002</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>3268</fpage><lpage>3282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12496095</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Andrews1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Iron homeostasis: Insights from genetics and animal models</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><year>2000</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11252750</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Bakowski1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bakowski</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Parekh</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Voltage-dependent conductance changes in the store-operated Ca<sup>2+</sup> current I<sub>CRAC</sub>in rat basophilic leukaemia cells</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>529</volume><fpage>295</fpage><lpage>306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11101641</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Berridge1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berridge</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bootman</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Roderick</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Calcium signalling: Dynamics, homeostasis and remodelling</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>517</fpage><lpage>529</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12838335</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Cammack1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cammack</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Channel behavior in a gamma-aminobutyrate transporter</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1996</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>723</fpage><lpage>727</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8570623</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Canonne-Hergaux1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Canonne-Hergaux</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruenheid</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponka</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gros</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cellular and subcellular localization of the Nramp2 iron transporter in the intestinal brush border and regulation by dietary iron</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>1999</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>4406</fpage><lpage>4417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10361139</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Canonne-Hergaux2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Canonne-Hergaux</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ralph</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Nramp2/DMT1 iron transporter is induced in the duodenum of microcytic anemia <italic>mk</italic> mice but is not properly targeted to the intestinal brush border</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2000</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>3964</fpage><lpage>3970</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11090085</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Canonne-Hergaux3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Canonne-Hergaux</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponka</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gros</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the iron transporter DMT1 (NRAMP2/DCT1) in red blood cells of normal and anemic <italic>mk</italic>/<italic>mk</italic> mice</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2001</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>3823</fpage><lpage>3830</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11739192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Chen1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>XZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Yeast SMF1 mediates H<sup>+</sup>-coupled iron uptake with concomitant uncoupled cation currents</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1999</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>35089</fpage><lpage>35094</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10574989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Chua1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Manganese metabolism is impaired in the Belgrade laboratory rat</article-title><source>J Comp Physiol [B]</source><year>1997</year><volume>167</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>369</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Ci1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ci</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ke</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> regulates the cellular iron uptake in K562 cells</article-title><source>Cell Calcium</source><year>2003</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12618146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-DeFelice1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeFelice</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Blakely</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pore models for transporters?</article-title><source>Biophys J</source><year>1996</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>579</fpage><lpage>580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8789077</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Diewald1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diewald</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rupp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dreger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hucho</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Activation by acidic pH of CLC-7 expressed in oocytes from <named-content content-type="genus-species">Xenopus laevis</named-content>
</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2002</year><volume>291</volume><fpage>421</fpage><lpage>424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846422</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Fairman1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fairman</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandenberg</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Arriza</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kavanaugh</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Amara</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An excitatory amino-acid transporter with properties of a ligand-gated chloride channel</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1995</year><volume>375</volume><fpage>599</fpage><lpage>603</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7791878</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Fleming1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Trenor</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Foernzler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Beier</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Microcytic anaemia mice have a mutation in Nramp2, a candidate iron transporter gene</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>1997</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>386</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9241278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Fleming2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrick</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrick</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nramp2 is mutated in the anemic Belgrade (<italic>b</italic>) rat: Evidence of a role for Nramp2 in endosomal iron transport</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1998</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>1148</fpage><lpage>1153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9448300</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Gadsby1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gadsby</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rakowski</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>De Weer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extracellular access to the Na,K pump: Pathway similar to ion channel</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1993</year><volume>260</volume><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7682009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Gruenheid1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gruenheid</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Canonne-Hergaux</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hackam</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Grinstein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The iron transport protein NRAMP2 is an integral membrane glycoprotein that colocalizes with transferrin in recycling endosomes</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>1999</year><volume>189</volume><fpage>831</fpage><lpage>841</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10049947</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Grynkiewicz1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grynkiewicz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Poenie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsien</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new generation of Ca<sup>2+</sup> indicators with greatly improved fluorescence properties</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1985</year><volume>260</volume><fpage>3440</fpage><lpage>3450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3838314</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Gunshin1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gunshin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackenzie</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>UV</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunshin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cloning and characterization of a mammalian proton-coupled metal-ion transporter</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1997</year><volume>388</volume><fpage>482</fpage><lpage>488</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9242408</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Hirai1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Heymann</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Maloney</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Three-dimensional structure of a bacterial oxalate transporter</article-title><source>Nat Struct Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>597</fpage><lpage>600</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12118242</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Hodgkin1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hodgkin</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Horowicz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Movements of Na and K in single muscle fibres</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>1959</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>432</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13642309</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Kaplan1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Sturrock</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of the transferrin-independent iron transport system in cultured cells</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1991</year><volume>266</volume><fpage>2997</fpage><lpage>3004</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1993673</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Kozak1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kozak</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerschbaum</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cahalan</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distinct properties of CRAC and MIC channels in RBL cells</article-title><source>J Gen Physiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12149283</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Lester1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lester</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dougherty</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New views of multi-ion channels</article-title><source>J Gen Physiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9450937</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Levy1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transferrin receptor is necessary for development of erythrocytes and the nervous system</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>1999</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>396</fpage><lpage>399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10192390</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Lewis1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ion-concentration dependence of the reversal potential and the single channel conductance of ion channels at the frog neuromuscular junction</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>1979</year><volume>286</volume><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>445</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">312319</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Monaghan1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Monaghan</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mintenig</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sepulveda</surname><given-names>FV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Outwardly rectifying Cl<sup>&#x02013;</sup> channel in guinea pig small intestinal villus enterocytes: Effect of inhibitors</article-title><source>Am J Physiol</source><year>1997</year><volume>273</volume><issue>Suppl</issue><fpage>G1141</fpage><lpage>G1152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9374713</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Neher1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neher</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Correction for liquid junction potentials in patch clamp experiments</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol</source><year>1992</year><volume>207</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1528115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Nelson1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sacher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The significance of molecular slips in transport systems</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>876</fpage><lpage>881</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12415305</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Picard1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Picard</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Govoni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Jabado</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gros</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nramp2 (DCT1/DMT1) expressed at the plasma membrane transports iron and other divalent cations into a calcein-accessible cytoplasmic pool</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>35738</fpage><lpage>35745</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10942769</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Prakriya1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prakriya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Separation and characterization of currents through store-operated CRAC channels and Mg<sup>2+</sup>-inhibited cation (MIC) channels</article-title><source>J Gen Physiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>507</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11981025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Sacher1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sacher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Properties of the mammalian and yeast metal-ion transporters DCT1 and Smf1p expressed in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Xenopus laevis</named-content> oocytes</article-title><source>J Exp Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>204</volume><fpage>1053</fpage><lpage>1061</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11222124</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Sather1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sather</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>McCleskey</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Permeation and selectivity in calcium channels</article-title><source>Annu Rev Physiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12471162</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Su1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Trenor</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The G185R mutation disrupts function of the iron transporter Nramp2</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>1998</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>2157</fpage><lpage>2163</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9731075</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Tandy1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tandy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Leggett</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez-Jimenez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dedes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nramp2 expression is associated with pH-dependent iron uptake across the apical membrane of human intestinal Caco-2 cells</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>1023</fpage><lpage>1029</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10625641</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020050-Touret1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Touret</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Furuya</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gros</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Grinstein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamic traffic through the recycling compartment couples the metal transporter Nramp2 (DMT1) with the transferrin receptor</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>25548</fpage><lpage>25557</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12724326</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>CRAC</term><def><p>Ca<sup>2+</sup>-release activated Ca<sup>2+</sup> channel</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DIDS</term><def><p>diisothiocyanostilbene 2,2-disolphonic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DMT1</term><def><p>divalent metal transporter-1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EGFP</term><def><p>enhanced green fluorescent protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>E<sub>rev</sub></term><def><p>reversal potential</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>I<sub>G185R</sub></term><def><p>inward current mediated by the G185R mutant DMT1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>I-V</term><def><p>current&#x02013;voltage</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>mk</italic></term><def><p>microcytic</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NMDG</term><def><p>
<italic>N</italic>-methyl-D-glucamine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RR</term><def><p>ruthenium red</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TM</term><def><p>transmembrane</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TRP</term><def><p>transient receptor potential</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VGCC</term><def><p>voltage-gated Ca<sup>2+</sup> channel</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></back></article>