<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">pbio</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosbiol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1544-9173</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1545-7885</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">14966529</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">340938</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0020022</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Cancer Biology</subject><subject>Cell Biology</subject><subject>Genetics/Genomics/Gene Therapy</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="System Taxonomy"><subject>Mus (Mouse)</subject><subject>Homo (Human)</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>pRb Inactivation in Mammary Cells Reveals Common Mechanisms for Tumor Initiation and Progression in Divergent Epithelia</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">pRb and p53 in Mammary Tumor Suppression</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Simin</surname><given-names>Karl</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Hua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="n4">&#x000a4;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Lucy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pinkel</surname><given-names>Dan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Albertson</surname><given-names>Donna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cardiff</surname><given-names>Robert D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Dyke</surname><given-names>Terry Van</given-names></name><email>tvdlab@med.unc.edu</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><bold>1</bold><institution>Department of Genetics, Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</institution><addr-line>The University of North Carolina School of Medicine, Chapel Hill, North Carolina</addr-line><country>United States of America</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><bold>2</bold><institution>Comprehensive Cancer Center, University of California</institution><addr-line>San Francisco, San Francisco, California</addr-line><country>United States of America</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><bold>3</bold><institution>Center for Comparative Medicine, University of California</institution><addr-line>Davis, Davis, California</addr-line><country>United States of America</country></aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>2</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>17</day><month>2</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>e22</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>9</month><year>2003</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>12</month><year>2003</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9;2004 Simin et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2004</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="d35e193" related-article-type="companion" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pbio.0020059" xlink:title="synopsis" vol="2" page="e59">
<article-title>A New Breast Cancer Model</article-title>
</related-article><abstract><p>Retinoblastoma 1 (pRb) and the related pocket proteins, retinoblastoma-like 1 (p107) and retinoblastoma-like 2 (p130) (pRb<sub>f</sub>, collectively), play a pivotal role in regulating eukaryotic cell cycle progression, apoptosis, and terminal differentiation. While aberrations in the pRb-signaling pathway are common in human cancers, the consequence of pRb<sub>f</sub> loss in the mammary gland has not been directly assayed in vivo. We reported previously that inactivating these critical cell cycle regulators in divergent cell types, either brain epithelium or astrocytes, abrogates the cell cycle restriction point, leading to increased cell proliferation and apoptosis, and predisposing to cancer. Here we report that mouse mammary epithelium is similar in its requirements for pRb<sub>f</sub> function; Rb<sub>f</sub> inactivation by T<sub>121</sub>, a fragment of SV40 T antigen that binds to and inactivates pRb<sub>f</sub> proteins, increases proliferation and apoptosis. Mammary adenocarcinomas form within 16 mo. Most apoptosis is regulated by p53, which has no impact on proliferation, and heterozygosity for a <italic>p53</italic> null allele significantly shortens tumor latency. Most tumors in <italic>p53</italic> heterozygous mice undergo loss of the wild-type <italic>p53</italic> allele. We show that the mechanism of <italic>p53</italic> loss of heterozygosity is not simply the consequence of Chromosome 11 aneuploidy and further that chromosomal instability subsequent to <italic>p53</italic> loss is minimal. The mechanisms for pRb and p53 tumor suppression in the epithelia of two distinct tissues, mammary gland and brain, are indistinguishable. Further, this study has produced a highly penetrant breast cancer model based on aberrations commonly observed in the human disease.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="toc"><p>Inactivation of the three retinoblastoma genes in the mouse mammary gland provides a new animal model for human breast cancer</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Aberrant retinoblastoma 1 (pRb) pathway activity, resulting from defects in pRb itself, cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor 2A (p16<sup>INK4a</sup>), cyclin D1 (CCND1), or cyclin-dependent kinase 4 (CDK4), is observed in the majority of human sporadic cancers (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Marshall1" ref-type="bibr">Marshall 1991</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Weinberg1" ref-type="bibr">Weinberg 1995</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Sherr1" ref-type="bibr">Sherr 1996</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Ortega1" ref-type="bibr">Ortega et al. 2002</xref>). This pathway is commonly altered early in cancer development, indicating an ability to predispose cells to tumorigenesis. However, whether the mechanism(s) is similar among cell types is not known. Examination of pRb inactivation in specific cell types in vivo has been technically challenging due to the apparent functional compensation or redundancy among pRb, retinoblastoma-like 1 (p107), and retinoblastoma-like 2 (p130) in many cell types of the mouse (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Luo1" ref-type="bibr">Luo et al. 1998</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Robanus-Maandag1" ref-type="bibr">Robanus-Maandag et al. 1998</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Dannenberg1" ref-type="bibr">Dannenberg et al. 2000</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Sage1" ref-type="bibr">Sage et al. 2000</xref>). Thus, genetic inactivation of the <italic>Rb</italic> gene alone, either by conditional deletion (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Marino1" ref-type="bibr">Marino et al. 2000</xref>) or by the generation of chimeric mice harboring pRb-deficient cells (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Maandag1" ref-type="bibr">Maandag et al. 1994</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Williams1" ref-type="bibr">Williams et al. 1994</xref>) yields only medulloblastomas, pituitary, and thyroid tumors.</p><p>We have begun to systematically examine the role of retinoblastoma protein family (pRb<sub>f</sub>) inactivation in multiple cell types of the mouse by dominant expression of T<sub>121</sub>, a truncation mutant of simian virus 40 (SV40) T antigen that inactivates all three pRb-related proteins (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-DeCaprio1" ref-type="bibr">DeCaprio et al. 1989</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Dyson2" ref-type="bibr">Dyson et al. 1989</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Ewen1" ref-type="bibr">Ewen et al. 1989</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Stubdal1" ref-type="bibr">Stubdal et al. 1997</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Sullivan1" ref-type="bibr">Sullivan et al. 2000</xref>). In this report we determine the role of pRb inactivation in mammary adenocarcinoma predisposition, establish a role for p53 inactivation in subsequent mammary adenocarcinoma progression, and, together with our previous studies, provide a comprehensive comparison of these mechanisms in distinct epithelial lineages.</p><p>pRb plays a critical role in eukaryotic cell cycle progression, when cells exit G0 or G1 and enter S phase, thereby acting as a crucial negative regulator of cellular proliferation and neoplasia (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Sherr2" ref-type="bibr">Sherr and McCormick 2002</xref>). In quiescent or early G1-phase cells, pRb is hypophosphorylated and associates with specific members of the E2F transcription factor family, converting them to active transcriptional repressors (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Hamel1" ref-type="bibr">Hamel et al. 1992</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Weintraub1" ref-type="bibr">Weintraub et al. 1992</xref>). Gene repression is also mediated by pRb and p130 recruitment of histone deacetylase to promote formation of inhibitory nucleosomes (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Brehm1" ref-type="bibr">Brehm et al. 1998</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Luo1" ref-type="bibr">Luo et al. 1998</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Magnaghi-Jaulin1" ref-type="bibr">Magnaghi-Jaulin et al. 1998</xref>). The many proteins found in association with pRb suggest other regulatory mechanisms may also be involved (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Morris1" ref-type="bibr">Morris and Dyson 2001</xref>), although the biological potential for most of these interactions remains yet unproven. Cell cycle progression from G to S phase occurs when complexes of D-type cyclins/CDK4/CDK6 phosphorylate pRb, thereby derepressing E2Fs to direct transcription of DNA-replication machinery and nucleotide biosynthesis genes (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Dyson1" ref-type="bibr">Dyson 1998</xref>).</p><p>Like most human solid tumors, breast cancers harbor frequent alterations in the pRb pathway, including CCND1 overexpression in 45% (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Buckley1" ref-type="bibr">Buckley et al. 1993</xref>), p16<sup>INK4A</sup> loss in 49% (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Geradts1" ref-type="bibr">Geradts and Wilson 1996</xref>), and pRb loss in 6% of breast tumors (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Geradts1" ref-type="bibr">Geradts and Wilson 1996</xref>). In the <italic>Rb</italic>-deficient mouse mammary gland, p107 and/or p130 may play overlapping or compensatory roles, as they do during embryonic development, given that pRb is dispensable for normal mammary development and mammary tumor suppression. pRb-deficient embryonic stem cells participate in normal mammary gland formation in chimeric mice (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Maandag1" ref-type="bibr">Maandag et al. 1994</xref>), and donor <italic>pRb<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mammary precursor cells transplanted into wild-type mice can populate a normal mammary gland without evidence of neoplasia, even after multiple pregnancies (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Robinson1" ref-type="bibr">Robinson et al. 2001</xref>).</p><p>The interplay between pRb signaling and the tumor protein p53 pathway is also critical to the understanding of breast cancer biology. Since the pRb pathway is defective in a majority of human tumors and the <italic>p53</italic> gene is mutated in about half of them, including approximately a fifth of sporadic breast cancers (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Nigro1" ref-type="bibr">Nigro et al. 1989</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Greenblatt1" ref-type="bibr">Greenblatt et al. 1994</xref>), these aberrations often coexist. Whether loss of these tumor suppressor pathways collaborate in tumorigenesis is also cell type-specific. In a brain epithelial tumor model, we previously demonstrated that, in the absence of pRb<sub>f</sub> function, inactivation of p53 significantly decreases apoptosis and accelerates tumor growth in vivo (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Symonds3" ref-type="bibr">Symonds et al. 1994</xref>). However, in astrocytic brain tumors induced by pRb<sub>f</sub> inactivation, tumor progression is not accelerated by reduced p53 activity; rather, the phosphatase and tensin homolog (<italic>PTEN</italic>) regulates the apoptosis, and reduction in its function accelerates tumor growth (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Xiao1" ref-type="bibr">Xiao et al. 2002</xref>).</p><p>In this report, we extend our analysis of pRb function in vivo and examine the consequence of pRb<sub>f</sub> loss specifically in mammary epithelium. These studies serve not only to provide insight into the cell specificity of tumor suppression mechanisms, but also to model the stepwise evolution of breast adenocarcinomas that harbor defects in this pathway.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Generation of Mice with Inducible pRb<sub>f</sub> Deficiency in Mammary Cells</title><p>Seven founder mice were generated in which the <italic>T<sub>121</sub></italic> gene was regulated by the whey acidic protein (WAP) transcriptional signals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g001">Figure 1</xref>; see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>). Of these, two founder animals died spontaneously of unknown causes, while the transgenic progeny of the third line died prematurely, also of unknown cause (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g002">Figure 2</xref>A). The extent to which the transgene contributed to these deaths was not investigated further; however, ectopic transgene expression was detected in several tissues (data not shown). Characterization of female mice of the four remaining lines is the focus of this report.</p><fig id="pbio-0020022-g001" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Diagram of the <italic>WAP-T<sub>121</sub></italic> Transgene and Protein</title><p>The fragment consists of the 2.4 kb WAP promoter (hatched) and the mutant SV40 T-antigen coding region (white box) containing two deletions, the 196-bp amino-terminal deletion, which abolishes small t antigen production, and the <italic>dl</italic>1137 deletion, which truncates T antigen. Both the J domain and the LXCXE domain are required for pRb family inactivation (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020022.g001"/></fig><fig id="pbio-0020022-g002" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Expression of T<sub>121</sub> Protein in <italic>WAP-T<sub>121</sub></italic> Mice and a Summary of Gross Phenotypes</title><p>As expected, each line showed mammary-specific expression following lactation induction, while line 4 showed more widespread expression, with protein detected in brain and kidney. Mice from the higher-expressing lines 3 and 4 failed to nurse because of lactation defects. Mammary glands of adult female mice from all four lines showed elevated proliferation and apoptosis. Glands from line 1 and 2 mice were hyperplastic, while glands from lines 3 and 4 were atrophic. Lines 3 and 4 later developed carcinomas and other neoplasms. T<sub>121</sub> protein was detected by Western blot analysis in lactating mammary glands of animals from all four lines (B), although the lower-expressing lines 1 and 2 required immunoprecipitation with anti-T-antigen antibody prior to Western blot analysis (right panel in [B]). Brain tumor extract (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>) was used for a positive control, and nontransgenic mammary tissue extract was used for a negative control. A timecourse analysis of T<sub>121</sub> expression (C) shows lactation-induced expression peaking at 5 d postpartum.</p><p>
<bold>Abbreviations:</bold> Adeno-Ca, adenocarcinoma; AP, elevated apoptosis in mammary gland; At, atrophy; dpc, postcoital; FTN, failure to nurse; Hyp, hyperplastic acini; MG, mammary gland; MIN, mammary epithelia neoplasia; ND, not determined; nt, nontransgenic; pp, postpartum; Pr, elevated proliferation in mammary gland; pw, post-weaning.</p><p>
<bold> Footnotes:</bold>
<sup>a</sup>Mosaic founder animal.<sup>b</sup>At earlier stages, development defects attributed to atrophy, while MIN and adenocarcinoma were observed at terminal stages.<sup>c</sup>Approximately half of progeny died of unknown cause.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020022.g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>T<sub>121</sub> Is Expressed in Lactating Mammary</title><p>Western immunoblotting analyses of mammary gland extracts demonstrated that this tissue expresses T<sub>121</sub> protein at the expected size in all four lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g002">Figure 2</xref>B). T<sub>121</sub> expression in lines 1 and 2 was only revealed following immunoprecipitation using an anti-T-antigen antibody prior to Western blot analysis, indicating lower levels of T<sub>121</sub> (right panel in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g002">Figure 2</xref>B). A survey of select tissues showed that detectable expression was restricted to the mammary gland in lines 1&#x02013;3, while expression was more widespread in the higher expressing line 4 (data not shown) and included brain and kidney expression. As expected, T<sub>121</sub> expression was induced by lactation with highest levels observed 5 d postpartum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g002">Figure 2</xref>C). Southern blot analyses indicate that mice in line 3, which was used as a representative line for extensive characterization, harbor approximately ten copies of the transgene at a single insertion site (data not shown).</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Impact of Rb<sub>f </sub>Inactivation in Mammary Epithelium </title><p>Representative histological analysis of lactating mammary glands (day 1) from single-pregnancy females of the line 2 founder (F<sub>0</sub>) and a line 3 F<sub>1</sub> mouse shows that the impact of <italic>Rb</italic> perturbation is severalfold. Compared to an age- and parity-matched control tissue, the normal architecture of the lactating mammary tissue is disturbed. In contrast to normal tissue where acini consist of a single layer of secretory epithelia with milk-filled lumen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g003">Figure 3</xref>A), transgenic animals have a lower density of acini (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g003">Figure 3</xref>K), consistent with atrophy, and are often atypical (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g003">Figure 3</xref>I). T<sub>121</sub>-positive mammary epithelial cells were associated with abnormalities (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g003">Figure 3</xref>B, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g003">3</xref>F, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g003">3</xref>J). The line 2 F<sub>0</sub> animal was mosaic for T<sub>121</sub> protein expression with distinct regions of expressing and nonexpressing cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g003">Figure 3</xref>F), whereas T<sub>121</sub> expression in the line 3 animal was in secretory epithelium distributed throughout the gland (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g003">Figure 3</xref>J). Increased proliferation, indicated by proliferating cell nuclear antigen (PCNA) staining, was also observed in transgenic mammary glands (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g003">Figure 3</xref>C, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g003">3</xref>G, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g003">3</xref>K), concomitant with increased levels of apoptosis assayed by TUNEL staining (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g003">Figure 3</xref>D, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g003">3</xref>H, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g003">3</xref>L). Quantification of T<sub>121</sub> expression and apoptosis revealed higher protein expression levels (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g002">Figure 2</xref>B) correlate with higher percentages of apoptotic cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g004">Figure 4</xref>A). Consistent with a model for cell-autonomous functioning of T<sub>121</sub>, the pattern of abnormalities of morphology, proliferation, and apoptosis in the mosaic animal mimicked the regionalized T<sub>121</sub> expression pattern, and conversely, where T<sub>121</sub> protein was absent, the tissue appeared normal.</p><fig id="pbio-0020022-g003" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Mammary-Specific Inactivation of the pRb Pathway Induces Extensive Abnormalities</title><p>Histologic comparisons of nontransgenic (A&#x02013;D), mosaic (F<sub>0</sub> line 2 [E&#x02013;H]), and transgenic (F<sub>1</sub>, line 3 [I&#x02013;L]) lactating mammary glands reveals that T<sub>121</sub> expression results in increased proliferation and apoptosis. Hemotoxylin and eosin staining shows acini of the normal lactating gland are composed of a single layer of secretory epithelial cells (A) with milk-filled lumen. Consistent with atrophy, transgenic animals have a lower density of acini demonstrated by the presence of lipid-filled adipocytes (asterisk in [K]). Acini composed of T<sub>121</sub>-expressing cells are atypical. Many are collapsed and composed of tall columnar epithelia of large hyperchromatic cells with papillary tufting (arrows in [I]). Transgene-expressing cells have large pleomorphic nuclei (open arrows in [G]) as compared to nuclei of nonexpressing cells (arrows in [G]). Staining for T<sub>121</sub> expression (blue in [B]&#x02013;[J]) indicates the line 2 F<sub>0</sub> animal is mosaic, showing localized expression (F), whereas the transgene expresses throughout the gland of an F<sub>1</sub> line 3 animal (J). Increased proliferation assayed by PCNA staining (red) is also localized in the mosaic founder (G), but found throughout the F<sub>1</sub> transgenic gland (K). Similarly, TUNEL staining (brown) demonstrates increased apoptosis in transgenic animals (H and L); moreover, the regionalized apoptosis in the mosaic gland (H) strongly suggests that transgene expression and not precocious involution is the cause. All samples are from primiparous females on lactation day 1.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020022.g003"/></fig><fig id="pbio-0020022-g004" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Reduced p53 Activity Decreases Apoptosis but Does Not Increase Proliferation</title><p>Representative apoptosis levels of each mouse line correlate with T<sub>121</sub> expression as indicated by the percentage of TUNEL positive cells (A). Decreasing levels of p53 activity correlate with lower levels of apoptosis in transgenic mammary glands (B). The mean percentage of apoptotic cells in <italic>p53</italic> wild-type transgenic glands was 21%; in <italic>p53</italic> heterozygous animals, 9%; and in <italic>p53</italic> null animals, 5% (B), indicating that 75% of the apoptosis is p53-dependent. Apoptosis levels are further reduced to 2% in terminal stage tumors (B, Tumors). The percentage of PCNA staining cells remains unchanged in <italic>p53</italic> heterozygous or nullizygous animals (C), indicating that reduction of p53 activity levels had no significant impact on cell proliferation. Samples were derived from primiparous animals on lactation day 1, except as indicated as tumor samples (B). Transgenic animals in (B) and (C) were from line 3.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020022.g004"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Role of p53 in Apoptosis</title><p>To investigate the impact of germline loss of p53 on apoptosis levels in Rb<sub>f</sub>-deficient mammary glands, we mated line 3 animals to <italic>p53</italic> null mice to generate transgenic and nontransgenic females of distinct <italic>p53</italic> genotypes (+/+, +/&#x02212;, &#x02212;/&#x02212;). Transgene expression was induced by a single pregnancy, and mammary glands were examined on lactation day 1. As expected, nontransgenic mammary glands showed no appreciable apoptosis regardless of <italic>p53</italic> status (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g004">Figure 4</xref>B). However, in transgenic animals, decreased levels of p53 activity were correlated with lower levels of apoptosis. The mean percentage of apoptotic cells in <italic>p53</italic> wild-type transgenic glands was 21%; in <italic>p53</italic> heterozygous animals, 9%;and in <italic>p53</italic> null animals, 5% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g004">Figure 4</xref>B), indicating that 75% of the apoptosis is p53-dependent. That we could detect haploinsufficiency of <italic>p53</italic> for apoptosis is remarkable, since in the previously characterized T<sub>121</sub>-expressing choroid plexus epithelium, apoptosis levels were the same in <italic>p53</italic> heterozygous and wild-type backgrounds (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Lu1" ref-type="bibr">Lu et al. 2001</xref>). This observation indicates that there is a threshold for p53 levels in eliciting apoptosis and that either the threshold is different between cell types or that the absolute functional p53 level is distinct. Such differences could have significant impact on the requirements for tumorigenesis.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Role of p53 in Proliferation</title><p>In two other transgenic mouse models of breast cancer, where tumors were initiated by activated Harvey rat sarcoma viral oncogene homolog (v<italic>-Ha-ras</italic>) (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Hundley1" ref-type="bibr">Hundley et al. 1997</xref>) or <italic>wingless</italic>-related murine mammary tumor virus (MMTV) integration site 1 (<italic>Wnt-1</italic>) (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Donehower1" ref-type="bibr">Donehower et al. 1995</xref>), inactivation of p53 did not result in a reduction of apoptosis; rather, loss of p53 was associated with increased proliferation of the mammary epithelium. To determine whether p53 inactivation also impacted mammary cell proliferation induced by Rb<sub>f</sub> inactivation, glands from primiparous lactating (day 1) mice were assessed for the expression of nuclear PCNA. Unlike the tumors initiated by activated <italic>Ras</italic> or <italic>Wnt-1</italic>, <italic>p53</italic> heterozygosity or nullizygosity had no significant impact on the level of cell proliferation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g004">Figure 4</xref>C). This experiment indicates that p53 can have distinct mechanisms of action depending on the nature of the initiating lesion.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>pRb Inactivation Predisposes to Tumorigenesis</title><p>All females from higher-expressing lines (lines 3 and 4) failed to nurse pups because of lactation defects and developed mammary tumors after multiple pregnancies. Because line 4 mice expressed T<sub>121</sub> in nonmammary tissues, further characterization focused on line 3. For this line, the median time following initial transgene induction until a palpable tumor appeared was 10 mo, and within 16 mo, all mice developed palpable tumors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g005">Figure 5</xref>A). Interestingly, latency in this line on a BALB/cJ background (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>) was reduced to a median time of 8.5 mo (<italic>p</italic> = 0.0077; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g005">Figure 5</xref>A) indicating the presence of modifier alleles. The condensed timeframe for tumor development in this strain will also be valuable for future preclinical studies using this model. However, all further studies in the current report were carried out on the original B6D2F1 background.</p><fig id="pbio-0020022-g005" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Mammary Tumor Onset and Growth Are Accelerated by p53 Reduction</title><p>Among line 3 animals, the median time following initial transgene induction until a palpable tumor appeared was 10 mo, and within 16 mo, all mice developed palpable tumors (red line in [A]). In <italic>p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic> transgenic animals (blue line in [A]), mammary tumors were detected significantly earlier (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0003) with a median onset of 6 mo. Among mice with BALB/cJ background (black line in [A]), median mammary tumor latency (8.5 mo) was significantly shorter (<italic>p</italic> = 0.0077) compared to mice of the hybrid BDF1 background strain and indistinguishable (<italic>p</italic> = 0.2466) from <italic>WAP-T</italic>
<italic><sub>121</sub></italic>
<italic>;p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice. Once palpable, <italic>WAP-T</italic>
<italic><sub>121</sub></italic>
<italic>;p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic> tumors grew faster than the <italic>p53</italic> wild-type counterparts (B). The average growth rates for <italic>p53<sup>+/+</sup></italic> (black solid) and <italic>p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic> (dashed) are indicated.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020022.g005"/></fig><p>The median onset for mammary tumors in line 4 was 14 mo (<italic>n</italic> = 3; data not shown), which indicates that the transgene and not its insertion caused tumorigenesis. With two exceptions, line 3 <italic>WAP-T<sub>121 </sub></italic>mice, regardless of <italic>p53</italic> status, developed a single palpable tumor (87% of <italic>p53<sup>+/+</sup></italic>, <italic>n</italic> = 15; 78% of <italic>p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic>, <italic>n</italic> = 9). A single mouse with either two or three palpable tumors was also observed in both <italic>p53</italic> +/+ and +/&#x02212; backgrounds. At least one additional nonpalpable tumor was visible during necropsy in approximately one-third of all tumor-bearing mice. While the two lower-expressing lines, lines 1 and 2, were able to nurse pups and appeared grossly normal, both had hyperplastic lobular alveoli associated with increased levels of proliferation and apoptosis. However, females from low-expressing lines did not develop adenocarcinomas after at least four pregnancies and 20 mo of age (line 1, <italic>n</italic> = 2; line 2, <italic>n</italic> = 6) (data not shown).</p><p>Most terminal stage tumors in either wild-type or <italic>p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic> backgrounds were adenocarcinomas (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g006">Figure 6</xref>A, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g006">6</xref>B, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g006">6</xref>E); however, we also observed four pilar tumors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g006">Figure 6</xref>C and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g006">6</xref>E) and one spindle cell carcinoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g006">Figure 6</xref>D and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g006">6</xref>E). Terminal-stage mammary adenocarcinomas resembled poorly to moderately differentiated invasive ductal adenocarcinoma in humans. Morphologically, we designate these tumors as mixed solid and glandular carcinomas with necrosis and fibrosis. Poorly differentiated solid tumors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g006">Figure 6</xref>A) are composed of nests of epithelial cells with large pleomorphic nuclei and delicate chromatin patterns with inverted nuclear:cytoplasmic ratios, while glandular tumors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g006">Figure 6</xref>B) are composed of irregular glands with varying degrees of differentiation. While most animals had a single tumor mass, the adenocarcinomas were multifocal, with solid tumors consisting of subclones of distinct expansile masses, and with only two exceptions, glandular tumors were coincident with solid tumors. The adenocarcinomas were malignant, infiltrating dense, fibrous connective tissue, and were accompanied by strong peripheral immune response (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g006">Figure 6</xref>A).</p><fig id="pbio-0020022-g006" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Tumor Morphologies</title><p>Hemotoxylin and eosin staining of <italic>WAP-T<sub>121</sub></italic> (C and D) and <italic>WAP-T</italic>
<italic><sub>121</sub></italic>
<italic>p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic> (A and B) (also representative of <italic>WAP-T<sub>121</sub></italic>) tumor sections shows that terminal stage adenocarcinomas have varied morphologies. Poorly differentiated solid tumors were comprised of nests (A) or cords of epithelial cells (Tu) that infiltrate a fibrous stroma and were accompanied by necrosis (arrow) and strong immune response (arrowheads). Moderately differentiated glandular tumors (B) consisted of irregular, disorganized glands. In animals of wild-type <italic>p53</italic> background, four pilar tumors (C), distinguished by swirls of laminar acellular keratin (arrow), and a single spindle cell carcinoma (D) were also observed. For comparison, a lactating gland from a wild-type animal is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g003">Figure 3</xref>A. The percentage of animals displaying each of the phenotypes is summarized in (G). Since many tumors shared multiple morphologies, the sum exceeds 100%.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020022.g006"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>Mammary Tumor Onset and Growth Are Accelerated by p53 Reduction </title><p>Since 75% of the apoptosis induced by Rb<sub>f</sub> inactivation was mediated by <italic>p53</italic> and was indeed reduced even in <italic>p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice, we investigated the impact of <italic>p53</italic> loss on tumor onset and growth kinetics. Animals harboring either one or two <italic>p53</italic> null alleles were monitored for mammary tumors. As expected, a subset of <italic>p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic> and <italic>p53<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice developed nonmammary tumors (either thymic lymphomas or sarcomas), consistent with published reports (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Jacks1" ref-type="bibr">Jacks et al. 1994</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Sandgren1" ref-type="bibr">Sandgren et al. 1995</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Dannenberg1" ref-type="bibr">Dannenberg et al. 2000</xref>). All <italic>p53<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice (<italic>n</italic> = 4) succumbed to these tumors by 4 mo of age, prior to developing palpable mammary tumors, so acceleration of this phenotype could not be assessed. In <italic>p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic> animals, mammary tumors were detected significantly earlier (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g005">Figure 5</xref>A; <italic>p</italic> = 0.0003) compared with <italic>p53<sup>+/+</sup></italic> mice. Furthermore, once palpable, <italic>WAP-T<sub>121</sub>;p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic> tumors grew significantly faster than the <italic>p53</italic> wild-type counterparts (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g005">Figure 5</xref>B). The observation of four pilar tumors in <italic>p53<sup>+/+</sup></italic> animals and none in <italic>p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic> animals is a statistically significant difference (Fisher&#x02013;Freeman&#x02013;Halton's exact test, <italic>p</italic> = 0.0177) and suggests that the reduction of p53 activity drives tumors to the adenocarcinoma phenotype. Taken together, these studies indicate that <italic>p53</italic> heterozygosity leads to increased tumor growth rates and/or progression and may alter the spectrum of tumor morphologies.</p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title>Selective Pressure for p53 Inactivation during Adenocarcinoma Development</title><p>Since apoptosis was significantly reduced in <italic>WAP-T<sub>121</sub>;p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mammary tissue compared with that of <italic>WAP-T<sub>121</sub>;p53<sup>+/+</sup></italic> mice, it was possible that <italic>p53</italic> heterozygosity was sufficient for tumor acceleration. To assess whether this was the case or whether there was selective pressure for p53 inactivation during tumor progression, real-time PCR analysis was employed to determine the status of the wild-type <italic>p53</italic> allele in <italic>WAP-T<sub>121</sub>;p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic> tumors. Of ten tumors, eight showed loss of the wild-type <italic>p53</italic> allele (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pbio-0020022-t001">Table 1</xref>), indicating that the apoptosis reduction observed in <italic>WAP-T<sub>121</sub>;p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic>mammary epithelium was not sufficient for tumor progression. Significant selective pressure favored cells that had completely inactivated p53, indicating that tumor progression requires further reduction of apoptotic activity and/or that <italic>p53</italic> loss contributes to tumor progression through additional mechanisms that confer selective advantage. Assessment of apoptosis levels in terminal tumors showed apoptosis levels were indeed reduced in comparison to preneoplastic tissue (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g004">Figure 4</xref>B).</p><table-wrap id="pbio-0020022-t001" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>
<italic>p53</italic> LOH among the Majority of <italic>p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic> Tumors</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020022.t001"/><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><p>Real-time PCR was performed in duplicate to determine the status of the wild-type <italic>p53</italic> alleles in the mammary tumors or tissues as indicated. Analysis of standard samples indicates that copy numbers of 2, 1, and 0 are indicated by 2<sup>-&#x00394;&#x00394;Ct</sup> values of greater than or equal to 0.7, 0.2&#x02013;0.7, and less than 0.2, respectively (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Lu1" ref-type="bibr">Lu et al. 2001</xref>). Of ten <italic>WAP-T<sub>121</sub>;p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic> tumors, eight show LOH of <italic>p53</italic> gene, while all three <italic>WAP-T<sub>121</sub>;p53<sup>+/+</sup></italic> tumors retained both <italic>p53</italic> alleles. Abbreviation: Tg, transgenic</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><p>
<sup>a</sup>Tumor samples were derived from line 3 animals, except tumor 1, which was derived from a line 4 animal</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><p>
<sup>b</sup>&#x00394;&#x00394;C<sub>t</sub> = [sample C<sub>t</sub> (<italic>p53</italic>) &#x02212; sample C<sub>t</sub> (<italic>&#x003b2;-actin</italic>) ] &#x02212; [ <italic>p53<sup>+/+</sup></italic> control Ct (<italic>p53</italic>) &#x02212; <italic>p53<sup>+/+</sup></italic> control C<sub>t</sub> (<italic>&#x003b2;-actin</italic>) ]. C<sub>t</sub> = the number of cycles required to reach a threshold value, which is set within the exponential phase of the logarithmic scale amplification plot</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2i"><title>Comparative Genomic Hybridization Reveals Recurrent Chromosomal Imbalances in Tumors, but Limited Chromosomal Instability</title><p>Among the multiple mechanisms of tumor suppression attributed to p53, a common hypothesis is that p53 prevents genetic instability. Indeed, studies using other mouse models indicate loss of p53 function in tumors often correlates with chromosomal instability. These include other breast cancer models such as <italic>Wnt-1p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic> (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Donehower1" ref-type="bibr">Donehower et al. 1995</xref>) and <italic>MMTV-ras p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic> (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Hundley1" ref-type="bibr">Hundley et al. 1997</xref>) and <italic>p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic> thymic lymphomas and sarcomas (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Venkatachalam1" ref-type="bibr">Venkatachalam et al. 1998</xref>). In marked contrast, our study of p53 deficiency in an evolving brain epithelial tumor showed that tumorigenesis progresses without chromosomal instability, indicating p53 loss contributes via alternative mechanisms (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Lu1" ref-type="bibr">Lu et al. 2001</xref>). To determine whether this difference was due to cell-type specificity, differences in initiating mechanisms, or differences in experimental approaches, we analyzed the genome of mammary <italic>WAP-T<sub>121</sub>;p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic> tumors. We employed two methods of comparative genomic hybridization (CGH): chromosome-based CGH (cCGH) (Panel I in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g007">Figure 7</xref>) (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Kallioniemi1" ref-type="bibr">Kallioniemi et al. 1992</xref>) and microarray CGH (aCGH) (Panel II in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g007">Figure 7</xref>) (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Solinas-Toldo1" ref-type="bibr">Solinas-Toldo et al. 1997</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Pinkel1" ref-type="bibr">Pinkel et al. 1998</xref>).</p><fig id="pbio-0020022-g007" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>CGH Analysis Shows Limited Genomic Instability</title><p>Twelve tumors were analyzed by CGH: ten by cCGH (Panel I, A&#x02013;J), eight by aCGH (Panel II, B, C, E, and H&#x02013;L), and six by both procedures (Panels I and II, B, C, E, and H&#x02013;J). In Panel I, green and red lines adjacent to the ideograms indicate relative gain or loss, respectively. Tumor sample identities are indicated by letters above gain and loss lines. Only a single sample (Panel I, D) shows loss of Chromosome 11. Telomeric sequences of many chromosomes are increased, most frequently Chromosomes 5 and 15. Recurrent losses are seen on Chromosomes 10 and X. For aCGH (Panel II), the genomic map is depicted with chromosomes horizontally aligned centromere to telomere. The relative fluorescence intensities (tumor:normal) are indicated along the vertical axis. Individual BACs are plotted according to their physical map position versus relative fluorescence, with sample identities indicated by a unique symbol for each tumor. To simplify visualization, only BACs with relative intensities greater than 1.25 (gains) or less than 0.75 (losses) are shown. X Chromosome values were halved to account for sex-mismatched samples. Changes spanning the entire length of the chromosome are readily detected on Chromosomes 6, 8, 10, 15, 18, and X. None of the clones showing loss on Chromosome 11 spans the <italic>p53</italic> locus. The original <italic>p53</italic> background of the animal and the <italic>p53</italic> LOH status of each tumor are also indicated in the legend.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0020022.g007"/></fig><p>Twelve mammary tumors were assayed by CGH: ten by cCGH, eight by aCGH, and six by both procedures. Both assays revealed limited genomic imbalances (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g007">Figure 7</xref>), yet only a single tumor showed loss of Chromosome 11 (which harbors <italic>p53</italic>). Among samples tested by both methods, there is strong concordance among large chromosomal changes, encompassing multiple cytological bands to whole chromosome lengths. For example, there is apparent whole chromosomal duplication of Chromosomes 6 and 15 in tumor C and of Chromosomes 8 and 18 in tumor H, monosomy of Chromosome 10 in tumor J, and loss of X Chromosome in tumors E and H (all or partial, respectively). Making comparisons among imbalances spanning shorter chromosome lengths was more difficult, mainly due to the challenge of reconciling cytological and physical maps. Furthermore, technical limitations may account for real differences between the two assays: small imbalances detected by one to several bacterial artificial chromosome (BAC) clones are irresolvable by cCGH; on the other hand, the relatively low density of BAC clones may not adequately sample smaller regions detected by cCGH. Nevertheless, on average, about five imbalances per tumor were detected by cCGH. This number is comparable to the number of changes observed in myelocytomatosis oncogene (c<italic>-myc</italic>)-induced mouse mammary tumors (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Weaver1" ref-type="bibr">Weaver et al. 1999</xref>) and human tumors (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Ried1" ref-type="bibr">Ried et al. 1995</xref>), yet less than the number of changes seen in breast cancer 1 (<italic>Brca1</italic>)-deficient mouse tumors (8.0) and more than v-<italic>erb-b2</italic> erythroblastic leukemia viral oncogene homolog 2 (HER2/<italic>neu</italic>)-induced tumors (2.8) (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Montagna1" ref-type="bibr">Montagna et al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Weaver2" ref-type="bibr">Weaver et al. 2002</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Common Mechanisms for Tumor Progression in Epithelial Cells of Distinct Origin</title><p>Here we report that loss of pRb family function in mammary epithelium predisposes to malignant adenocarcinoma. Using a single transgenic allele, we have thus far inactivated the pRb pathway in several cell types in the mouse: brain choroid plexus epithelium, astrocytes, and mammary epithelium. In each case, despite the marked differences among these divergent cell types, pRb inactivation causes a similar response, initially evoking increased proliferation and apoptosis and, ultimately, predisposing to tumorigenesis (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Chen1" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al. 1992</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Saenz-Robles1" ref-type="bibr">Saenz-Robles et al. 1994</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Symonds3" ref-type="bibr">Symonds et al. 1994</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Xiao1" ref-type="bibr">Xiao et al. 2002</xref>).</p><p>Not surprisingly, the long latency of mammary adenocarcinomas indicates that additional events are required for tumor progression. We show that mammary epithelium is similar to brain epithelium (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Symonds3" ref-type="bibr">Symonds et al. 1994</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Lu1" ref-type="bibr">Lu et al. 2001</xref>) in its requirement for p53 activity in the apoptotic response to aberrant proliferation caused by pRb<sub>f</sub> inactivation. Previous models using wild-type large T antigen (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Li2" ref-type="bibr">Li et al. 1996b</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Husler1" ref-type="bibr">Husler et al. 1998</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Green1" ref-type="bibr">Green et al. 2000</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Schulze-Garg1" ref-type="bibr">Schulze-Garg et al. 2000</xref>) are unable to address the relative contribution of pRb and p53, since T antigen also binds and inactivates p53. As in brain epithelium, we show here that when the mammary tumor phenotype is initiated by pRb<sub>f</sub> inactivation, most of the apoptosis is mediated through p53. Furthermore, as in brain epithelium, heterozygosity for a null <italic>p53</italic> allele significantly shortens tumor latency (discussed further below). Importantly, the Rb<sub>f</sub> deficiency-induced apoptotic response and inhibition of tumor progression are not universally dependent on p53. In astrocytes, we recently showed that PTEN, and <italic>not</italic> p53, modulates these same responses to Rb<sub>f</sub> inactivation. In contrast to the p53-dependent apoptosis of mammary epithelial cells in response to pRb<sub>f</sub> deficiency, apoptosis associated with normal mammary involution subsequent to lactation does not require p53 (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Li1" ref-type="bibr">Li et al. 1996a</xref>). Thus, the &#x0201c;wiring&#x0201d; of the apoptotic response within this cell type is not global, but rather depends on the signal.</p><p>Although loss of p53-dependent apoptosis accounts for the acceleration of mammary tumorigenesis in <italic>WAP-T<sub>121</sub>;p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice, in models expressing either activated <italic>v-Ha-ras</italic> (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Hundley1" ref-type="bibr">Hundley et al. 1997</xref>) or <italic>Wnt-1</italic> (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Jones1" ref-type="bibr">Jones et al. 1997</xref>), earlier tumor formation in p53 heterozygous and homozygous null mice is accounted for by increased proliferation rather than attenuated apoptosis. An important caveat to this comparison is that the latter studies compared apoptosis in terminal tumors in which loss of apoptosis might have been selected regardless of initial p53 status, leaving open the possibility that tumor growth rates in these models reflect the combined effects of increased proliferation as well as reduced apoptosis. Nevertheless, there is a clear difference in <italic>WAP-T<sub>121</sub></italic> mammary gland in that, unlike the <italic>Ras</italic> and <italic>Wnt-1</italic> models, proliferation levels do not depend on <italic>p53</italic> status. Taken together, these observations indicate that the specific cellular response to an oncogenic stimulus depends on the nature of the initial insult. Given that the pRb pathway is directly disrupted in T<sub>121</sub>-expressing cells, this could be explained if these other initiating events evoke p53-dependent growth arrest which, in part, functions upstream of pRb.</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>High Selective Pressure for p53 Inactivation in the Transition to Aggressive Mammary Adenocarcinoma</title><p>Most of the apoptosis induced by pRb<sub>f</sub> deficiency in both mammary (75%) and brain (85%) epithelia is <italic>p53</italic>-dependent as determined by comparing <italic>p53<sup>+/+</sup></italic> and <italic>p53<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> tissue. However, while <italic>p53</italic> heterozygosity had no impact on the level of apoptosis in the brain epithelium, in the mammary gland the level was reduced by half in <italic>p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic> tissue. Given that apoptosis is the basis for selective inactivation of p53 in the brain tumor model (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Lu1" ref-type="bibr">Lu et al. 2001</xref>; X. Lu and T. Van Dyke, unpublished data), it was possible that the pressure was relieved or reduced in <italic>WAP-T<sub>121</sub>;p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice. However, aggressive adenocarcinoma growth was accelerated with 100% penetrance, and 80% of these tumors underwent selective loss of the wild-type <italic>p53</italic> allele, just as in the brain tumor model (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Lu1" ref-type="bibr">Lu et al. 2001</xref>). This result indicates that tumor progression requires more than a simple reduction in the level of apoptosis; it follows that <italic>p53</italic> may contribute to tumor suppression by multiple mechanisms.</p><p>While both mammary and brain carcinomas show high rates of <italic>p53</italic> loss of heterozygosity (LOH), the mechanism of loss may be distinct. Chromosome loss clearly explains <italic>p53</italic> LOH in the brain carcinoma model (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Lu1" ref-type="bibr">Lu et al. 2001</xref>) where nearly all tumors (greater than 90%) are monosomic for Chromosome 11, whereas only a single mammary tumor analyzed by CGH showed Chromosome 11 loss. Alternative mechanisms that may explain <italic>p53</italic> LOH in the mammary tumors include somatic recombination or chromosomal reduplication following mitotic nondisjunction. Whether these alternative routes of LOH represent bona fide tissue-specific phenomena or are due to relatively small sample sizes will require further analyses. Interestingly, most mammary tumors derived from <italic>Brca1</italic>-deficient mice lost <italic>p53</italic>; however, regions distal to <italic>p53</italic> were amplified (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Weaver2" ref-type="bibr">Weaver et al. 2002</xref>). Thus, it is possible that mammary tumor promoting factor(s) is located on distal Chromosome 11, selecting <italic>against</italic> loss.</p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Limited Chromosomal Instability in the Absence of p53</title><p>Genomic instability is a hallmark of most human solid tumors, and a widely held view is that p53 represses instability to suppress tumorigenesis, although evidence for this activity has been mostly correlative. Contrary to this model, we demonstrated previously that in the absence of p53 activity in brain epithelia, tumors progress without chromosomal instability; except for Chromosome 11 loss, in a <italic>p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic> background these carcinomas are diploid (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Lu1" ref-type="bibr">Lu et al. 2001</xref>). Here we show that mammary tumors similarly harbor limited genome-wide alterations. While the number of aberrations within the mammary tumors is small, it is intriguing that some changes are recurrent, suggesting that their accrual is causal in tumorigenesis. T<sub>121</sub>-induced mammary carcinomas harbor more genomic imbalances than brain tumors (approximately five versus approximately one). One explanation for this observation is that, because the brain is a vital organ, animals succumb to their illness when the brain tumor is at a relatively earlier stage at which fewer changes have accumulated. However, chromosome content of choroid plexus tumors passaged further in xenografts remained stable (X. Lu and T. Van Dyke, unpublished data). The converse experiment, analyses of early mammary tumors subsequent to p53 loss, will be required to determine the kinetics of chromosomal changes in this tissue.</p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>Pocket Protein Redundancy</title><p>Chimera and tissue-grafting experiments with pRb-deficient cells indicate the absence of pRb alone is not sufficient for abnormal mammary development or tumor formation (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Maandag1" ref-type="bibr">Maandag et al. 1994</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Robinson1" ref-type="bibr">Robinson et al. 2001</xref>). Yet mammary-directed overexpression of CCND1, an upstream regulator of pRb<sub>f</sub>, leads to mammary adenocarcinoma (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al. 1994</xref>). Given other recent studies indicating the possibility for compensation of pRb function by p107 and/or p130 (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Dannenberg1" ref-type="bibr">Dannenberg et al. 2000</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Sage1" ref-type="bibr">Sage et al. 2000</xref>) and the clear redundancy of function in some murine cell types (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Robanus-Maandag1" ref-type="bibr">Robanus-Maandag et al. 1998</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Xiao1" ref-type="bibr">Xiao et al. 2002</xref>), it is likely that the discrepancy among our results can be explained by overlapping functions of other family members, p107 and/or p130. In our studies, T<sub>121</sub> abrogates the activities of all <italic>Rb</italic> family members by a dominant interfering mechanism. A subtly distinct alternative explanation is that the acute loss of pRb signaling, rather than a chronic loss as of pRb during mammary development, as in the chimera and grafting models, accounts for the difference. Cell culture experiments that support this hypothesis were recently reported (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Sage2" ref-type="bibr">Sage et al. 2003</xref>). In this model, p107 and p130 may be more responsive to pRb regulatory signals during development than in the terminally differentiated tissue; therefore, the developing tissue more easily accommodates for the absence of pRb in the pool of available pocket proteins. In the <italic>WAP-T<sub>121</sub></italic> model, the gland undergoes normal development and then is subsequently subjected to acute pRb pathway loss. We presume that this scenario more closely mimics the situation of spontaneous somatic loss in adult human breast. The test of this alternative hypothesis awaits analyses of tissue-specific inactivation of pRb and the paralogous pocket proteins using conditional alleles.</p></sec><sec id="s3e"><title>A Model for Mammary Tumorigenesis Initiated by Targeting the pRb Pathway</title><p>The <italic>WAP-T<sub>121</sub></italic> model is a significant addition to the current repertoire of preclinical mammary tumor models exploring the role of pRb pathway in tumorigenesis. Despite the prevalence of pRb pathway defects in human sporadic cancers, mice harboring germline mutations of <italic>p16<sup>INK4a</sup></italic> do not develop mammary cancer (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Krimpenfort1" ref-type="bibr">Krimpenfort et al. 2001</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Sharpless1" ref-type="bibr">Sharpless et al. 2001</xref>). In addition, mammary-directed expression of CCND1 is only mildly oncogenic (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al. 1994</xref>), and as mentioned above, inactivation of pRb alone is not sufficient for tumorigenesis. Although the WAP promoter was a convenient means of directing mammary-specific expression for an initial assessment this model, it also presents the major shortcoming to this model in that expression of T<sub>121 </sub>is linked to lactogenic hormone activity, as in most existing murine mammary tumor models. Future improvements aim to direct expression of T<sub>121</sub> through hormone-independent methods. Finally, the advantage over wild-type T antigen models is that <italic>WAP-T<sub>121</sub></italic> uncouples the simultaneous inactivation of pRb and p53 and permits an assessment of the relative contributions of the individual oncogenic pathways. Testing the combinatorial effects of <italic>Rb</italic> loss and other breast cancer mutations (e.g., <italic>BRCA1</italic> and <italic>BRCA2</italic>), along with the further characterization of <italic>WAP-T<sub>121</sub></italic> tumors, should help provide additional insights into human breast cancer biology.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title/><sec id="s4a1"><title>Derivation and characterization of transgenic mice.</title><p>The 2.4 kb WAP promoter region was isolated from a WAP-TGF&#x003b1; construct (a gift from David Lee, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, United States [<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Sandgren1" ref-type="bibr">Sandgren et al. 1995</xref>]) and was cloned upstream of a 2.4 kb KpnI&#x02013;SalI fragment of the <italic>dl</italic>1137&#x02032;t plasmid (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Chen1" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al. 1992</xref>). We targeted T<sub>121</sub> expression to mammary gland using the WAP promoter, which is induced late in pregnancy and expressed during lactation (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Pittius1" ref-type="bibr">Pittius et al. 1988</xref>) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g001">Figure 1</xref>). T<sub>121</sub> contains the first 121 amino acids of the SV40 T antigen (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g001">Figure 1</xref>) that encodes a J domain and a pRb-binding domain, which together are sufficient to cause transformation by inactivating the pRb<sub>f</sub> proteins (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-DeCaprio1" ref-type="bibr">DeCaprio et al. 1989</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Dyson2" ref-type="bibr">Dyson et al. 1989</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Ewen1" ref-type="bibr">Ewen et al. 1989</xref>). Importantly, in contrast to other wild-type T antigen constructs encoding the entire SV40 early region (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Husler1" ref-type="bibr">Husler et al. 1998</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Green1" ref-type="bibr">Green et al. 2000</xref>; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Schulze-Garg1" ref-type="bibr">Schulze-Garg et al. 2000</xref>), small t antigen expression is absent due to a deletion that removes the splice acceptor site. The importance of this is demonstrated by the recent observation that small t antigen alone is sufficient for tumorigenesis in the mammary gland (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Goetz1" ref-type="bibr">Goetz et al. 2001</xref>). Furthermore, p53 and EP300 (E1A-binding protein p300), which map to the carboxyl half of T antigen, are also abolished, thus permitting assessment of pRb<sub>f</sub> inactivation without the confounding effects of altering additional suppressor pathways. An EcoRI fragment containing the full transgene (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0020022-g001">Figure 1</xref>) at a concentration of 4 ng/&#x003bc;l was injected in to fertilized eggs harvested from B6D2F1 (Jackson Laboratory, Bar Harbor, Maine, United States) mice as described previously (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Yan1" ref-type="bibr">Yan et al. 1990</xref>). Transgenic mice were identified by PCR amplification of a 160 bp fragment using primers 5&#x02032;-GAATCTTTGCAGCTAATGGACC-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-GCATCCCAGAAGCTCCAAAG-3&#x02032; with toe-derived genomic DNA as template. Cycling profile was as follows: 94&#x000b0;C, 2 min; 35 cycles of 94&#x000b0;C, 20 s; 62&#x000b0;C, 45 s; 72&#x000b0;C, 45 s; and final incubation of 72&#x000b0;C, 2 min. <italic>TgWAP-T<sub>121</sub></italic> mouse lines were maintained by crossing to nontransgenic B6D2F1 mice (Jackson Laboratory) and therefore are designated as B6;D2-Tg(WAP-T<sub>121</sub>) Tvd. To study the effect of background differences, <italic>WAP-T<sub>121</sub></italic> males were backcrossed to BALB/cJ (Jackson Laboratory) female mice. To increase sample size, tumor onset analysis for BALB/c background mice combined data for N6 (<italic>n</italic> = 6), N7 (<italic>n</italic> = 1), and N9 (<italic>n</italic> = 4) generation mice. For tumor induction, female mice, unless noted as virgin, were housed with male mice to maximize the number of pregnancies, because WAP promoter activity is lactation-dependent (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Pittius1" ref-type="bibr">Pittius et al. 1988</xref>).</p><p>To study the effect of <italic>p53</italic> mutation on mammary tumorigenesis in <italic>WAP-T<sub>121</sub></italic> mice, male <italic>WAP-T<sub>121<sup>+</sup></sub></italic> mice were mated to <italic>p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic> females (<italic>p53<sup>tm1Tyj</sup></italic>; Jackson Laboratory). <italic>p53</italic> genotypes were determined by PCR using two reactions (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Lowe1" ref-type="bibr">Lowe et al. 1993</xref>), one that amplifies the neomycin insertion site (neomycin primer: 5&#x02032;- TCCTCGTGCTTTACGGTATC-3&#x02032;, <italic>p53</italic> primer: 5&#x02032;-TATACTCAGAGCCGGCCT-3&#x02032;; 525 bp product) and a second that amplifies the endogenous <italic>p53</italic> allele (substituting 5&#x02032;-ACAGCGTGGTGGTACCTTAT-3&#x02032; for the <italic>neo</italic> primer, 475 bp product). Cycling parameters were the same as the above <italic>WAP-T<sub>121</sub></italic> reaction. We performed the cross <italic>WAP-T<sub>121<sup>&#x02212;</sup></sub>;p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic> &#x000d7; <italic>WAP-T<sub>121<sup>+</sup></sub>;p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup>,</italic> and transgenic female mice that were <italic>p53<sup>+/+</sup></italic>, <italic>p53<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup></italic>, or <italic>p53<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> were used for analyses while nontransgenic littermates served as controls.</p></sec><sec id="s4a2"><title>Western immunoblotting analysis.</title><p>Protein expression levels were assayed as previously described (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Symonds2" ref-type="bibr">Symonds et al. 1993</xref>). Fresh or flash-frozen tissue samples were homogenized in lysis buffer (50 mM Tris [pH 8.0], 5 mM EDTA, 150 mM NaCl , and 1% NP-40) using a Polytron<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> homogenizer (Kinematica, Littau-Lucerne, Switzerland). Total protein (10 &#x003bc;g) was electrophoresed through a 15% polyacrylamide denaturing gel and then transferred to nitrocellulose membrane (15 V, 30 min). Alternatively, for low-expressing lines, immunoprecipitation was performed prior to electrophoresis as previously described (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Symonds1" ref-type="bibr">Symonds et al. 1991</xref>). The filter was preincubated in 3% bovine serum albumin, followed by incubation with primary antibody against SV40 T antigen (PAb419 at a dilution of 1:5,000; <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Harlow1" ref-type="bibr">Harlow et al. 1981</xref>). The filter was then washed, followed by incubation at room temperature with horseradish peroxidase-conjugated goat anti-mouse IgG (Amersham Biosciences, Little Chalfont, United Kingdom). The enhanced chemiluminescence method (Amersham Biosciences) was used for autoradiography.</p></sec><sec id="s4a3"><title>Histopathology and immunohistochemistry.</title><p>Mammary tissue and tumor samples were dissected from <italic>WAP-T<sub>121</sub></italic> transgenic or age- and parity-matched B6D2F1 animals. A portion of each tumor was flash-frozen in liquid nitrogen and the remaining tissue was fixed in 10% phosphate buffered formalin, embedded in paraffin, cut to a 5-&#x003bc;m thickness, and stained with hemotoxylin and eosin or immunostained using the Vector ABC system (Vector Laboratories, Burlingame, California, United States) for histopathological examination. Apoptosis levels were evaluated by TUNEL assay (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Gavrieli1" ref-type="bibr">Gavrieli et al. 1992</xref>) essentially as described in <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Symonds3" ref-type="bibr">Symonds et al. (1994</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4a4"><title>Real-time PCR.</title><p>Quantitative real-time PCR analysis was performed using a TaqMan approach on DNA derived from terminal tumors to determine the status of the wild-type <italic>p53</italic> allele as previously described (<xref rid="pbio-0020022-Lu1" ref-type="bibr">Lu et al. 2001</xref>). The primers for the <italic>p53</italic> allele were 5&#x02032;-ATGGCCATCTACAAGAAGTCACAG-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-ATCGGAGCAGCGCTCATG-3&#x02032;. The sequence of the <italic>p53</italic> probe was 5&#x02032;-ACATGACGGAGGTCGTGAGACGCTG-3&#x02032;. The primers for the internal control <italic>&#x003b2;-actin</italic> gene were 5&#x02032;-AAGAGCTATGAGCTGCCTGA-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-ACGGATGTCAACGTCACACT-3&#x02032;. The sequence of the <italic>&#x003b2;-actin</italic> probe was 5&#x02032;-CACTATTGGCAACGAGCGGTTCCG-3&#x02032;. Each 25-&#x003bc;l reaction mixture contained 50 ng of DNA template, 18 nM <italic>p53</italic> primers, 80 nM <italic>&#x003b2;-actin</italic> primers, 8 nM probe, and 12.5 &#x003bc;l of TaqMan Universal PCR Master Mix (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, California, United States) containing AmpliTaq Gold polymerase, deoxynucleoside triphosphates, and PCR buffer. The cycling conditions were 50&#x000b0;C for 2 min and 95&#x000b0;C for 10 min for 1 cycle, and 95&#x000b0;C for 15 s and 60&#x000b0;C for 1 min for 40 cycles. The reactions were performed using an ABI 7700 Sequence Detection system (Applied Biosystems), and the data analyzed using Sequence Detector 1.7 (Applied Biosystems) and standard protocols (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.appliedbiosystems.com">http://www.appliedbiosystems.com</ext-link>). The copy number of each sample was determined by calculating &#x00394;&#x00394;Ct based on the formula &#x00394;&#x00394;C<sub>t</sub> = [sample C<sub>t(p53)</sub> &#x02212; sample C<sub>t(</sub>
<italic><sub>&#x003b2;-actin</sub></italic>
<sub>)</sub>] &#x02212; [p53<sup>+/+</sup> control Ct<sub>(p53)</sub> &#x02212; p53<sup>+/+</sup> control Ct<sub>(</sub>
<italic><sub>&#x003b2;-actin</sub></italic>
<sub>)</sub>], where C<sub>t</sub> is the number of cycles required to reach a threshold based on linear amplification. Analyses of standard samples (L. Chin, Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts, United States, personal communication) indicate copy numbers of 2, 1, and 0 are indicated by 2<sup>-&#x00394;Ctn</sup> values of greater than 0.6, 0.15&#x02013;0.6, and less than 0.15, respectively. Standard samples analyzed along with experimental samples confirmed the accuracy of these assignments.</p></sec><sec id="s4a5"><title>Statistical analyses.</title><p>Kaplan&#x02013;Meier survival analysis was used to determine median tumor latencies (StatsDirect, Camcode, Sale, United Kingdom), and the Log-Rank (Peto, StatsDirect) test was performed to evaluate significance. The equivalence of tumor morphology distributions was tested using the Fisher&#x02013;Freeman&#x02013;Halton's exact test.</p></sec><sec id="s4a6"><title>CGH.</title><p>Genomic DNA was extracted from end-stage tumors (1 cm in diameter) or tails using a DNeasy genomic tip (Qiagen, Valencia, California, United States) and further purified by proteinase K digestion followed by phenol/chloroform extraction, ethanol precipitation, and resuspension in sterile H<sub>2</sub>O. cCGH was performed as described in <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Kallioniemi1" ref-type="bibr">Kallioniemi et al. (1992</xref>), <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Donehower1" ref-type="bibr">Donehower et al. (1995</xref>), and <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Lu1" ref-type="bibr">Lu et al. (2001</xref>). aCGH was performed as described in <xref rid="pbio-0020022-Snijders1" ref-type="bibr">Snijders et al. (2001</xref>). For both methods, genomic DNA from tumor and normal tissue was labeled with different fluorochromes and then cohybridized together with <italic>Cot-1</italic> DNA to either normal metaphase chromosomes from cultured cells (cCGH) or microarrayed BAC clones containing mouse genomic DNA (aCGH). Nonequivalent fluorescence intensities indicate relative imbalances of genomic DNA. Aneuploidy and partial chromosome gains and losses are detectable by cCGH with approximately 10 Mb resolution. Graphical output of cCGH data was generated using the National Cancer Institute and National Center for Biotechnology Information Spectral Karyotyping <italic>SKY</italic> and Comparative Genomic Hybridization CGH Database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sky/skyweb.cgi">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sky/skyweb.cgi</ext-link>). For aCGH, approximately 1,500 BAC clones span the entire mouse genome with 2&#x02013;20 Mb spacing. Tumor DNA and normal DNA were sex-mismatched; thus, the X Chromosome served as an internal control, while normal tail DNA was used as a negative control. Gains or losses were scored based on tumor:normal fluorescence ratios that were greater than 1.25 or less than 0.75, respectively.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><sec id="s5a"><title/><sec id="s5a1"><title>Accession Numbers</title><p>The accession numbers for the genes and gene products discussed in this paper are <italic>Brca1</italic> (LocusLink ID 12189), CDK2 (LocusLink ID 1017), CDK4 (LocusLink ID 1019), CDK6 (LocusLink ID 1021), c<italic>-myc</italic> (LocusLink ID 17869), cyclin D1 (LocusLink ID 595), cyclin E (LocusLink ID 898), E2F (InterPro ID IPR003316), HER2/<italic>neu</italic> (LocusLink ID 13866), histone deacetylase (LocusLink ID 3065), p16<sup>INK4a</sup> (LocusLink ID 1029), p53 (LocusLink ID 7157), p107 (LocusLink ID 5933), p130 (LocusLink ID 5934), p300 (LocusLink ID 2033), PCNA (LocusLink ID 18538), pRb (LocusLink ID 5925), <italic>PTEN</italic> (LocusLink ID 5728), v<italic>-Ha-ras</italic> (LocusLink ID 3265), WAP (LocusLink ID 22373), and <italic>Wnt-1</italic> (LocusLink ID 22408).</p><p>These databases may be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/LocusLink/">www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/LocusLink/</ext-link> (LocusLink), and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ebi.ac.uk/InterPro/">www.ebi.ac.uk/InterPro/</ext-link> (InterPro).</p></sec></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors thank Lisa Livanos at the University of North Carolina (UNC) chromosome imaging core facility for assistance with cCGH; Joe McCarville for the assembly of the <italic>WAP-T<sub>121</sub></italic> construct; Drew Fogarty and Anne Wolthusen for expert technical assistance; the UNC histopathology core facility; the UNC Division of Laboratory Animal Medicine; Bing Huey for aCGH; and Karl Sirotkin and Vasuki Gobu at the National Center for Biotechnology Information for their assistance with cCGH data submission. We also thank Xiangdong Lu and Dale Cowley for their critical reading of the manuscript. KS was supported by a National Cancer Institute postdoctoral training grant (T32CA09156) to the Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center. This work was also supported by grants from the Susan G. Komen Breast Cancer Foundation (BCTR98), the United States Army (DAMD17&#x02013;99-1&#x02013;9332), and two grants from the National Cancer Institute, to TVD (5 R01 CA46283&#x02013;15) and to DA (CA84118).</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="n1" fn-type="COI-statement"><p>
<bold>Conflicts of interest.</bold> The authors have declared that no conflicts of interest exist.</p></fn><fn id="n2" fn-type="con"><p>
<bold>Author contributions.</bold> KS, HW, and TVD conceived and designed the experiments. KS, HW, and LL performed the experiments. KS, HW, RDC, and TVD analyzed the data. DP and DA contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools. KS and TVD wrote the paper.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="n3" fn-type="edited-by"><p>Academic Editor: Chris Marshall, Institute for Cancer Research</p></fn><fn id="n4" fn-type="current-aff"><p>&#x000a4;Current address: Phenomix Corporation, La Jolla, California, United States of America</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pbio-0020022-Brehm1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brehm</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Miska</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>McCance</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bannister</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Retinoblastoma protein recruits histone deacetylase to repress transcription</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1998</year><volume>391</volume><fpage>597</fpage><lpage>601</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9468139</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Buckley1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sweeney</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sini</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression and amplification of cyclin genes in human breast cancer</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>1993</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>2127</fpage><lpage>2133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8336939</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Chen1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tobin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pipas</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Dyke</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>T antigen mutant activities in transgenic mice: Roles of p53 and pRb-binding in tumorigenesis of the choroid plexus</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>1992</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1167</fpage><lpage>1175</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1317542</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Dannenberg1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dannenberg</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>van Rossum</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuijff</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>te Riele</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ablation of the retinoblastoma gene family deregulates G(1) control causing immortalization and increased cell turnover under growth-restricting conditions</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2000</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>3051</fpage><lpage>3064</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11114893</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-DeCaprio1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeCaprio</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ludlow</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Furukawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The product of the retinoblastoma susceptibility gene has properties of a cell-cycle regulatory element</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1989</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>1085</fpage><lpage>1095</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2673542</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Donehower1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donehower</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Godley</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Aldaz</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pyle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Deficiency of p53 accelerates mammary tumorigenesis in <italic>Wnt-1</italic> transgenic mice and promotes chromosomal instability</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1995</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>882</fpage><lpage>895</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7705663</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Dyson1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dyson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The regulation of E2F by pRb-family proteins</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1998</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>2245</fpage><lpage>2262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9694791</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Dyson2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dyson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchkovich</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Whyte</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Harlow</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cellular 107K protein that binds to adenovirus E1A also associates with the large T antigens of SV40 and JC virus</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1989</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2546678</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Ewen1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ewen</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Ludlow</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsilio</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>DeCaprio</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Millikan</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An N-terminal transformation-governing sequence of SV40 large T antigen contributes to the binding of both p110Rb and a second cellular protein, p120</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1989</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2526683</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Gavrieli1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gavrieli</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Sasson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of programmed cell death <italic>in situ</italic> via specific labeling of nuclear fragmentation</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1992</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>493</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1400587</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Geradts1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geradts</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High frequency of aberrant p16<sup>INK4A</sup> expression in human breast cancer</article-title><source>Am J Pathol</source><year>1996</year><volume>149</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8686738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Goetz1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goetz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tzeng</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Guhl</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Merker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Graessmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The SV40 small t-antigen prevents mammary gland differentiation and induces breast cancer formation in transgenic mice: Truncated large T-antigen molecules harboring the intact p53 and pRb binding region do not have this effect</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2001</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>2325</fpage><lpage>2332</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11402328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Green1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshidome</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorcyk</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The C3(1)/SV40 T-antigen transgenic mouse model of mammary cancer: Ductal epithelial cell targeting with multistage progression to carcinoma</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2000</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1020</fpage><lpage>1027</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10713685</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Greenblatt1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenblatt</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutations in the p53 tumor suppressor gene: Clues to cancer etiology and molecular pathogenesis</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>1994</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>4855</fpage><lpage>4878</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8069852</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Hamel1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamel</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallie</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The retinoblastoma protein and cell-cycle regulation</article-title><source>Trends Genet</source><year>1992</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>180</fpage><lpage>185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1369744</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Harlow1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harlow</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name><surname>Pim</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monoclonal antibodies specific for simian virus 40 tumor antigens</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>1981</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>861</fpage><lpage>869</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6169844</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Hundley1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hundley</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Koester</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Troyer</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilsenbeck</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Subler</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Increased tumor proliferation and genomic instability without decreased apoptosis in MMTV-ras mice deficient in p53</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>723</fpage><lpage>731</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9001226</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Husler1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Husler</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotopoulis</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundberg</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Tennent</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunig</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lactation-induced <italic>WAP-SV40</italic> Tag transgene expression in C57BL/6J mice leads to mammary carcinoma</article-title><source>Transgenic Res</source><year>1998</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9859214</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Jacks1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacks</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Remington</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Scmitt</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Halachmi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tumor spectrum analysis in <italic>p53</italic>-mutant mice</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>1994</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7922305</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Jones1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Attardi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Godley</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Laucirica</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Medina</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Absence of p53 in a mouse mammary tumor model promotes tumor cell proliferation without affecting apoptosis</article-title><source>Cell Growth Differ</source><year>1997</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>829</fpage><lpage>838</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9269892</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Kallioniemi1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kallioniemi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kallionemi</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Sudar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutovitz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative genomic hybridization for molecular cytogenetic analysis of solid tumors</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1992</year><volume>258</volume><fpage>818</fpage><lpage>821</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1359641</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Krimpenfort1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krimpenfort</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Quon</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mooi</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Loonstra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Berns</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Loss of p16<sup>Ink4a</sup> confers susceptibility to metastatic melanoma in mice</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2001</year><volume>413</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11544530</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Li1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Heermeier</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hennighausen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Furth</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Apoptosis and remodeling of mammary gland tissue during involution proceeds through p53-independent pathways</article-title><source>Cell Growth Differ</source><year>1996a</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8788029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Li2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Heermeier</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hennighausen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Furth</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of a viral oncoprotein during mammary gland development alters cell fate and function: Induction of p53-independent apoptosis is followed by impaired milk protein production in surviving cells</article-title><source>Cell Growth Differ</source><year>1996b</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8788028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Lowe1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacks</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>p53 is required for radiation-induced apoptosis in mouse thymocytes</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1993</year><volume>362</volume><fpage>847</fpage><lpage>849</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8479522</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Lu1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Magrane</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Louis</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Selective inactivation of p53 facilitates mouse epithelial tumor progression without chromosomal instability</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>6017</fpage><lpage>6030</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11486039</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Luo1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>RX</given-names></name><name><surname>Postigo</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>
<italic>Rb</italic> interacts with histone deacetylase to repress transcription</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1998</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>463</fpage><lpage>473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9491888</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Maandag1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maandag</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Valk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vlaar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Feltkamp</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Developmental rescue of an embryonic-lethal mutation in the retinoblastoma gene in chimeric mice</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1994</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>4260</fpage><lpage>4268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7925271</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Magnaghi-Jaulin1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Magnaghi-Jaulin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Groisman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Naguibneva</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Robin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Retinoblastoma protein represses transcription by recruiting a histone deacetylase</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1998</year><volume>391</volume><fpage>601</fpage><lpage>605</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9468140</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Marino1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vooijs</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van Der Gulden</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonkers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Berns</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of medulloblastomas in <italic>p53</italic>-null mutant mice by somatic inactivation of Rb in the external granular layer cells of the cerebellum</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2000</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>994</fpage><lpage>1004</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10783170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Marshall1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tumor suppressor genes</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1991</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1988150</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Montagna1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montagna</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrechek</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Padilla-Nash</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ried</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Centrosome abnormalities, recurring deletions of chromosome 4, and genomic amplification of HER2/<italic>neu</italic> define mouse mammary gland adenocarcinomas induced by mutant HER2/<italic>neu</italic>
</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2002</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>890</fpage><lpage>898</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11840334</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Morris1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dyson</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retinoblastoma protein partners</article-title><source>Adv Cancer Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11447760</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Nigro1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nigro</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Preisinger</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jessup</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hostetter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mutations in the <italic>p53</italic> gene occur in diverse human tumor types</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1989</year><volume>342</volume><fpage>705</fpage><lpage>708</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2531845</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Ortega1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ortega</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Malumbres</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbacid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cyclin D-dependent kinases, INK4 inhibitors and cancer</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2002</year><volume>1602</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11960696</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Pinkel1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pinkel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Segraves</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sudar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High resolution analysis of DNA copy number variation using comparative genomic hybridization to microarrays</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>1998</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9771718</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Pittius1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pittius</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hennighausen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Westphal</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicols</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A milk protein gene promoter directs the expression of human tissue plasminogen activator cDNA to the mammary gland in transgenic mice</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1988</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>5874</fpage><lpage>5878</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2842753</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Ried1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ried</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Just</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Holtgreve-Grez</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>du Manoir</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Speicher</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative genomic hybridization of formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded breast tumors reveals different patterns of chromosomal gains and losses in fibroadenomas and diploid and aneuploid carcinomas</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>1995</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>5415</fpage><lpage>5423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7585611</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Robanus-Maandag1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robanus-Maandag</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Dekker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Valk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrozza</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeanny</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>p107 is a suppressor of retinoblastoma development in pRb-deficient mice</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1998</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1599</fpage><lpage>1609</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9620848</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Robinson1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>KU</given-names></name><name><surname>Hennighausen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional mammary gland development and oncogene-induced tumor formation are not affected by the absence of the retinoblastoma gene</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2001</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>7115</fpage><lpage>7119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11704837</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Saenz-Robles1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saenz-Robles</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Symonds</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Dyke</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction versus progression of brain tumor development: Differential functions for the pRb- and p53-targeting domains of simian virus 40 T antigen</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1994</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>2686</fpage><lpage>2698</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8139568</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Sage1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sage</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulligan</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Attardi</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Targeted disruption of the three Rb-related genes leads to loss of G(1) control and immortalization</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2000</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>3037</fpage><lpage>3050</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11114892</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Sage2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sage</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez-Mancera</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wysocki</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacks</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute mutation of retinoblastoma gene function is sufficient for cell cycle reentry</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2003</year><volume>424</volume><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12853964</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Sandgren1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sandgren</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Qui</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmiter</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Brinster</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of mammary gland involution is associated with transforming growth factor alpha but not c-<italic>myc</italic>-induced tumorigenesis in transgenic mice</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>1995</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>3915</fpage><lpage>3927</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7641211</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Schulze-Garg1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schulze-Garg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gocht</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Deppert</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A transgenic mouse model for the ductal carcinoma <italic>in situ</italic> (DCIS) of the mammary gland</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2000</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1028</fpage><lpage>1037</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10713686</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Sharpless1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharpless</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bardeesy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrasco</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Castrillon</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Loss of p16<sup>Ink4a</sup> with retention of p19<sup>Arf</sup> predisposes mice to tumorigenesis</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2001</year><volume>413</volume><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11544531</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Sherr1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sherr</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cancer cell cycles</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1996</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>1672</fpage><lpage>1677</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8939849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Sherr2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sherr</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Rb and p53 pathways in cancer</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12204530</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Snijders1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snijders</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Segraves</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Blackwood</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Assembly of microarrays for genome-wide measurement of DNA copy number</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2001</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11687795</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Solinas-Toldo1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Solinas-Toldo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lampel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stilgenbauer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nickolenko</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Benner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Matrix-based comparative genomic hybridization: Biochips to screen for genomic imbalances</article-title><source>Genes Chromosomes Cancer</source><year>1997</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>399</fpage><lpage>407</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9408757</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Stubdal1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stubdal</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zalvide</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Schweitzer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inactivation of pRb-related proteins p130 and p107 mediated by the J domain of simian virus 40 large T antigen</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>4979</fpage><lpage>4990</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9271376</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Sullivan1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Trembly</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Fewell</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brodsky</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Species-specific elements in the large T-antigen J domain are required for cellular transformation and DNA replication by simian virus 40</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2000</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>5749</fpage><lpage>5757</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10891510</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Symonds1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Symonds</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Dyke</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complex formation between the lymphotropic papovavirus large tumor antigen and the tumor suppressor protein, p53</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>1991</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>5417</fpage><lpage>5424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1895390</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Symonds2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Symonds</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pipas</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Dyke</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of transgenic mice reveals cell-specific transformation by a simian virus 40 T-antigen amino-terminal mutant</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1993</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>3255</fpage><lpage>3265</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8388535</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Symonds3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Symonds</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Krall</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Remington</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Saenz-Robles</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>p53-dependent apoptosis suppresses tumor growth and progression in vivo</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1994</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>703</fpage><lpage>711</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8069917</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Venkatachalam1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Venkatachalam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Retention of wild-type <italic>p53</italic> in tumors from <italic>p53</italic> heterozygous mice: Reduction of p53 dosage can promote cancer formation</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1998</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>4657</fpage><lpage>4667</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9707425</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Wang1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardiff</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Zukerberg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lees</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mammary hyperplasia and carcinoma in MMTV-cyclin D1 transgenic mice</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1994</year><volume>369</volume><fpage>669</fpage><lpage>671</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8208295</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Weaver1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></name><name><surname>McCormack</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liyanage</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>du Manoir</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A recurring pattern of chromosomal aberrations in mammary gland tumors of MMTV&#x02013;c-<italic>myc</italic> transgenic mice</article-title><source>Genes Chromosomes Cancer</source><year>1999</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10379871</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Weaver2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Montagna</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gadina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mammary tumors in mice conditionally mutant for <italic>Brca1</italic> exhibit gross genomic instability and centrosome amplification yet display a recurring distribution of genomic imbalances that is similar to human breast cancer</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2002</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>5097</fpage><lpage>5107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12140760</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Weinberg1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The retinoblastoma protein and cell cycle control</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1995</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7736585</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Weintraub1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weintraub</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Prater</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retinoblastoma protein switches the E2F site from positive to negative element</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1992</year><volume>358</volume><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1321348</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Williams1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Remington</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bronson</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Extensive contribution of Rb-deficient cells to adult chimeric mice with limited histopathological consequences</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1994</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>4251</fpage><lpage>4259</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7925270</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Xiao1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandolfi</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Louis</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Dyke</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Astrocyte inactivation of the pRb pathway predisposes mice to malignant astrocytoma development that is accelerated by <italic>PTEN</italic> mutation</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12086874</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0020022-Yan1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Darnell</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Dyke</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distinct positive and negative elements control the limited hepatocyte and choroid plexus expression of transthyretin in transgenic mice</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1990</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>869</fpage><lpage>878</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1690125</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>aCGH</term><def><p>microarray comparative genomic hybridization</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BAC</term><def><p>bacterial artificial chromosome</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Brca1</term><def><p>breast cancer 1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>cCGH</term><def><p>chromosome comparative genomic hybridization</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CCND1</term><def><p>cyclin D1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CCNE1</term><def><p>cyclin E1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CDK2</term><def><p>cyclin-dependent kinase 2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CDK4</term><def><p>cyclin-dependent kinase 4</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CDK6</term><def><p>cyclin-dependent kinase 6</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CGH</term><def><p>comparative genomic hybridization</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>c<italic>-myc</italic></term><def><p>myelocytomatosis oncogene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LOH</term><def><p>loss of heterozygosity</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MMTV</term><def><p>murine mammary tumor virus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>p16<sup>INK4a</sup></term><def><p>cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor 2A</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PCNA</term><def><p>proliferating cell nuclear antigen</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>pRb</term><def><p>retinoblastoma 1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>pRb<sub>f</sub></term><def><p>retinoblastoma protein family</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PTEN</term><def><p>phosphatase and tensin homolog</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SV40</term><def><p>simian virus 40</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>v-<italic>erb-b2</italic></term><def><p>erythroblastic leukemia viral oncogene homolog 2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>v<italic>-Ha-ras</italic></term><def><p>Harvey rat sarcoma viral oncogene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WAP</term><def><p>whey acidic protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Wnt-1</term><def><p>
<italic>wingless</italic>-related MMTV integration site 1</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></back></article>